<references>
    <!-- This document is meant to serve as a repository for any passage in War and Peace that the musical directly takes from. 
    Ideally, the <ref> elements will have numbered elements so that lines in the XML lyric markup can be connected directly to the passages.
    At this exact moment the passages include the entire paragraph or sentence the borrowed text comes from, 
    but they can and should be whittled down or at least specified with elements to show exactly which phrases appear in the musical to make connecting
    it to the XML lyrics easier.
    Song no. correlates to the number in the XML title of the lyric doc.
    Source: https://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/2600/pg2600.txt-->
    <book n="8">
        <chapter n="1">
            <ch>CHAPTER 1</ch>
            <ref song="02">Pierre without any apparent cause suddenly felt it impossible to go on
                living as before.</ref>
            <ref song="02">Only the skeleton of life remained: his house, a brilliant wife who now
                enjoyed the favors of a very important personage, acquaintance with all Petersburg,
                and his court service with its dull formalities.</ref>
            <ref song="02">And this life suddenly seemed to Pierre unexpectedly loathsome.</ref>
            <ref song="02">In Moscow as soon as he entered his huge house in which the faded and
                fading princesses still lived, with its enormous retinue; as soon as, driving
                through the town, he saw the Iberian shrine with innumerable tapers burning before
                the golden covers of the icons, the Krémlin Square with its snow undisturbed by
                vehicles, the sleigh drivers and hovels of the Sívtsev Vrazhók, those old Moscovites
                who desired nothing, hurried nowhere, and were ending their days leisurely; when he
                saw those old Moscow ladies, the Moscow balls, and the English Club, he felt himself
                at home in a quiet haven.</ref>
            <ref song="03">Moscow society, from the old women down to the children, received Pierre
                like a long-expected guest whose place was always ready awaiting him. For Moscow
                society Pierre was the nicest, kindest, most intellectual, merriest, and most
                magnanimous of cranks, a heedless, genial nobleman of the old Russian type. His
                purse was always empty because it was open to everyone.</ref>
            <ref song="02"><q>Il est charmant; il n’a pas de sexe,</q> they said of him. <q>He is
                    charming; he has no sex.</q></ref>
            <ref song="02">Pierre was one of those retired gentlemen-in-waiting of whom there were
                hundreds good-humoredly ending their days in Moscow.</ref>
            <ref song="02">Sometimes he consoled himself with the thought that he was only living
                this life temporarily; but then he was shocked by the thought of how many, like
                himself, had entered that life and that club temporarily, with all their teeth and
                hair, and had only left it when not a single tooth or hair remained.</ref>
            <ref song="02">In moments of pride, when he thought of his position it seemed to him
                that he was quite different and distinct from those other retired
                gentlemen-in-waiting he had formerly despised: they were empty, stupid, contented
                fellows, satisfied with their position, <q>while I am still discontented and want to
                    do something for mankind. But perhaps all these comrades of mine struggled just
                    like me and sought something new, a path in life of their own, and like me were
                    brought by force of circumstances, society, and race—by that elemental force
                    against which man is powerless—to the condition I am in,</q> said he to himself
                in moments of humility; and after living some time in Moscow he no longer despised,
                but began to grow fond of, to respect, and to pity his comrades in destiny, as he
                pitied himself.</ref>
            <ref song="02">So thought Pierre, and the whole of this general deception which everyone
                accepts, accustomed as he was to it, astonished him each time as if it were
                something new. <q>I understand the deception and confusion,</q> he thought, <q>but
                    how am I to tell them all that I see? I have tried, and have always found that
                    they too in the depths of their souls understand it as I do, and only try not to
                    see it. So it appears that it must be so! But I—what is to become of
                me?</q></ref>
            <ref song="09">Though the doctors warned him that with his corpulence wine was dangerous
                for him, he drank a great deal. He was only quite at ease when having poured several
                glasses of wine mechanically into his large mouth he felt a pleasant warmth in his
                body, an amiability toward all his fellows, and a readiness to respond superficially
                to every idea without probing it deeply</ref>
            <ref song="02"><q>It doesn’t matter. I’ll get it unraveled. I have a solution ready, but
                    have no time now—I’ll think it all out later on!</q> But the later on never
                came.</ref>
            <ref song="14"><q>Nothing is trivial, and nothing is important, it’s all the same—only
                    to save oneself from it as best one can,</q> thought Pierre. <q>Only not to see
                    it, that dreadful it!</q></ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="2">
            <ch>CHAPTER 2</ch>
            <ref song="04">The prince had aged very much that year. He showed marked signs of
                senility by a tendency to fall asleep, forgetfulness of quite recent events,
                remembrance of remote ones, and the childish vanity with which he accepted the role
                of head of the Moscow opposition. In spite of this the old man inspired in all his
                visitors alike a feeling of respectful veneration—especially of an evening when he
                came in to tea in his old-fashioned coat and powdered wig and, aroused by anyone,
                told his abrupt stories of the past, or uttered yet more abrupt and scathing
                criticisms of the present. For them all, that old-fashioned house with its gigantic
                mirrors, pre-Revolution furniture, powdered footmen, and the stern shrewd old man
                (himself a relic of the past century) with his gentle daughter and the pretty
                Frenchwoman who were reverently devoted to him presented a majestic and agreeable
                spectacle.</ref>
            <ref song="04">But the visitors did not reflect that besides the couple of hours during
                which they saw their host, there were also twenty-two hours in the day during which
                the private and intimate life of the house continued.</ref>
            <ref song="04">She did not go out into society; everyone knew that her father would not
                let her go anywhere without him, and his failing health prevented his going out
                himself, so that she was not invited to dinners and evening parties. She had quite
                abandoned the hope of getting married.</ref>
            <ref song="04">She saw the coldness and malevolence with which the old prince received
                and dismissed the young men, possible suitors, who sometimes appeared at their
                house. She had no friends</ref>
            <ref song="04">The idea that at the first moment of receiving the news of his son’s
                intentions had occurred to him in jest—that if Andrew got married he himself would
                marry Bourienne—had evidently pleased him</ref>
            <ref song="04">One day in Moscow in Princess Mary’s presence (she thought her father did
                it purposely when she was there) the old prince kissed Mademoiselle Bourienne’s hand
                and, drawing her to him, embraced her affectionately. Princess Mary flushed and ran
                out of the room.</ref>
            <ref song="04">
                <q>It’s horrible, vile, inhuman, to take advantage of the weakness...</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="04">At such moments something like a pride of sacrifice gathered in her soul.
                And suddenly that father whom she had judged would look for his spectacles in her
                presence, fumbling near them and not seeing them, or would forget something that had
                just occurred, or take a false step with his failing legs and turn to see if anyone
                had noticed his feebleness, or, worst of all, at dinner when there were no visitors
                to excite him would suddenly fall asleep, letting his napkin drop and his shaking
                head sink over his plate. <q>He is old and feeble, and I dare to condemn him!</q>
                she thought at such moments, with a feeling of revulsion against herself.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="6">
            <ch>CHAPTER 6</ch>
            <ref song="03">Then she had dinner, a substantial and appetizing meal at which there
                were always three or four guests; after dinner she played a game of boston, and at
                night she had the newspapers or a new book read to her while she knitted.</ref>
            <ref song="03"><q>The count’s things? Bring them here,</q> she said, pointing to the
                portmanteaus and not greeting anyone. <q>The young ladies’? There to the left. Now
                    what are you dawdling for?</q> she cried to the maids. <q>Get the samovar
                    ready!... You’ve grown plumper and prettier,</q> she remarked, drawing Natásha
                (whose cheeks were glowing from the cold) to her by the hood. <q>Foo! You are cold!
                    Now take off your things, quick!</q> she shouted to the count who was going to
                kiss her hand. <q>You’re half frozen, I’m sure! Bring some rum for tea!... Bonjour,
                    Sónya dear!</q> she added, turning to Sónya and indicating by this French
                greeting her slightly contemptuous though affectionate attitude toward her.</ref>
            <ref song="03"><q>All right. All right. They’ll be safe with me, as safe as in Chancery!
                    I’ll take them where they must go, scold them a bit, and pet them a bit,</q>
                said Márya Dmítrievna, touching her goddaughter and favorite, Natásha, on the cheek
                with her large hand.</ref>
            <ref song="03"><q>Well, now we’ll talk. I congratulate you on your betrothed. You’ve
                    hooked a fine fellow! I am glad for your sake and I’ve known him since he was so
                    high.</q> She held her hand a couple of feet from the ground. <c3>Natásha</c3>
                blushed happily. <q>I like him and all his family. Now listen! You know that old
                        <c11>Prince Nicholas</c11> much dislikes his son’s marrying. The old
                    fellow’s crotchety! Of course <c1>Prince Andrew</c1> is not a child and can
                    shift without him, but it’s not nice to enter a family against a father’s will.
                    One wants to do it peacefully and lovingly. You’re a clever girl and you’ll know
                    how to manage. Be kind, and use your wits. Then all will be well.</q></ref>
            <ref song="03">Natásha remained silent, from shyness Márya Dmítrievna supposed, but
                really because she disliked anyone interfering in what touched her love of Prince
                Andrew, which seemed to her so apart from all human affairs that no one could
                understand it. She loved and knew Prince Andrew, he loved her only, and was to come
                one of these days and take her. She wanted nothing more.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="7">
            <ch>CHAPTER 7</ch>
            <ref song="04"><q>They can’t help liking me,</q> she thought. <q>Everybody always has
                    liked me, and I am so willing to do anything they wish, so ready to be fond of
                    him—for being his father—and of her—for being his sister—that there is no reason
                    for them not to like me....</q></ref>
            <ref song="05">From the first glance Princess Mary did not like Natásha. She thought her
                too fashionably dressed, frivolously gay and vain. She did not at all realize that
                before having seen her future sister-in-law she was prejudiced against her by
                involuntary envy of her beauty, youth, and happiness, as well as by jealousy of her
                brother’s love for her.</ref>
            <ref song="05">Apart from this insuperable antipathy to her, Princess Mary was agitated
                just then because on the Rostóvs’ being announced, the old prince had shouted that
                he did not wish to see them, that Princess Mary might do so if she chose, but they
                were not to be admitted to him. She had decided to receive them, but feared lest the
                prince might at any moment indulge in some freak, as he seemed much upset by the
                Rostóvs’ visit.</ref>
            <ref song="05"><q>I am so glad you should get to know one another... very sorry the
                    prince is still ailing,</q> and after a few more commonplace remarks he
                rose.</ref>
            <ref song="05">She blushed for him, grew still angrier at having blushed, and looked at
                the princess with a bold and defiant expression which said that she was not afraid
                of anybody.</ref>
            <ref song="05">Natásha felt offended by the hesitation she had noticed in the anteroom,
                by her father’s nervousness, and by the unnatural manner of the princess who—she
                thought—was making a favor of receiving her, and so everything displeased her. She
                did not like Princess Mary, whom she thought very plain, affected, and dry.</ref>
            <ref song="05">Natásha suddenly shrank into herself and involuntarily assumed an offhand
                air which alienated Princess Mary still more. After five minutes of irksome,
                constrained conversation, they heard the sound of slippered feet rapidly
                approaching.</ref>
            <ref song="05"><q>I beg you to excuse me, excuse me! God is my witness, I did not
                    know,</q> muttered the old man, and after looking Natásha over from head to foot
                he went out.</ref>
            <ref song="05"><q>Dear Natalie,</q> said Princess Mary, <q>I want you to know that I am
                    glad my brother has found happiness....</q></ref>
            <ref song="05"><q>I think, Princess, it is not convenient to speak of that now,</q> she
                said with external dignity and coldness, though she felt the tears choking her.
                    <q>What have I said and what have I done?</q> thought she, as soon as she was
                out of the room.They waited a long time for Natásha to come to dinner that day. She
                sat in her room crying like a child, blowing her nose and sobbing. Sónya stood
                beside her, kissing her hair. <q> Natásha, what is it about?</q> she asked. <q>What
                    do they matter to you? It will all pass, Natásha.</q>
                <q>But if you only knew how offensive it was... as if I...</q>
                <q>Don’t talk about it, Natásha. It wasn’t your fault so why should you mind? Kiss
                    me,</q> said Sónya.Natásha raised her head and, kissing her friend on the lips,
                pressed her wet face against her. <q>I can’t tell you, I don’t know. No one’s to
                    blame,</q> said Natásha—<q>It’s my fault. But it all hurts terribly. Oh, why
                    doesn’t he come?...</q>
            </ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="8">
            <ch>CHAPTER 8</ch>
            <ref song="06"><q>O God, if he were here now I would not behave as I did then, but
                    differently. I would not be silly and afraid of things, I would simply embrace
                    him, cling to him, and make him look at me with those searching inquiring eyes
                    with which he has so often looked at me, and then I would make him laugh as he
                    used to laugh. And his eyes—how I see those eyes!</q> thought Natásha. <q>And
                    what do his father and sister matter to me? I love him alone, him, him, with
                    that face and those eyes, with his smile, manly and yet childlike....</q></ref>
            <ref song="03">
                <q>I can’t bear this waiting and I shall cry in a minute!</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="03">Natásha at that moment felt so softened and tender that it was not enough
                for her to love and know she was beloved, she wanted now, at once, to embrace the
                man she loved, to speak and hear from him words of love such as filled her
                heart.</ref>
            <ref song="07">The music sounded louder and through the door rows of brightly lit boxes
                in which ladies sat with bare arms and shoulders, and noisy stalls brilliant with
                uniforms, glittered before their eyes. A lady entering the next box shot a glance of
                feminine envy at Natásha. The curtain had not yet risen and the overture was being
                played. Natásha, smoothing her gown, went in with Sónya and sat down, scanning the
                brilliant tiers of boxes opposite. A sensation she had not experienced for a long
                time—that of hundreds of eyes looking at her bare arms and neck—suddenly affected
                her both agreeably and disagreeably and called up a whole crowd of memories, desires
                and emotions associated with that feeling.</ref>
            <ref song="07">The two remarkably pretty girls, Natásha and Sónya, with Count Rostóv who
                had not been seen in Moscow for a long time, attracted general attention. Moreover,
                everybody knew vaguely of Natásha’s engagement to Prince Andrew, and knew that the
                Rostóvs had lived in the country ever since, and all looked with curiosity at a
                fiancée who was making one of the best matches in Russia.</ref>
            <ref song="07"><q>Dear me, Michael Kirílovich has grown still stouter!</q> remarked the
                count. <q>Look at our Anna Mikháylovna—what a headdress she has on!</q><q>The
                    Karágins, Julie—and Borís with them. One can see at once that they’re
                    engaged....</q></ref>
            <ref song="07"><q>They are talking about us, about me and him!</q> thought Natásha.
                    <q>And he no doubt is calming her jealousy of me. They needn’t trouble
                    themselves! If only they knew how little I am concerned about any of
                them.</q></ref>
            <ref song="07">He stood in full view of the audience, well aware that he was attracting
                everyone’s attention, yet as much at ease as though he were in his own room. Around
                him thronged Moscow’s most brilliant young men, whom he evidently dominated.</ref>
            <ref song="07"><q>He did,</q> replied Shinshín. <q>He was in the Caucasus and ran away
                    from there. They say he has been acting as minister to some ruling prince in
                    Persia, where he killed the Shah’s brother. Now all the Moscow ladies are mad
                    about him! It’s Dólokhov the Persian that does it!</q></ref>
            <ref song="07">A tall, beautiful woman with a mass of plaited hair and much exposed
                plump white shoulders and neck, round which she wore a double string of large
                pearls, entered the adjoining box rustling her heavy silk dress and took a long time
                settling into her place.</ref>
            <ref song="07">Natásha involuntarily gazed at that neck, those shoulders, and pearls and
                coiffure, and admired the beauty of the shoulders and the pearls. While Natásha was
                fixing her gaze on her for the second time the lady looked round and, meeting the
                count’s eyes, nodded to him and smiled. She was the Countess Bezúkhova, Pierre’s
                wife, and the count, who knew everyone in society, leaned over and spoke to
                her.</ref>
            <ref song="07"><q>Have you been here long, Countess?</q> he inquired. <q>I’ll call, I’ll
                    call to kiss your hand. I’m here on business and have brought my girls with me.
                    They say Semënova acts marvelously. Count Pierre never used to forget us. Is he
                    here?</q></ref>
            <ref song="07">As soon as it rose everyone in the boxes and stalls became silent, and
                all the men, old and young, in uniform and evening dress, and all the women with
                gems on their bare flesh, turned their whole attention with eager curiosity to the
                stage.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="9">
            <ch>CHAPTER 9</ch>
            <ref song="07">After her life in the country, and in her present serious mood, all this
                seemed grotesque and amazing to Natásha. She could not follow the opera nor even
                listen to the music; she saw only the painted cardboard and the queerly dressed men
                and women who moved, spoke, and sang so strangely in that brilliant light. She knew
                what it was all meant to represent, but it was so pretentiously false and unnatural
                that she first felt ashamed for the actors and then amused at them. She looked at
                the faces of the audience, seeking in them the same sense of ridicule and perplexity
                she herself experienced, but they all seemed attentive to what was happening on the
                stage, and expressed delight which to Natásha seemed feigned.</ref>
            <ref song="07">especially at Hélène in the next box, who—apparently quite unclothed—sat
                with a quiet tranquil smile</ref>
            <ref song="07">And feeling the bright light that flooded the whole place and the warm
                air heated by the crowd, Natásha little by little began to pass into a state of
                intoxication she had not experienced for a long while.</ref>
            <ref song="07">As she looked and thought, the strangest fancies unexpectedly and
                disconnectedly passed through her mind: the idea occurred to her of jumping onto the
                edge of the box and singing the aria the actress was singing, then she wished to
                touch with her fan an old gentleman sitting not far from her, then to lean over to
                Hélène and tickle her.</ref>
            <ref song="07">At a moment when all was quiet before the commencement of a song, a door
                leading to the stalls on the side nearest the Rostóvs’ box creaked, and the steps of
                a belated arrival were heard. <q>There’s <c7>Kurágin</c7>!</q> whispered Shinshín.
                    <c9>Countess Bezúkhova</c9> turned smiling to the newcomer, and
                <c3>Natásha</c3>, following the direction of that look, saw an exceptionally
                handsome adjutant approaching their box with a self-assured yet courteous bearing.
                This was <c7>Anatole Kurágin</c7> whom she had seen and noticed long ago at the ball
                in Petersburg. He was now in an adjutant’s uniform with one epaulet and a shoulder
                knot. He moved with a restrained swagger which would have been ridiculous had he not
                been so good-looking and had his handsome face not worn such an expression of
                good-humored complacency and gaiety. Though the performance was proceeding, he
                walked deliberately down the carpeted gangway, his sword and spurs slightly jingling
                and his handsome perfumed head held high. Having looked at <c3>Natásha</c3> he
                approached his sister, laid his well gloved hand on the edge of her box, nodded to
                her, and leaning forward asked a question, with a motion toward
                <c3>Natásha</c3>.</ref>
            <ref song="07"><q>Mais charmante!</q> said he, evidently referring to <c3>Natásha</c3>,
                who did not exactly hear his words but understood them from the movement of his
                lips. Then he took his place in the first row of the stalls and sat down beside
                    <c8>Dólokhov</c8>, nudging with his elbow in a friendly and offhand way that
                    <c8>Dólokhov</c8> whom others treated so fawningly. He winked at him gaily,
                smiled, and rested his foot against the orchestra screen.</ref>
            <ref song="07">She turned and their eyes met. Almost smiling, he gazed straight into her
                eyes with such an enraptured caressing look that it seemed strange to be so near
                him, to look at him like that, to be so sure he admired her, and not to be
                acquainted with him.</ref>
            <ref song="07">In the second act there was scenery representing tombstones, there was a
                round hole in the canvas to represent the moon, shades were raised over the
                footlights, and from horns and contrabass came deep notes while many people appeared
                from right and left wearing black cloaks and holding things like daggers in their
                hands. They began waving their arms.</ref>
            <ref song="12">
                <q>How is it you’re not ashamed to bury such pearls in the country?</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="12"><c9>Countess Bezúkhova</c9> quite deserved her reputation of being a
                fascinating woman. She could say what she did not think—especially what was
                flattering—quite simply and naturally.</ref>
            <ref song="07">The scene of the third act represented a palace in which many candles
                were burning and pictures of knights with short beards hung on the walls. In the
                middle stood what were probably a king and a queen. The king waved his right arm
                and, evidently nervous, sang something badly and sat down on a crimson throne.</ref>
            <ref song="07">But suddenly a storm came on, chromatic scales and diminished sevenths
                were heard in the orchestra, everyone ran off, again dragging one of their number
                away, and the curtain dropped. Once more there was a terrible noise and clatter
                among the audience, and with rapturous faces everyone began shouting: <q>Duport!
                    Duport! Duport!</q></ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="10">
            <ch>CHAPTER 10</ch>
            <ref song="07">During the entr’acte a whiff of cold air came into <c9>Hélène</c9>’s box,
                the door opened, and <c7>Anatole</c7> entered, stooping and trying not to brush
                against anyone.</ref>
            <ref song="08"><c7>Anatole</c7>, who was as handsome at close quarters as at a distance,
                sat down beside her and told her he had long wished to have this happiness—ever
                since the Narýshkins’ ball in fact, at which he had had the well-remembered pleasure
                of seeing her. <c7>Kurágin</c7> was much more sensible and simple with women than
                among men. He talked boldly and naturally, and <c3>Natásha</c3> was strangely and
                agreeably struck by the fact that there was nothing formidable in this man about
                whom there was so much talk, but that on the contrary his smile was most naïve,
                cheerful, and good-natured.</ref>
            <ref song="08"><c7>Kurágin</c7> asked her opinion of the performance and told her how at
                a previous performance Semënova had fallen down on the stage.</ref>
            <ref song="08"><q>And do you know, Countess,</q> he said, suddenly addressing her as an
                old, familiar acquaintance, <q>we are getting up a costume tournament; you ought to
                    take part in it! It will be great fun. We shall all meet at the Karágins’!
                    Please come! No! Really, eh?</q> said he.</ref>
            <ref song="08">While saying this he never removed his smiling eyes from her face, her
                neck, and her bare arms. <c3>Natásha</c3> knew for certain that he was enraptured by
                her. This pleased her, yet his presence made her feel constrained and oppressed.
                When she was not looking at him she felt that he was looking at her shoulders, and
                she involuntarily caught his eye so that he should look into hers rather than this.
                But looking into his eyes she was frightened, realizing that there was not that
                barrier of modesty she had always felt between herself and other men. She did not
                know how it was that within five minutes she had come to feel herself terribly near
                to this man. When she turned away she feared he might seize her from behind by her
                bare arm and kiss her on the neck. They spoke of most ordinary things, yet she felt
                that they were closer to one another than she had ever been to any man.</ref>
            <ref song="08">During one of these moments of awkward silence when <c7>Anatole</c7>’s
                prominent eyes were gazing calmly and fixedly at her, <c3>Natásha</c3>, to break the
                silence, asked him how he liked Moscow.</ref>
            <ref song="08"><q>At first I did not like it much, because what makes a town pleasant ce
                    sont les jolies femmes, * isn’t that so? But now I like it very much indeed,</q>
                he said, looking at her significantly. <q>You’ll come to the costume tournament,
                    Countess? Do come!</q> and putting out his hand to her bouquet and dropping his
                voice, he added, <q>You will be the prettiest there. Do come, dear countess, and
                    give me this flower as a pledge!</q></ref>
            <ref song="08">She smiled just as he was doing, gazing straight into his eyes. And again
                she felt with horror that no barrier lay between him and her.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="11">
            <ch>CHAPTER 11</ch>
            <ref song="09">There was a special reason for this, as he had got married two years
                before—a fact known only to his most intimate friends. At that time while with his
                regiment in Poland, a Polish landowner of small means had forced him to marry his
                daughter.</ref>
            <ref song="09"><c7>Anatole</c7> was always content with his position, with himself, and
                with others. He was instinctively and thoroughly convinced that it was impossible
                for him to live otherwise than as he did and that he had never in his life done
                anything base. He was incapable of considering how his actions might affect others
                or what the consequences of this or that action of his might be. He was convinced
                that, as a duck is so made that it must live in water, so God had made him such that
                he must spend thirty thousand rubles a year and always occupy a prominent position
                in society.</ref>
            <ref song="09">All he cared about was gaiety and women, and as according to his ideas
                there was nothing dishonorable in these tastes, and he was incapable of considering
                what the gratification of his tastes entailed for others, he honestly considered
                himself irreproachable, sincerely despised rogues and bad people, and with a
                tranquil conscience carried his head high.</ref>
            <ref song="09">At supper after the opera he described to <c8>Dólokhov</c8> with the air
                of a connoisseur the attractions of her arms, shoulders, feet, and hair and
                expressed his intention of making love to her.</ref>
            <ref song="09"><q>She’s first-rate, my dear fellow, but not for us,</q> replied
                    <c8>Dólokhov</c8>. <q>I will tell my sister to ask her to dinner,</q> said
                    <c7>Anatole</c7>. <q>Eh?</q>
                <q>You’d better wait till she’s married....</q></ref>
            <ref song="13"><q>You know, I adore little girls, they lose their heads at once,</q>
                pursued <c7>Anatole</c7>.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="12">
            <ch>CHAPTER 12</ch>
            <ref song="11">She suffered more now than during her first days in Moscow. To her
                impatience and pining for him were now added the unpleasant recollection of her
                interview with <c13>Princess Mary</c13> and the old prince, and a fear and anxiety
                of which she did not understand the cause. She continually fancied that either he
                would never come or that something would happen to her before he came.</ref>
            <ref song="11">As soon as she began to think of him, the recollection of the old prince,
                of <c13>Princess Mary</c13>, of the theater, and of <c7>Kurágin</c7> mingled with
                her thoughts. The question again presented itself whether she was not guilty,
                whether she had not already broken faith with <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>, and again she
                found herself recalling to the minutest detail every word, every gesture, and every
                shade in the play of expression on the face of the man who had been able to arouse
                in her such an incomprehensible and terrifying feeling.</ref>
            <ref song="11">She wore her holiday shawl, in which she paid calls, and announced that
                she was going to see <c11>Prince Nicholas</c11> Bolkónski to have an explanation
                with him about <c3>Natásha</c3>.</ref>
            <ref song="11">After she had gone, a dressmaker from Madame Suppert-Roguet waited on the
                Rostóvs, and <c3>Natásha</c3>, very glad of this diversion, having shut herself into
                a room adjoining the drawing room, occupied herself trying on the new dresses.</ref>
            <ref song="11">Just as she had put on a bodice without sleeves and only tacked together,
                and was turning her head to see in the glass how the back fitted, she heard in the
                drawing room the animated sounds of her father’s voice and another’s—a woman’s—that
                made her flush.</ref>
            <ref song="12"><q>Oh, my enchantress!</q> she cried to the blushing <c3>Natásha</c3>.
                    <q>Charming! No, this is really beyond anything, my dear count,</q> said she to
                    <c5>Count Rostóv</c5> who had followed her in. <q>How can you live in Moscow and
                    go nowhere?</q></ref>
            <ref song="12">She looked at <c3>Natásha</c3>’s dresses and praised them, as well as a
                new dress of her own made of <q>metallic gauze,</q> which she had received from
                Paris, and advised <c3>Natásha</c3> to have one like it.</ref>
            <ref song="12"><q>But anything suits you, my charmer!</q> she remarked.</ref>
            <ref song="12">The idea of throwing her brother and <c3>Natásha</c3> together amused
                her.</ref>
            <ref song="12">
                <q>My brother dined with me yesterday—we nearly died of laughter—he ate nothing and
                    kept sighing for you, my charmer! He is madly, quite madly, in love with you, my
                    dear.</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="12"><q>How she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!</q> said <c9>Hélène</c9>.
                    <q>You must certainly come. If you love somebody, my charmer, that is not a
                    reason to shut yourself up. Even if you are engaged, I am sure your fiancé would
                    wish you to go into society rather than be bored to death.</q></ref>
            <ref song="12"><q>So she knows I am engaged, and she and her husband
                    <c2>Pierre</c2>—that good <c2>Pierre</c2>—have talked and laughed about this. So
                    it’s all right.</q> And again, under <c9>Hélène</c9>’s influence, what had
                seemed terrible now seemed simple and natural. <q>And she is such a grande dame, so
                    kind, and evidently likes me so much. And why not enjoy myself?</q> thought
                    <c3>Natásha</c3>, gazing at <c9>Hélène</c9> with wide-open, wondering
                eyes.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="13">
            <ch>CHAPTER 13</ch>
            <ref song="13"><c7>Anatole</c7> was at the door, evidently on the lookout for the
                Rostóvs.</ref>
            <ref song="13">As soon as she saw him she was seized by the same feeling she had had at
                the opera—gratified vanity at his admiration of her and fear at the absence of a
                moral barrier between them.</ref>
            <ref song="13"><q>Adorable! divine! delicious!</q> was heard from every side.
                    <c3>Natásha</c3> looked at the fat actress, but neither saw nor heard nor
                understood anything of what went on before her. She only felt herself again
                completely borne away into this strange senseless world—so remote from her old
                world—a world in which it was impossible to know what was good or bad, reasonable or
                senseless. Behind her sat <c7>Anatole</c7>, and conscious of his proximity she
                experienced a frightened sense of expectancy.</ref>
            <ref song="13">He said this at a moment when she alone could hear him. <q>You are
                    enchanting... from the moment I saw you I have never ceased...</q></ref>
            <ref song="13"><c7>Anatole</c7> asked <c3>Natásha</c3> for a valse and as they danced he
                pressed her waist and hand and told her she was bewitching and that he loved her.
                During the écossaise, which she also danced with him, <c7>Anatole</c7> said nothing
                when they happened to be by themselves, but merely gazed at her. <c3>Natásha</c3>
                lifted her frightened eyes to him, but there was such confident tenderness in his
                affectionate look and smile that she could not, whilst looking at him, say what she
                had to say. She lowered her eyes.</ref>
            <ref song="13"><q>Don’t say such things to me. I am betrothed and love another,</q> she
                said rapidly.... She glanced at him.</ref>
            <ref song="13"><q>Don’t speak to me of that! What can I do?</q> said he. <q>I tell you I
                    am madly, madly, in love with you! Is it my fault that you are enchanting?...
                    It’s our turn to begin.</q></ref>
            <ref song="13"><c3>Natásha</c3>, animated and excited, looked about her with wide-open
                frightened eyes and seemed merrier than usual. She understood hardly anything that
                went on that evening. They danced the écossaise and the Grossvater.</ref>
            <ref song="13"><q>I cannot come to visit you but is it possible that I shall never see
                    you? I love you madly. Can I never...?</q> and, blocking her path, he brought
                his face close to hers. His large, glittering, masculine eyes were so close to hers
                that she saw nothing but them.<q>
                    <c3>Natalie</c3>?</q> he whispered inquiringly while she felt her hands being
                painfully pressed. <q><c3>Natalie</c3>?</q>
                <q>I don’t understand. I have nothing to say,</q> her eyes replied.</ref>
            <ref song="13">Burning lips were pressed to hers, and at the same instant she felt
                herself released, and <c9>Hélène</c9>’s footsteps and the rustle of her dress were
                heard in the room. <c3>Natásha</c3> looked round at her, and then, red and
                trembling, threw a frightened look of inquiry at <c7>Anatole</c7> and moved toward
                the door.</ref>
            <ref song="13">She paused. She so wanted a word from him that would explain to her what
                had happened and to which she could find no answer.</ref>
            <ref song="13">After reaching home <c3>Natásha</c3> did not sleep all night. She was
                tormented by the insoluble question whether she loved <c7>Anatole</c7> or <c1>Prince
                    Andrew</c1>. She loved Prince <c1>Andrew</c1>—she remembered distinctly how
                deeply she loved him. But she also loved <c7>Anatole</c7>, of that there was no
                doubt. <q>Else how could all this have happened?</q> thought she. <q>If, after that,
                    I could return his smile when saying good-by, if I was able to let it come to
                    that, it means that I loved him from the first. It means that he is kind, noble,
                    and splendid, and I could not help loving him.</q></ref>
            <ref song="14"><q>What am I to do if I love him and the other one too?</q> she asked
                herself, unable to find an answer to these terrible questions.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="14">
            <ch>CHAPTER 14</ch>
            <ref song="14"><c13>Princess Mary</c13> wrote that she was in despair at the
                misunderstanding that had occurred between them. Whatever her father’s feelings
                might be, she begged <c3>Natásha</c3> to believe that she could not help loving her
                as the one chosen by her brother, for whose happiness she was ready to sacrifice
                everything.</ref>
            <ref song="14"><q>Do not think, however,</q> she wrote, <q>that my father is
                    ill-disposed toward you. He is an invalid and an old man who must be forgiven;
                    but he is good and magnanimous and will love her who makes his son happy.</q>
                <c13>Princess Mary</c13> went on to ask <c3>Natásha</c3> to fix a time when she
                could see her again.</ref>
            <ref song="14"><q>Dear Princess,</q> she wrote in French quickly and mechanically, and
                then paused. What more could she write after all that had happened the evening
                before? <q>Yes, yes! All that has happened, and now all is changed,</q> she thought
                as she sat with the letter she had begun before her. <q>Must I break off with him?
                    Must I really? That’s awful...</q> and to escape from these dreadful thoughts
                she went to <c6>Sónya</c6> and began sorting patterns with her.</ref>
            <ref song="14"><q>Only, for Christ’s sake...</q> the girl went on, as <c3>Natásha</c3>,
                without thinking, mechanically broke the seal and read a love letter from
                    <c7>Anatole</c7>, of which, without taking in a word, she understood only that
                it was a letter from him—from the man she loved. Yes, she loved him, or else how
                could that have happened which had happened? And how could she have a love letter
                from him in her hand?</ref>
            <ref song="14">With trembling hands <c3>Natásha</c3> held that passionate love letter
                which <c8>Dólokhov</c8> had composed for <c7>Anatole</c7></ref>
            <ref song="14"><q>Since yesterday evening my fate has been sealed; to be loved by you or
                    to die. There is no other way for me,</q> the letter began. Then he went on to
                say that he knew her parents would not give her to him—for this there were secret
                reasons he could reveal only to her—but that if she loved him she need only say the
                word yes, and no human power could hinder their bliss. Love would conquer all. He
                would steal her away and carry her off to the ends of the earth.</ref>
            <ref song="14"><q>Yes, yes! I love him!</q> thought <c3>Natásha</c3>, reading the letter
                for the twentieth time and finding some peculiarly deep meaning in each word of
                it.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="15">
            <ch>CHAPTER 15</ch>
            <ref song="15"><q>How was it I noticed nothing? How could it go so far? Can she have
                    left off loving <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>? And how could she let <c7>Kurágin</c7>
                    go to such lengths? He is a deceiver and a villain, that’s plain! What will
                    Nicholas, dear noble Nicholas, do when he hears of it? So this is the meaning of
                    her excited, resolute, unnatural look the day before yesterday, yesterday, and
                    today,</q> thought <c6>Sónya</c6>. <q>But it can’t be that she loves him! She
                    probably opened the letter without knowing who it was from. Probably she is
                    offended by it. She could not do such a thing!</q></ref>
            <ref song="15"><q><c3>Natásha</c3>!</q> she said, just audibly. <c3>Natásha</c3> awoke
                and saw <c6>Sónya</c6>. <q>Ah, you’re back?</q></ref>
            <ref song="15">And with the decision and tenderness that often come at the moment of
                awakening, she embraced her friend, but noticing <c6>Sónya</c6>’s look of
                embarrassment, her own face expressed confusion and suspicion.</ref>
            <ref song="15">
                <p><q><c6>Sónya</c6>, you’ve read that letter?</q> she demanded.</p>
                <p><q>Yes,</q> answered <c6>Sónya</c6> softly.</p>
                <p><c3>Natásha</c3> smiled rapturously.</p>
                <p><q>No, <c6>Sónya</c6>, I can’t any longer!</q> she said. <q>I can’t hide it from
                        you any longer. You know, we love one another! <c6>Sónya</c6>, darling, he
                        writes... <c6>Sónya</c6>...</q></p>
                <p><c6>Sónya</c6> stared open-eyed at <c3>Natásha</c3>, unable to believe her
                    ears.</p>
                <p><q>And Bolkónski?</q> she asked.</p>
                <p><q>Ah, <c6>Sónya</c6>, if you only knew how happy I am!</q> cried
                        <c3>Natásha</c3>. <q>You don’t know what love is....</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>But, <c3>Natásha</c3>, can that be all over?</q>
                </p>
                <p><c3>Natásha</c3> looked at <c6>Sónya</c6> with wide-open eyes as if she could not
                    grasp the question.</p>
                <p><q>Well, then, are you refusing <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>?</q> said
                    <c6>Sónya</c6>.</p>
                <p><q>Oh, you don’t understand anything! Don’t talk nonsense, just listen!</q> said
                        <c3>Natásha</c3>, with momentary vexation.</p>
                <p><q>But I can’t believe it,</q> insisted <c6>Sónya</c6>. <q>I don’t understand.
                        How is it you have loved a man for a whole year and suddenly... Why, you
                        have only seen him three times! <c3>Natásha</c3>, I don’t believe you,
                        you’re joking! In three days to forget everything and so...</q></p>
                <p><q>Three days?</q> said <c3>Natásha</c3>. <q>It seems to me I’ve loved him a
                        hundred years. It seems to me that I have never loved anyone before. You
                        can’t understand it.... <c6>Sónya</c6>, wait a bit, sit here,</q> and
                        <c3>Natásha</c3> embraced and kissed her.</p>
                <p><q>I had heard that it happens like this, and you must have heard it too, but
                        it’s only now that I feel such love. It’s not the same as before. As soon as
                        I saw him I felt he was my master and I his slave, and that I could not help
                        loving him. Yes, his slave! Whatever he orders I shall do. You don’t
                        understand that. What can I do? What can I do, <c6>Sónya</c6>?</q> cried
                        <c3>Natásha</c3> with a happy yet frightened expression.</p>
                <p><q>But think what you are doing,</q> cried <c6>Sónya</c6>. <q>I can’t leave it
                        like this. This secret correspondence... How could you let him go so
                        far?</q> she went on, with a horror and disgust she could hardly
                    conceal.</p>
                <p><q>I told you that I have no will,</q>
                    <c3>Natásha</c3> replied. <q>Why can’t you understand? I love him!</q></p>
                <p><q>Then I won’t let it come to that... I shall tell!</q> cried <c6>Sónya</c6>,
                    bursting into tears.</p>
                <p><q>What do you mean? For God’s sake... If you tell, you are my enemy!</q>
                    declared <c3>Natásha</c3>. <q>You want me to be miserable, you want us to be
                        separated....</q></p>
                <p>When she saw <c3>Natásha</c3>’s fright, <c6>Sónya</c6> shed tears of shame and
                    pity for her friend.</p>
                <p><q>But what has happened between you?</q> she asked. <q>What has he said to you?
                        Why doesn’t he come to the house?</q></p>
                <p><c3>Natásha</c3> did not answer her questions.</p>
                <p><q>For God’s sake, <c6>Sónya</c6>, don’t tell anyone, don’t torture me,</q>
                    <c3>Natásha</c3> entreated. <q>Remember no one ought to interfere in such
                        matters! I have confided in you....</q></p>
                <p><q>But why this secrecy? Why doesn’t he come to the house?</q> asked
                        <c6>Sónya</c6>. <q>Why doesn’t he openly ask for your hand? You know
                            <c1>Prince Andrew</c1> gave you complete freedom—if it is really so; but
                        I don’t believe it! <c3>Natásha</c3>, have you considered what these secret
                        reasons can be?</q></p>
                <p><c3>Natásha</c3> looked at <c6>Sónya</c6> with astonishment. Evidently this
                    question presented itself to her mind for the first time and she did not know
                    how to answer it.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>I don’t know what the reasons are. But there must be reasons!</q>
                </p>
                <p><c6>Sónya</c6> sighed and shook her head incredulously.</p>
                <p><q>If there were reasons...</q> she began.</p>
                <p>But <c3>Natásha</c3>, guessing her doubts, interrupted her in alarm.</p>
                <p><q><c6>Sónya</c6>, one can’t doubt him! One can’t, one can’t! Don’t you
                        understand?</q> she cried.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>Does he love you?</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>Does he love me?</q>
                    <c3>Natásha</c3> repeated with a smile of pity at her friend’s lack of
                    comprehension. <q>Why, you have read his letter and you have seen him.</q></p>
                <p>
                    <q>But if he is dishonorable?</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>He! dishonorable? If you only knew!</q> exclaimed <c3>Natásha</c3>.</p>
                <p><q>If he is an honorable man he should either declare his intentions or cease
                        seeing you; and if you won’t do this, I will. I will write to him, and I
                        will tell Papa!</q> said <c6>Sónya</c6> resolutely.</p>
                <p><q>But I can’t live without him!</q> cried <c3>Natásha</c3>.</p>
                <p>
                    <q><c3>Natásha</c3>, I don’t understand you. And what are you saying! Think of
                        your father and of Nicholas.</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>I don’t want anyone, I don’t love anyone but him. How dare you say he is
                        dishonorable? Don’t you know that I love him?</q> screamed <c3>Natásha</c3>.
                        <q>Go away, <c6>Sónya</c6>! I don’t want to quarrel with you, but go, for
                        God’s sake go! You see how I am suffering!</q>
                    <c3>Natásha</c3> cried angrily, in a voice of despair and repressed irritation.
                        <c6>Sónya</c6> burst into sobs and ran from the room.</p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="15"><c3>Natásha</c3> went to the table and without a moment’s reflection
                wrote that answer to <c13>Princess Mary</c13> which she had been unable to write all
                the morning. In this letter she said briefly that all their misunderstandings were
                at an end; that availing herself of the magnanimity of <c1>Prince Andrew</c1> who
                when he went abroad had given her her freedom, she begged <c13>Princess Mary</c13>
                to forget everything and forgive her if she had been to blame toward her, but that
                she could not be his wife. At that moment this all seemed quite easy, simple, and
                clear to <c3>Natásha</c3>.</ref>
            <ref song="15"><q>Oh, <c6>Sónya</c6>, if you knew him as I do! He said... He asked me
                    what I had promised Bolkónski. He was glad I was free to refuse him.</q>
                <c6>Sónya</c6> sighed sorrowfully. <q>But you haven’t refused Bolkónski?</q> said
                she. <q>Perhaps I have. Perhaps all is over between me and Bolkónski. Why do you
                    think so badly of me?</q></ref>
            <ref song="15"><c6>Sónya</c6> did not succumb to the tender tone <c3>Natásha</c3> used
                toward her. The more emotional and ingratiating the expression of <c3>Natásha</c3>’s
                face became, the more serious and stern grew <c6>Sónya</c6>’s.</ref>
            <ref song="15"><q><c3>Natásha</c3>, I am afraid for you!</q>
                <q>Afraid of what?</q>
                <q>I am afraid you’re going to your ruin,</q> said <c6>Sónya</c6> resolutely, and
                was herself horrified at what she had said. Anger again showed in <c3>Natásha</c3>’s
                face. <q>And I’ll go to my ruin, I will, as soon as possible! It’s not your
                    business! It won’t be you, but I, who’ll suffer. Leave me alone, leave me alone!
                    I hate you!</q>
                <q><c3>Natásha</c3>!</q> moaned <c6>Sónya</c6>, aghast. <q>I hate you, I hate you!
                    You’re my enemy forever!</q> And <c3>Natásha</c3> ran out of the room.</ref>
            <ref song="16">Hard as it was for <c6>Sónya</c6>, she watched her friend and did not let
                her out of her sight. The day before the count was to return, <c6>Sónya</c6> noticed
                that <c3>Natásha</c3> sat by the drawing room window all the morning as if expecting
                something and that she made a sign to an officer who drove past, whom <c6>Sónya</c6>
                took to be <c7>Anatole</c7>. <c6>Sónya</c6> began watching her friend still more
                attentively and noticed that at dinner and all that evening <c3>Natásha</c3> was in
                a strange and unnatural state. She answered questions at random, began sentences she
                did not finish, and laughed at everything.</ref>
            <ref song="16">After tea <c6>Sónya</c6> noticed a housemaid at <c3>Natásha</c3>’s door
                timidly waiting to let her pass. She let the girl go in, and then listening at the
                door learned that another letter had been delivered. Then suddenly it became clear
                to <c6>Sónya</c6> that <c3>Natásha</c3> had some dreadful plan for that evening.
                    <c6>Sónya</c6> knocked at her door. <c3>Natásha</c3> did not let her in.</ref>
            <ref song="16"><q>She will run away with him!</q> thought <c6>Sónya</c6>. <q>She is
                    capable of anything. There was something particularly pathetic and resolute in
                    her face today. She cried as she said good-by to Uncle,</q>
                <c6>Sónya</c6> remembered. <q>Yes, that’s it, she means to elope with him, but what
                    am I to do?</q> thought she, recalling all the signs that clearly indicated that
                    <c3>Natásha</c3> had some terrible intention. <q>The count is away. What am I to
                    do? Write to <c7>Kurágin</c7> demanding an explanation? But what is there to
                    oblige him to reply? Write to <c2>Pierre</c2>, as <c1>Prince Andrew</c1> asked
                    me to in case of some misfortune?... But perhaps she really has already refused
                    Bolkónski—she sent a letter to <c13>Princess Mary</c13> yesterday. And Uncle is
                    away....</q> To tell <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4> who had such faith in
                    <c3>Natásha</c3> seemed to <c6>Sónya</c6> terrible. <q>Well, anyway,</q> thought
                    <c6>Sónya</c6> as she stood in the dark passage, <q>now or never I must prove
                    that I remember the family’s goodness to me and that I love Nicholas. Yes! If I
                    don’t sleep for three nights I’ll not leave this passage and will hold her back
                    by force and will and not let the family be disgraced,</q> thought she.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="16">
            <ch>CHAPTER 16</ch>
            <ref song="17">The plan for <c3>Natalie Rostóva</c3>’s abduction had been arranged and
                the preparations made by <c8>Dólokhov</c8> a few days before, and on the day that
                    <c6>Sónya</c6>, after listening at <c3>Natásha</c3>’s door, resolved to
                safeguard her, it was to have been put into execution. <c3>Natásha</c3> had promised
                to come out to <c7>Kurágin</c7> at the back porch at ten that evening.
                    <c7>Kurágin</c7> was to put her into a troyka he would have ready and to drive
                her forty miles to the village of Kámenka, where an unfrocked priest was in
                readiness to perform a marriage ceremony over them. At Kámenka a relay of horses was
                to wait which would take them to the Warsaw highroad, and from there they would
                hasten abroad with post horses.</ref>
            <ref song="17"><c7>Anatole</c7> had a passport, an order for post horses, ten thousand
                rubles he had taken from his sister and another ten thousand borrowed with
                    <c8>Dólokhov</c8>’s help.</ref>
            <ref song="17">Two witnesses for the mock marriage—Khvóstikov, a retired petty official
                whom <c8>Dólokhov</c8> made use of in his gambling transactions, and Makárin, a
                retired hussar, a kindly, weak fellow who had an unbounded affection for
                    <c7>Kurágin</c7>—were sitting at tea in <c8>Dólokhov</c8>’s front room.</ref>
            <ref song="17">In his large study, the walls of which were hung to the ceiling with
                Persian rugs, bearskins, and weapons, sat <c8>Dólokhov</c8> in a traveling cloak and
                high boots, at an open desk on which lay an abacus and some bundles of paper money.
                    <c7>Anatole</c7>, with uniform unbuttoned, walked to and fro from the room where
                the witnesses were sitting, through the study to the room behind, where his French
                valet and others were packing the last of his things. <c8>Dólokhov</c8> was counting
                the money and noting something down.</ref>
            <ref song="17"><q>Do you know? You’d really better drop it all. There’s still time!</q>
                <q>Fool,</q> retorted <c7>Anatole</c7>. <q>Don’t talk nonsense! If you only knew...
                    it’s the devil knows what!</q>
                <q>No, really, give it up!</q> said <c8>Dólokhov</c8>. <q>I am speaking seriously.
                    It’s no joke, this plot you’ve hatched.</q>
                <q>What, teasing again? Go to the devil! Eh?</q> said <c7>Anatole</c7>, making a
                grimace. <q>Really it’s no time for your stupid jokes,</q> and he left the
                room.</ref>
            <ref song="17"><q>You wait a bit,</q> he called after him. <q>I’m not joking, I’m
                    talking sense. Come here, come here!</q>
                <c7>Anatole</c7> returned and looked at <c8>Dólokhov</c8>, trying to give him his
                attention and evidently submitting to him involuntarily. <q>Now listen to me. I’m
                    telling you this for the last time. Why should I joke about it? Did I hinder
                    you? Who arranged everything for you? Who found the priest and got the passport?
                    Who raised the money? I did it all.</q>
                <q>Well, thank you for it. Do you think I am not grateful?</q> And <c7>Anatole</c7>
                sighed and embraced <c8>Dólokhov</c8>. <q>I helped you, but all the same I must tell
                    you the truth; it is a dangerous business, and if you think about it—a stupid
                    business. Well, you’ll carry her off—all right! Will they let it stop at that?
                    It will come out that you’re already married. Why, they’ll have you in the
                    criminal court....</q></ref>
            <ref song="17"><q>Oh, nonsense, nonsense!</q>
                <c7>Anatole</c7> ejaculated and again made a grimace. <q>Didn’t I explain to you?
                    What?</q> And <c7>Anatole</c7>, with the partiality dull-witted people have for
                any conclusion they have reached by their own reasoning, repeated the argument he
                had already put to <c8>Dólokhov</c8> a hundred times. <q>Didn’t I explain to you
                    that I have come to this conclusion: if this marriage is invalid,</q> he went
                on, crooking one finger, <q>then I have nothing to answer for; but if it is valid,
                    no matter! Abroad no one will know anything about it. Isn’t that so? And don’t
                    talk to me, don’t, don’t.</q></ref>
            <ref song="17"><q>Go to the devil!</q> cried <c7>Anatole</c7> and, clutching his hair,
                left the room, but returned at once and dropped into an armchair in front of
                    <c8>Dólokhov</c8> with his feet turned under him. <q>It’s the very devil! What?
                    Feel how it beats!</q> He took <c8>Dólokhov</c8>’s hand and put it on his heart.
                    <q>What a foot, my dear fellow! What a glance! A goddess!</q> he added in
                French.</ref>
            <ref song="17"><q>Now then! Nearly ready? You’re dawdling!</q> he shouted to the
                servants.</ref>
            <ref song="17"><c7>Anatole</c7> lay on the sofa in the study leaning on his elbow and
                smiling pensively, while his handsome lips muttered tenderly to himself.</ref>
            <ref song="17">
                <q>Come! <c12>Balagá</c12> is here.</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="18"><c12>Balagá</c12> was a famous troyka driver who had known
                    <c8>Dólokhov</c8> and <c7>Anatole</c7> some six years and had given them good
                service with his troykas. More than once when <c7>Anatole</c7>’s regiment was
                stationed at Tver he had taken him from Tver in the evening, brought him to Moscow
                by daybreak, and driven him back again the next night. More than once he had enabled
                    <c8>Dólokhov</c8> to escape when pursued. More than once he had driven them
                through the town with gypsies and <q>ladykins</q> as he called the cocottes. More
                than once in their service he had run over pedestrians and upset vehicles in the
                streets of Moscow and had always been protected from the consequences by <q>my
                    gentlemen</q> as he called them. He had ruined more than one horse in their
                service. More than once they had beaten him, and more than once they had made him
                drunk on champagne and Madeira, which he loved; and he knew more than one thing
                about each of them which would long ago have sent an ordinary man to Siberia. They
                often called <c12>Balagá</c12> into their orgies and made him drink and dance at the
                gypsies’, and more than one thousand rubles of their money had passed through his
                hands. In their service he risked his skin and his life twenty times a year, and in
                their service had lost more horses than the money he had from them would buy. But he
                liked them; liked that mad driving at twelve miles an hour, liked upsetting a driver
                or running down a pedestrian, and flying at full gallop through the Moscow streets.
                He liked to hear those wild, tipsy shouts behind him: <q>Get on! Get on!</q> when it
                was impossible to go any faster. He liked giving a painful lash on the neck to some
                peasant who, more dead than alive, was already hurrying out of his way. <q>Real
                    gentlemen!</q> he considered them.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="17">
            <ch>CHAPTER 17</ch>
            <ref song="19"><q>All take glasses; you too, <c12>Balagá</c12>. Well, comrades and
                    friends of my youth, we’ve had our fling and lived and reveled. Eh? And now,
                    when shall we meet again? I am going abroad. We have had a good time—now
                    farewell, lads! To our health! Hurrah!...</q> he cried, and emptying his glass
                flung it on the floor.</ref>
            <ref song="19"><q>No, stop!</q> said <c7>Anatole</c7>. <q>Shut the door; we have first
                    to sit down. That’s the way.</q></ref>
            <ref song="19"><q>And where’s the fur cloak?</q> asked <c8>Dólokhov</c8>. <q>Hey,
                    Ignátka! Go to Matrëna Matrévna and ask her for the sable cloak. I have heard
                    what elopements are like,</q> continued <c8>Dólokhov</c8> with a wink. <q>Why,
                    she’ll rush out more dead than alive just in the things she is wearing; if you
                    delay at all there’ll be tears and <q2>Papa</q2> and <q2>Mamma,</q2> and she’s
                    frozen in a minute and must go back—but you wrap the fur cloak round her first
                    thing and carry her to the sleigh.</q></ref>
            <ref song="19"><q>That’s the way,</q> said <c8>Dólokhov</c8></ref>
            <ref song="19"><q>Well, good-by, Matrëna,</q> said <c7>Anatole</c7>, kissing her. <q>Ah,
                    my revels here are over. Remember me to Stëshka. There, good-by! Good-by,
                    Matrëna, wish me luck!</q></ref>
            <ref song="19"><q>Go!</q> he cried, twisting the reins round his hands, and the troyka
                tore down the Nikítski Boulevard.</ref>
            <ref song="19">When they reached the gate <c8>Dólokhov</c8> whistled. The whistle was
                answered, and a maidservant ran out. <q>Come into the courtyard or you’ll be seen;
                    she’ll come out directly,</q> said she. <c8>Dólokhov</c8> stayed by the gate.
                    <c7>Anatole</c7> followed the maid into the courtyard, turned the corner, and
                ran up into the porch. </ref>
            <ref song="19"><q><c7>Kurágin</c7>! Come back!</q> shouted <c8>Dólokhov</c8>.
                    <q>Betrayed! Back!</q></ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="18">
            <ch>CHAPTER 18</ch>
            <ref song="20"><q>You shameless good-for-nothing!</q> said she. <q>I won’t hear a
                    word.</q></ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>Disgusting, abominable... In my house... horrid girl, hussy! I’m only
                    sorry for her father!</q> thought she, trying to restrain her wrath.</ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>A nice girl! Very nice!</q> said <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4>.
                    <q>Arranging meetings with lovers in my house! It’s no use pretending: you
                    listen when I speak to you!</q> And <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4> touched her arm.
                    <q>Listen when I speak! You’ve disgraced yourself like the lowest of hussies.
                    I’d treat you differently, but I’m sorry for your father, so I will conceal
                    it.</q></ref>
            <ref song="20"><c3>Natásha</c3> did not change her position, but her whole body heaved
                with noiseless, convulsive sobs which choked her.</ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>It’s lucky for him that he escaped me; but I’ll find him!</q> she said
                in her rough voice. <q>Do you hear what I am saying or not?</q> she added.</ref>
            <ref song="20">She put her large hand under <c3>Natásha</c3>’s face and turned it toward
                her.</ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>Let me be!... What is it to me?... I shall die!</q> she muttered,
                wrenching herself from <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4>’s hands with a vicious effort and
                sinking down again into her former position.</ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>But when your father comes back tomorrow what am I to tell him?
                    Eh?</q> Again <c3>Natásha</c3>’s body shook with sobs. <q>Suppose he finds out,
                    and your brother, and your betrothed?</q></ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>I have no betrothed: I have refused him!</q> cried <c3>Natásha</c3>.
                    <q>That’s all the same,</q> continued <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4>. <q>If they hear
                    of this, will they let it pass? He, your father, I know him... if he challenges
                    him to a duel will that be all right? Eh?</q>
                <q>Oh, let me be! Why have you interfered at all? Why? Why? Who asked you to?</q>
                shouted <c3>Natásha</c3>, raising herself on the sofa and looking malignantly at
                    <c4>Márya</c4> Dmítrievna.</ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>But what did you want?</q> cried <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4>, growing
                angry again. <q>Were you kept under lock and key? Who hindered his coming to the
                    house? Why carry you off as if you were some gypsy singing girl?... Well, if he
                    had carried you off... do you think they wouldn’t have found him? Your father,
                    or brother, or your betrothed? And he’s a scoundrel, a wretch—that’s a fact!</q>
                <q>He is better than any of you!</q> exclaimed <c3>Natásha</c3> getting up. <q>If
                    you hadn’t interfered... Oh, my God! What is it all? What is it? <c6>Sónya</c6>,
                    why?... Go away!</q></ref>
            <ref song="20">And she burst into sobs with the despairing vehemence with which people
                bewail disasters they feel they have themselves occasioned. <c4>Márya
                    Dmítrievna</c4> was to speak again but <c3>Natásha</c3> cried out: <q>Go away!
                    Go away! You all hate and despise me!</q> and she threw herself back on the
                sofa.</ref>
            <ref song="20"><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4> put a pillow under her head, covered her with
                two quilts, and herself brought her some lime-flower water, but <c3>Natásha</c3> did
                not respond to her.</ref>
            <ref song="20"><q>Well, let her sleep,</q> said <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4> as she went
                out of the room supposing <c3>Natásha</c3> to be asleep.</ref>
            <ref song="20">But <c3>Natásha</c3> was not asleep; with pale face and fixed wide-open
                eyes she looked straight before her. All that night she did not sleep or weep and
                did not speak to <c6>Sónya</c6> who got up and went to her several times.</ref>
            <ref song="20">With compressed and parched lips and dry fixed eyes, she sat at the
                window, uneasily watching the people who drove past and hurriedly glancing round at
                anyone who entered the room. She was evidently expecting news of him and that he
                would come or would write to her.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="19">
            <ch>CHAPTER 19</ch>
            <ref song="21">When he returned to Moscow <c2>Pierre</c2> was handed a letter from
                    <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4> asking him to come and see her on a matter of great
                importance relating to <c1>Andrew</c1> Bolkónski and his betrothed.</ref>
            <ref song="21"><q>What can have happened? And what can they want with me?</q> thought he
                as he dressed to go to <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4>’s.</ref>
            <ref song="17"><q>Yes, indeed, that’s a true sage,</q> thought <c2>Pierre</c2>. <q>He
                    sees nothing beyond the pleasure of the moment, nothing troubles him and so he
                    is always cheerful, satisfied, and serene. What wouldn’t I give to be like
                    him!</q> he thought enviously.</ref>
            <ref song="21"><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4> informed him that <c3>Natásha</c3> had refused
                    <c1>Prince Andrew</c1> without her parents’ knowledge and that the cause of this
                was <c7>Anatole Kurágin</c7> into whose society <c2>Pierre</c2>’s wife had thrown
                her and with whom <c3>Natásha</c3> had tried to elope during her father’s absence,
                in order to be married secretly.</ref>
            <ref song="21"><c2>Pierre</c2> raised his shoulders and listened open-mouthed to what
                was told him, scarcely able to believe his own ears. That <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>’s
                deeply loved affianced wife—the same <c3>Natásha</c3> Rostóva who used to be so
                charming—should give up Bolkónski for that fool <c7>Anatole</c7> who was already
                secretly married (as <c2>Pierre</c2> knew), and should be so in love with him as to
                agree to run away with him, was something <c2>Pierre</c2> could not conceive and
                could not imagine.</ref>
            <ref song="21"><q>They are all alike!</q> he said to himself, reflecting that he was not
                the only man unfortunate enough to be tied to a bad woman. But still he pitied
                    <c1>Prince Andrew</c1> to the point of tears and sympathized with his wounded
                pride, and the more he pitied his friend the more did he think with contempt and
                even with disgust of that <c3>Natásha</c3> who had just passed him in the ballroom
                with such a look of cold dignity.</ref>
            <ref song="21">Natásha looked from one to the other as a hunted and wounded animal looks
                at the approaching dogs and sportsmen.</ref>
            <ref song="21">She was afraid that the count or Bolkónski, who might arrive at any
                moment, if they knew of this affair (which she hoped to hide from them) might
                challenge <c7>Anatole</c7> to a duel, and she therefore asked <c2>Pierre</c2> to
                tell his brother-in-law in her name to leave Moscow and not dare to let her set eyes
                on him again. <c2>Pierre</c2>—only now realizing the danger to the old count,
                Nicholas, and Prince <c1>Andrew</c1>—promised to do as she wished.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="20">
            <ch>CHAPTER 20</ch>
            <ref song="22">He drove through the town seeking <c7>Anatole Kurágin</c7>, at the
                thought of whom now the blood rushed to his heart and he felt a difficulty in
                breathing. He was not at the ice hills, nor at the gypsies’, nor at Komoneno’s.
                    <c2>Pierre</c2> drove to the Club. In the Club all was going on as usual. The
                members who were assembling for dinner were sitting about in groups; they greeted
                    <c2>Pierre</c2> and spoke of the town news.</ref>
            <ref song="22">One of <c2>Pierre</c2>’s acquaintances, while they were talking about the
                weather, asked if he had heard of <c7>Kurágin</c7>’s abduction of Rostóva which was
                talked of in the town, and was it true? <c2>Pierre</c2> laughed and said it was
                nonsense for he had just come from the Rostóvs’.</ref>
            <ref song="22">It seemed to him essential to see <c3>Natásha</c3>. In the evening he
                drove to his sister’s to discuss with her how to arrange a meeting. When
                    <c2>Pierre</c2> returned home after vainly hunting all over Moscow, his valet
                informed him that Prince <c7>Anatole</c7> was with the countess.</ref>
            <ref song="22"><c2>Pierre</c2> without greeting his wife whom he had not seen since his
                return—at that moment she was more repulsive to him than ever—entered the drawing
                room and seeing <c7>Anatole</c7> went up to him.</ref>
            <ref song="22"><q>Ah, <c2>Pierre</c2>,</q> said the countess going up to her husband.
                    <q>You don’t know what a plight our <c7>Anatole</c7>...</q></ref>
            <ref song="22"><q>Where you are, there is vice and evil!</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2> to his
                wife. <q><c7>Anatole</c7>, come with me! I must speak to you,</q> he added in
                French.</ref>
            <ref song="22"><c7>Anatole</c7> followed him with his usual jaunty step but his face
                betrayed anxiety.</ref>
            <ref song="22">Having entered his study <c2>Pierre</c2> closed the door and addressed
                    <c7>Anatole</c7> without looking at him.</ref>
            <ref song="23">
                <q>You promised <c3>Countess Rostóva</c3> to marry her and were about to elope with
                    her, is that so?</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="23"><q>Mon cher,</q> answered <c7>Anatole</c7> (their whole conversation was
                in French), <q>I don’t consider myself bound to answer questions put to me in that
                    tone.</q></ref>
            <ref song="23"><c2>Pierre</c2>’s face, already pale, became distorted by fury. He seized
                    <c7>Anatole</c7> by the collar of his uniform with his big hand and shook him
                from side to side till <c7>Anatole</c7>’s face showed a sufficient degree of
                terror.</ref>
            <ref song="23"><q>When I tell you that I must talk to you!...</q> repeated
                    <c2>Pierre</c2>. <q>Come now, this is stupid. What?</q> said <c7>Anatole</c7>,
                fingering a button of his collar that had been wrenched loose with a bit of the
                cloth. <q>You’re a scoundrel and a blackguard, and I don’t know what deprives me
                    from the pleasure of smashing your head with this!</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2>,
                expressing himself so artificially because he was talking French.</ref>
            <ref song="23">
                <q>Did you promise to marry her?</q>
                <q>I... I didn’t think of it. I never promised, because...</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="23"><q>Have you any letters of hers? Any letters?</q> he said, moving toward
                    <c7>Anatole</c7>.</ref>
            <ref song="23"><q>I shan’t be violent, don’t be afraid!</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2> in
                answer to a frightened gesture of <c7>Anatole</c7>’s. <q>First, the letters,</q>
                said he, as if repeating a lesson to himself. <q>Secondly,</q> he continued after a
                short pause, again rising and again pacing the room, <q>tomorrow you must get out of
                    Moscow.</q>
                <q>But how can I?...</q>
                <q>Thirdly,</q>
                <c2>Pierre</c2> continued without listening to him, <q>you must never breathe a word
                    of what has passed between you and <c3>Countess Rostóva</c3>. I know I can’t
                    prevent your doing so, but if you have a spark of conscience...</q>
                <c2>Pierre</c2> paced the room several times in silence. <c7>Anatole</c7> sat at a
                table frowning and biting his lips.</ref>
            <ref song="23">
                <q>After all, you must understand that besides your pleasure there is such a thing
                    as other people’s happiness and peace, and that you are ruining a whole life for
                    the sake of amusing yourself! Amuse yourself with women like my wife—with them
                    you are within your rights, for they know what you want of them. They are armed
                    against you by the same experience of debauchery; but to promise a maid to marry
                    her... to deceive, to kidnap.... Don’t you understand that it is as mean as
                    beating an old man or a child?...</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="23"><q>I don’t know about that, eh?</q> said <c7>Anatole</c7>, growing more
                confident as <c2>Pierre</c2> mastered his wrath. <q>I don’t know that and don’t want
                    to,</q> he said, not looking at <c2>Pierre</c2> and with a slight tremor of his
                lower jaw, <q>but you have used such words to me—<q2>mean</q2> and so on—which as a
                    man of honor I can’t allow anyone to use.</q></ref>
            <ref song="23"><q>Is it satisfaction you want?</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2> ironically.
                    <q>You could at least take back your words. What? If you want me to do as you
                    wish, eh?</q></ref>
            <ref song="23"><q>I take them back, I take them back!</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2>, <q>and I
                    ask you to forgive me.</q>
                <c2>Pierre</c2> involuntarily glanced at the loose button. <q>And if you require
                    money for your journey...</q>
                <c7>Anatole</c7> smiled. The expression of that base and cringing smile, which
                    <c2>Pierre</c2> knew so well in his wife, revolted him. <q>Oh, vile and
                    heartless brood!</q> he exclaimed, and left the room. Next day <c7>Anatole</c7>
                left for Petersburg.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="21">
            <ch>CHAPTER 21</ch>
            <ref song="24">The whole house was in a state of alarm and commotion. <c3>Natásha</c3>
                was very ill, having, as <c4>Márya Dmítrievna</c4> told him in secret, poisoned
                herself the night after she had been told that <c7>Anatole</c7> was married, with
                some arsenic she had stealthily procured. After swallowing a little she had been so
                frightened that she woke <c6>Sónya</c6> and told her what she had done. The
                necessary antidotes had been administered in time and she was now out of danger,
                though still so weak that it was out of the question to move her to the country, and
                so the countess had been sent for.</ref>
            <ref song="24">He was awaiting <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>’s return with dread and went every
                day to the old prince’s for news of him.</ref>
            <ref song="25"><q>Well, how are you? Still getting stouter?</q> he said with animation,
                but the new wrinkle on his forehead deepened. <q>Yes, I am well,</q> he said in
                answer to <c2>Pierre</c2>’s question, and smiled.</ref>
            <ref song="25">
                <q>Forgive me for troubling you....</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="25">
                <q>I have received a refusal from <c3>Countess Rostóva</c3> and have heard reports
                    of your brother-in-law having sought her hand, or something of that kind. Is
                    that true?</q>
            </ref>
            <ref song="25">
                <p><q>Here are her letters and her portrait,</q> said he.</p>
                <p>He took the packet from the table and handed it to <c2>Pierre</c2>.</p>
                <p>
                    <q>Give this to the countess... if you see her.</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>She is very ill,</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2>.</p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="25">
                <p>
                    <q>He left long ago. She has been at death’s door.</q>
                </p>
                <p><q>I much regret her illness,</q> said <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>; and he smiled like
                    his father, coldly, maliciously, and unpleasantly.</p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="25">
                <p><q>Well, it doesn’t matter,</q> said <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>. <q>Tell <c3>Countess
                            Rostóva</c3> that she was and is perfectly free and that I wish her all
                        that is good.</q></p>

                <p><c2>Pierre</c2> took the packet. <c1>Prince Andrew</c1>, as if trying to remember
                    whether he had something more to say, or waiting to see if <c2>Pierre</c2> would
                    say anything, looked fixedly at him.</p>

                <p><q>I say, do you remember our discussion in Petersburg?</q> asked
                    <c2>Pierre</c2>, <q>about...</q></p>

                <p><q>Yes,</q> returned <c1>Prince Andrew</c1> hastily. <q>I said that a fallen
                        woman should be forgiven, but I didn’t say I could forgive her. I
                    can’t.</q></p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="25"><c1>Prince Andrew</c1> interrupted him and cried sharply: <q>Yes, ask her
                    hand again, be magnanimous, and so on?... Yes, that would be very noble, but I
                    am unable to follow in that gentleman’s footsteps. If you wish to be my friend
                    never speak to me of that... of all that! Well, good-by. So you’ll give her the
                    packet?</q></ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="22">
            <ch>CHAPTER 22</ch>
            <ref song="26"><c3>Natásha</c3> was standing in the middle of the drawing room,
                emaciated, with a pale set face, but not at all shamefaced as <c2>Pierre</c2>
                expected to find her. When he appeared at the door she grew flurried, evidently
                undecided whether to go to meet him or to wait till he came up.</ref>
            <ref song="26"><c2>Pierre</c2> hastened to her. He thought she would give him her hand
                as usual; but she, stepping up to him, stopped, breathing heavily, her arms hanging
                lifelessly just in the pose she used to stand in when she went to the middle of the
                ballroom to sing, but with quite a different expression of face.</ref>
            <ref song="26"><q><c2>Peter Kirílovich</c2>,</q> she began rapidly, <q>Prince Bolkónski
                    was your friend—is your friend,</q> she corrected herself. (It seemed to her
                that everything that had once been must now be different.) <q>He told me once to
                    apply to you...</q></ref>
            <ref song="26"><c2>Pierre</c2> sniffed as he looked at her, but did not speak. Till then
                he had reproached her in his heart and tried to despise her, but he now felt so
                sorry for her that there was no room in his soul for reproach.</ref>
            <ref song="26">
                <p><q>He is here now: tell him... to for... forgive me!</q> She stopped and breathed
                    still more quickly, but did not shed tears.</p>

                <p><q>Yes... I will tell him,</q> answered <c2>Pierre</c2>; <q>but...</q></p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="26"><q>No, I know all is over,</q> she said hurriedly. <q>No, that can never
                    be. I’m only tormented by the wrong I have done him. Tell him only that I beg
                    him to forgive, forgive, forgive me for everything....</q></ref>
            <ref song="26"><q>I will tell him, I will tell him everything once more,</q> said
                    <c2>Pierre</c2>. <q>But... I should like to know one thing....</q></ref>
            <ref song="26">
                <p><q>I should like to know, did you love...</q>
                    <c2>Pierre</c2> did not know how to refer to <c7>Anatole</c7> and flushed at the
                    thought of him—<q>did you love that bad man?</q></p>

                <p><q>Don’t call him bad!</q> said <c3>Natásha</c3>. <q>But I don’t know, don’t know
                        at all....</q></p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="26">She began to cry and a still greater sense of pity, tenderness, and love
                welled up in <c2>Pierre</c2>. He felt the tears trickle under his spectacles and
                hoped they would not be noticed.</ref>
            <ref song="26">
                <p><q>We won’t speak of it any more, my dear,</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2>, and his
                    gentle, cordial tone suddenly seemed very strange to <c3>Natásha</c3>.</p>

                <p><q>We won’t speak of it, my dear—I’ll tell him everything; but one thing I beg of
                        you, consider me your friend and if you want help, advice, or simply to open
                        your heart to someone—not now, but when your mind is clearer--think of
                        me!</q> He took her hand and kissed it. <q>I shall be happy if it’s in my
                        power...</q></p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="26">
                <p><c2>Pierre</c2> grew confused.</p>

                <p><q>Don’t speak to me like that. I am not worth it!</q> exclaimed <c3>Natásha</c3>
                    and turned to leave the room, but <c2>Pierre</c2> held her hand.</p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="26">
                <p><q>Stop, stop! You have your whole life before you,</q> said he to her.</p>

                <p><q>Before me? No! All is over for me,</q> she replied with shame and
                    self-abasement.</p>

                <p><q>All over?</q> he repeated. <q>If I were not myself, but the handsomest,
                        cleverest, and best man in the world, and were free, I would this moment ask
                        on my knees for your hand and your love!</q></p>

                <p>For the first time for many days <c3>Natásha</c3> wept tears of gratitude and
                    tenderness, and glancing at <c2>Pierre</c2> she went out of the room.</p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="26"><c2>Pierre</c2> too when she had gone almost ran into the anteroom,
                restraining tears of tenderness and joy that choked him, and without finding the
                sleeves of his fur cloak threw it on and got into his sleigh.</ref>
            <ref song="27"><q>Where to?</q>
                <c2>Pierre</c2> asked himself. <q>Where can I go now? Surely not to the Club or to
                    pay calls?</q> All men seemed so pitiful, so poor, in comparison with this
                feeling of tenderness and love he experienced: in comparison with that softened,
                grateful, last look she had given him through her tears.</ref>
            <ref song="26"><q>Home!</q> said <c2>Pierre</c2>, and despite twenty-two degrees of
                frost Fahrenheit he threw open the bearskin cloak from his broad chest and inhaled
                the air with joy.</ref>
            <ref song="27">It was clear and frosty. Above the dirty, ill-lit streets, above the
                black roofs, stretched the dark starry sky. Only looking up at the sky did
                    <c2>Pierre</c2> cease to feel how sordid and humiliating were all mundane things
                compared with the heights to which his soul had just been raised. At the entrance to
                the Arbát Square an immense expanse of dark starry sky presented itself to his eyes.
                Almost in the center of it, above the Prechístenka Boulevard, surrounded and
                sprinkled on all sides by stars but distinguished from them all by its nearness to
                the earth, its white light, and its long uplifted tail, shone the enormous and
                brilliant comet of 1812—the comet which was said to portend all kinds of woes and
                the end of the world. In <c2>Pierre</c2>, however, that comet with its long luminous
                tail aroused no feeling of fear. On the contrary he gazed joyfully, his eyes moist
                with tears, at this bright comet which, having traveled in its orbit with
                inconceivable velocity through immeasurable space, seemed suddenly—like an arrow
                piercing the earth—to remain fixed in a chosen spot, vigorously holding its tail
                erect, shining and displaying its white light amid countless other scintillating
                stars. It seemed to <c2>Pierre</c2> that this comet fully responded to what was
                passing in his own softened and uplifted soul, now blossoming into a new life.</ref>
        </chapter>
    </book>
    <book n="4">
        <chapter n="4">
            <ch>CHAPTER 4</ch>
            <ref song="09">
                <p><q>Well, now to the health of handsome women!</q> said Dólokhov, and with a
                    serious expression, but with a smile lurking at the corners of his mouth, he
                    turned with his glass to Pierre.</p>
                <p><q>Here’s to the health of lovely women, Peterkin—and their lovers!</q> he
                    added.</p>
            </ref>
            <ref song="09">Dólokhov looked at Pierre with clear, mirthful, cruel eyes, and that
                smile of his which seemed to say, <q>Ah! This is what I like!</q></ref>
            <ref song="09"><q>You...! you... scoundrel! I challenge you!</q> he ejaculated, and,
                pushing back his chair, he rose from the table.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="5">
            <ref song="09">Denísov first went to the barrier and announced: <q>As the adve’sawies
                    have wefused a weconciliation, please pwoceed. Take your pistols, and at the
                    word thwee begin to advance</q></ref>
            <ref song="09"><q>No-o-o!</q> muttered Dólokhov through his teeth, <q>no, it’s not
                    over.</q></ref>
            <ref song="09"><q>Missed!</q> shouted Dólokhov, and he lay helplessly, face downwards on
                the snow.</ref>
            <ref song="09"><q>My mother! My mother, my angel, my adored angel mother,</q> and
                Dólokhov pressed Rostóv’s hand and burst into tears.</ref>
        </chapter>
        <chapter n="6">
            <ch>CHAPTER 5</ch>
            <ref song="10">Such a storm of feelings, thoughts, and memories suddenly arose within
                him that he could not fall asleep, nor even remain in one place, but had to jump up
                and pace the room with rapid steps.</ref>
        </chapter>
    </book>
    <book n="2">
        <chapter n="4">
            <ch>CHAPTER 4</ch>
            <ref song="10"><q>You see, my fwiend,</q> he said, <q>we sleep when we don’t love. We
                    are childwen of the dust... but one falls in love and one is a God, one is pua’
                    as on the fihst day of cweation... Who’s that now? Send him to the devil, I’m
                    busy!</q> he shouted to Lavrúshka, who went up to him not in the least
                abashed.</ref>
        </chapter>
    </book>
    <book n="6">
        <chapter n="2">
            <ch>CHAPTER 2</ch>
            <ref song="06"><q>Sónya! Sónya!</q> he again heard the first speaker. <q>Oh, how can you
                    sleep? Only look how glorious it is! Ah, how glorious! Do wake up, Sónya!</q>
                she said almost with tears in her voice. <q>There never, never was such a lovely
                    night before!</q></ref>
            <ref song="06">
                <q>Do just come and see what a moon!... Oh, how lovely! Come here.... Darling,
                    sweetheart, come here! There, you see? I feel like sitting down on my heels,
                    putting my arms round my knees like this, straining tight, as tight as possible,
                    and flying away! Like this....</q>
            </ref>
        </chapter>
    </book>
    <book n="7">
        <chapter n="10">
            <ch>CHAPTER 10</ch>
            <ref song="06"><q>No, I don’t believe we ever were in animals,</q> said Natásha, still
                in a whisper though the music had ceased. <q>But I am certain that we were angels
                    somewhere there, and have been here, and that is why we remember....</q></ref>
        </chapter>
    </book>
    <book n="9">
        <chapter n="19">
            <ch>CHAPTER 19</ch>
            <ref song="14"><p>Writing the words L’Empereur Napoléon in numbers, it appears that the sum of them is
                666, and that Napoleon was therefore the beast foretold in the Apocalypse. Moreover,
                by applying the same system to the words quarante-deux, * which was the term allowed
                to the beast that <q>spoke great things and blasphemies,</q> the same number 666 was
                obtained; from which it followed that the limit fixed for Napoleon’s power had come
                in the year 1812 when the French emperor was forty-two. This prophecy pleased Pierre
                very much and he often asked himself what would put an end to the power of the
                beast, that is, of Napoleon, and tried by the same system of using letters as
                numbers and adding them up, to find an answer to the question that engrossed him. He
                wrote the words L’Empereur Alexandre, La nation russe and added up their numbers,
                but the sums were either more or less than 666. Once when making such calculations
                he wrote down his own name in French, Comte Pierre Besouhoff, but the sum of the
                numbers did not come right. Then he changed the spelling, substituting a z for the s
                and adding de and the article le, still without obtaining the desired result. Then
                it occurred to him: if the answer to the question were contained in his name, his
                nationality would also be given in the answer. So he wrote Le russe Besuhof and
                adding up the numbers got 671. This was only five too much, and five was represented
                by e, the very letter elided from the article le before the word Empereur. By
                omitting the e, though incorrectly, Pierre got the answer he sought. L’russe Besuhof
                made 666. This discovery excited him. How, or by what means, he was connected with
                the great event foretold in the Apocalypse he did not know, but he did not doubt
                that connection for a moment. His love for Natásha, Antichrist, Napoleon, the
                invasion, the comet, 666, L’Empereur Napoléon, and L’russe Besuhof—all this had to
                mature and culminate, to lift him out of that spellbound, petty sphere of Moscow
                habits in which he felt himself held captive and lead him to a great achievement and
                great happiness.</p></ref>
        </chapter>
    </book>
</references>
