    <book>
        <title>BOOK EIGHT: 1811 - 12</title>

        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER I </title>
            <p>After <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>’s engagement to <chara>Natásha</chara>, <chara>Pierre</chara> without any apparent cause
                suddenly felt it impossible to go on living as before. Firmly convinced as he was of
                the truths revealed to him by his benefactor, and happy as he had been in perfecting
                his inner man, to which he had devoted himself with such ardor—all the zest of such
                a life vanished after the engagement of <chara>Andrew</chara> and <chara>Natásha</chara> and the death of Joseph
                Alexéevich, the news of which reached him almost at the same time. Only the skeleton
                of life remained: his house, a brilliant wife who now enjoyed the favors of a very
                important personage, acquaintance with all Petersburg, and his court service with
                its dull formalities. And this life suddenly seemed to <chara>Pierre</chara> unexpectedly
                loathsome. He ceased keeping a diary, avoided the company of the Brothers, began
                going to the club again, drank a great deal, and came once more in touch with the
                bachelor sets, leading such a life that the <chara>Countess Hélène</chara> thought it necessary to
                speak severely to him about it. <chara>Pierre</chara> felt that she was right, and to avoid
                compromising her went away to Moscow.</p>

            <p>In Moscow as soon as he entered his huge house in which the faded and fading
                princesses still lived, with its enormous retinue; as soon as, driving through the
                town, he saw the Iberian shrine with innumerable tapers burning before the golden
                covers of the icons, the Krémlin Square with its snow undisturbed by vehicles, the
                sleigh drivers and hovels of the Sívtsev Vrazhók, those old Moscovites who desired
                nothing, hurried nowhere, and were ending their days leisurely; when he saw those
                old Moscow ladies, the Moscow balls, and the English Club, he felt himself at home
                in a quiet haven. In Moscow he felt at peace, at home, warm and dirty as in an old
                dressing gown.</p>

            <p>Moscow society, from the old women down to the children, received <chara>Pierre</chara> like a
                long-expected guest whose place was always ready awaiting him. For Moscow society
                <chara>Pierre</chara> was the nicest, kindest, most intellectual, merriest, and most magnanimous of
                cranks, a heedless, genial nobleman of the old Russian type. His purse was always
                empty because it was open to everyone.</p>

            <p>Benefit performances, poor pictures, statues, benevolent societies, gypsy choirs,
                schools, subscription dinners, sprees, Freemasons, churches, and books—no one and
                nothing met with a refusal from him, and had it not been for two friends who had
                borrowed large sums from him and taken him under their protection, he would have
                given everything away. There was never a dinner or soiree at the club without him.
                As soon as he sank into his place on the sofa after two bottles of Margaux he was
                surrounded, and talking, disputing, and joking began. When there were quarrels, his
                kindly smile and well-timed jests reconciled the antagonists. The Masonic dinners
                were dull and dreary when he was not there.</p>

            <p>When after a bachelor supper he rose with his amiable and kindly smile, yielding to
                the entreaties of the festive company to drive off somewhere with them, shouts of
                delight and triumph arose among the young men. At balls he danced if a partner was
                needed. Young ladies, married and unmarried, liked him because without making love
                to any of them, he was equally amiable to all, especially after supper. <q>Il est
                    charmant; il n’a pas de sexe,</q> * they said of him.</p>

            <p>* <q>He is charming; he has no sex.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> was one of those retired gentlemen-in-waiting of whom there were hundreds
                good-humoredly ending their days in Moscow.</p>

            <p>How horrified he would have been seven years before, when he first arrived from
                abroad, had he been told that there was no need for him to seek or plan anything,
                that his rut had long been shaped, eternally predetermined, and that wriggle as he
                might, he would be what all in his position were. He could not have believed it! Had
                he not at one time longed with all his heart to establish a republic in Russia; then
                himself to be a Napoleon; then to be a philosopher; and then a strategist and the
                conqueror of Napoleon? Had he not seen the possibility of, and passionately desired,
                the regeneration of the sinful human race, and his own progress to the highest
                degree of perfection? Had he not established schools and hospitals and liberated his
                serfs?</p>

            <p>But instead of all that—here he was, the wealthy husband of an unfaithful wife, a
                retired gentleman-in-waiting, fond of eating and drinking and, as he unbuttoned his
                waistcoat, of abusing the government a bit, a member of the Moscow English Club, and
                a universal favorite in Moscow society. For a long time he could not reconcile
                himself to the idea that he was one of those same retired Moscow
                gentlemen-in-waiting he had so despised seven years before.</p>

            <p>Sometimes he consoled himself with the thought that he was only living this life
                temporarily; but then he was shocked by the thought of how many, like himself, had
                entered that life and that club temporarily, with all their teeth and hair, and had
                only left it when not a single tooth or hair remained.</p>

            <p>In moments of pride, when he thought of his position it seemed to him that he was
                quite different and distinct from those other retired gentlemen-in-waiting he had
                formerly despised: they were empty, stupid, contented fellows, satisfied with their
                position, <q>while I am still discontented and want to do something for mankind. But
                    perhaps all these comrades of mine struggled just like me and sought something
                    new, a path in life of their own, and like me were brought by force of
                    circumstances, society, and race—by that elemental force against which man is
                    powerless—to the condition I am in,</q> said he to himself in moments of
                humility; and after living some time in Moscow he no longer despised, but began to
                grow fond of, to respect, and to pity his comrades in destiny, as he pitied
                himself.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> no longer suffered moments of despair, hypochondria, and disgust with life,
                but the malady that had formerly found expression in such acute attacks was driven
                inwards and never left him for a moment. <q>What for? Why? What is going on in the
                    world?</q> he would ask himself in perplexity several times a day, involuntarily
                beginning to reflect anew on the meaning of the phenomena of life; but knowing by
                experience that there were no answers to these questions he made haste to turn away
                from them, and took up a book, or hurried off to the club or to Apollón
                Nikoláevich’s, to exchange the gossip of the town.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Hélène</chara>, who has never cared for anything but her own body and is one of the
                    stupidest women in the world,</q> thought <chara>Pierre</chara>, <q>is regarded by people as
                    the acme of intelligence and refinement, and they pay homage to her. Napoleon
                    Bonaparte was despised by all as long as he was great, but now that he has
                    become a wretched comedian the Emperor Francis wants to offer him his daughter
                    in an illegal marriage. The Spaniards, through the Catholic clergy, offer praise
                    to God for their victory over the French on the fourteenth of June, and the
                    French, also through the Catholic clergy, offer praise because on that same
                    fourteenth of June they defeated the Spaniards. My brother Masons swear by the
                    blood that they are ready to sacrifice everything for their neighbor, but they
                    do not give a ruble each to the collections for the poor, and they intrigue, the
                    Astraea Lodge against the Manna Seekers, and fuss about an authentic Scotch
                    carpet and a charter that nobody needs, and the meaning of which the very man
                    who wrote it does not understand. We all profess the Christian law of
                    forgiveness of injuries and love of our neighbors, the law in honor of which we
                    have built in Moscow forty times forty churches—but yesterday a deserter was
                    knouted to death and a minister of that same law of love and forgiveness, a
                    priest, gave the soldier a cross to kiss before his execution.</q> So thought
                <chara>Pierre</chara>, and the whole of this general deception which everyone accepts, accustomed
                as he was to it, astonished him each time as if it were something new. <q>I
                    understand the deception and confusion,</q> he thought, <q>but how am I to tell
                    them all that I see? I have tried, and have always found that they too in the
                    depths of their souls understand it as I do, and only try not to see it. So it
                    appears that it must be so! But I—what is to become of me?</q> thought he. He
                had the unfortunate capacity many men, especially Russians, have of seeing and
                believing in the possibility of goodness and truth, but of seeing the evil and
                falsehood of life too clearly to be able to take a serious part in it. Every sphere
                of work was connected, in his eyes, with evil and deception. Whatever he tried to
                be, whatever he engaged in, the evil and falsehood of it repulsed him and blocked
                every path of activity. Yet he had to live and to find occupation. It was too
                dreadful to be under the burden of these insoluble problems, so he abandoned himself
                to any distraction in order to forget them. He frequented every kind of society,
                drank much, bought pictures, engaged in building, and above all—read.</p>

            <p>He read, and read everything that came to hand. On coming home, while his valets were
                still taking off his things, he picked up a book and began to read. From reading he
                passed to sleeping, from sleeping to gossip in drawing rooms of the club, from
                gossip to carousals and women; from carousals back to gossip, reading, and wine.
                Drinking became more and more a physical and also a moral necessity. Though the
                doctors warned him that with his corpulence wine was dangerous for him, he drank a
                great deal. He was only quite at ease when having poured several glasses of wine
                mechanically into his large mouth he felt a pleasant warmth in his body, an
                amiability toward all his fellows, and a readiness to respond superficially to every
                idea without probing it deeply. Only after emptying a bottle or two did he feel
                dimly that the terribly tangled skein of life which previously had terrified him was
                not as dreadful as he had thought. He was always conscious of some aspect of that
                skein, as with a buzzing in his head after dinner or supper he chatted or listened
                to conversation or read. But under the influence of wine he said to himself: <q>It
                    doesn’t matter. I’ll get it unraveled. I have a solution ready, but have no time
                    now—I’ll think it all out later on!</q> But the later on never came.</p>

            <p>In the morning, on an empty stomach, all the old questions appeared as insoluble and
                terrible as ever, and <chara>Pierre</chara> hastily picked up a book, and if anyone came to see him
                he was glad.</p>

            <p>Sometimes he remembered how he had heard that soldiers in war when entrenched under
                the enemy’s fire, if they have nothing to do, try hard to find some occupation the
                more easily to bear the danger. To <chara>Pierre</chara> all men seemed like those soldiers,
                seeking refuge from life: some in ambition, some in cards, some in framing laws,
                some in women, some in toys, some in horses, some in politics, some in sport, some
                in wine, and some in governmental affairs. <q>Nothing is trivial, and nothing is
                    important, it’s all the same—only to save oneself from it as best one can,</q>
                thought <chara>Pierre</chara>. <q>Only not to see it, that dreadful it!</q></p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER II </title>
            <p>At the beginning of winter <chara>Prince Nicholas Bolkónski</chara> and his daughter moved to
                Moscow. At that time enthusiasm for the Emperor Alexander’s regime had weakened and
                a patriotic and anti-French tendency prevailed there, and this, together with his
                past and his intellect and his originality, at once made <chara>Prince Nicholas Bolkónski</chara>
                an object of particular respect to the Moscovites and the center of the Moscow
                opposition to the government.</p>

            <p>The prince had aged very much that year. He showed marked signs of senility by a
                tendency to fall asleep, forgetfulness of quite recent events, remembrance of remote
                ones, and the childish vanity with which he accepted the role of head of the Moscow
                opposition. In spite of this the old man inspired in all his visitors alike a
                feeling of respectful veneration—especially of an evening when he came in to tea in
                his old-fashioned coat and powdered wig and, aroused by anyone, told his abrupt
                stories of the past, or uttered yet more abrupt and scathing criticisms of the
                present. For them all, that old-fashioned house with its gigantic mirrors,
                pre-Revolution furniture, powdered footmen, and the stern shrewd old man (himself a
                relic of the past century) with his gentle daughter and the pretty Frenchwoman who
                were reverently devoted to him presented a majestic and agreeable spectacle. But the
                visitors did not reflect that besides the couple of hours during which they saw
                their host, there were also twenty-two hours in the day during which the private and
                intimate life of the house continued.</p>

            <p>Latterly that private life had become very trying for <chara>Princess Mary</chara>. There in Moscow
                she was deprived of her greatest pleasures—talks with the pilgrims and the solitude
                which refreshed her at Bald Hills—and she had none of the advantages and pleasures
                of city life. She did not go out into society; everyone knew that her father would
                not let her go anywhere without him, and his failing health prevented his going out
                himself, so that she was not invited to dinners and evening parties. She had quite
                abandoned the hope of getting married. She saw the coldness and malevolence with
                which the old prince received and dismissed the young men, possible suitors, who
                sometimes appeared at their house. She had no friends: during this visit to Moscow
                she had been disappointed in the two who had been nearest to her. Mademoiselle
                Bourienne, with whom she had never been able to be quite frank, had now become
                unpleasant to her, and for various reasons <chara>Princess Mary</chara> avoided her. Julie, with
                whom she had corresponded for the last five years, was in Moscow, but proved to be
                quite alien to her when they met. Just then Julie, who by the death of her brothers
                had become one of the richest heiresses in Moscow, was in the full whirl of society
                pleasures. She was surrounded by young men who, she fancied, had suddenly learned to
                appreciate her worth. Julie was at that stage in the life of a society woman when
                she feels that her last chance of marrying has come and that her fate must be
                decided now or never. On Thursdays <chara>Princess Mary</chara> remembered with a mournful smile
                that she now had no one to write to, since Julie—whose presence gave her no pleasure
                was here and they met every week. Like the old émigré who declined to marry the lady
                with whom he had spent his evenings for years, she regretted Julie’s presence and
                having no one to write to. In Moscow <chara>Princess Mary</chara> had no one to talk to, no one to
                whom to confide her sorrow, and much sorrow fell to her lot just then. The time for
                <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>’s return and marriage was approaching, but his request to her to
                prepare his father for it had not been carried out; in fact, it seemed as if matters
                were quite hopeless, for at every mention of the young <chara>Countess Rostóva</chara> the old
                prince (who apart from that was usually in a bad temper) lost control of himself.
                Another lately added sorrow arose from the lessons she gave her six year-old nephew.
                To her consternation she detected in herself in relation to little <chara>Nicholas</chara> some
                symptoms of her father’s irritability. However often she told herself that she must
                not get irritable when teaching her nephew, almost every time that, pointer in hand,
                she sat down to show him the French alphabet, she so longed to pour her own
                knowledge quickly and easily into the child—who was already afraid that Auntie might
                at any moment get angry—that at his slightest inattention she trembled, became
                flustered and heated, raised her voice, and sometimes pulled him by the arm and put
                him in the corner. Having put him in the corner she would herself begin to cry over
                her cruel, evil nature, and little <chara>Nicholas</chara>, following her example, would sob, and
                without permission would leave his corner, come to her, pull her wet hands from her
                face, and comfort her. But what distressed the princess most of all was her father’s
                irritability, which was always directed against her and had of late amounted to
                cruelty. Had he forced her to prostrate herself to the ground all night, had he
                beaten her or made her fetch wood or water, it would never have entered her mind to
                think her position hard; but this loving despot—the more cruel because he loved her
                and for that reason tormented himself and her—knew how not merely to hurt and
                humiliate her deliberately, but to show her that she was always to blame for
                everything. Of late he had exhibited a new trait that tormented <chara>Princess Mary</chara> more
                than anything else; this was his ever-increasing intimacy with Mademoiselle
                Bourienne. The idea that at the first moment of receiving the news of his son’s
                intentions had occurred to him in jest—that if <chara>Andrew</chara> got married he himself would
                marry Bourienne—had evidently pleased him, and latterly he had persistently, and as
                it seemed to <chara>Princess Mary</chara> merely to offend her, shown special endearments to the
                companion and expressed his dissatisfaction with his daughter by demonstrations of
                love of Bourienne.</p>

            <p>One day in Moscow in <chara>Princess Mary</chara>’s presence (she thought her father did it
                purposely when she was there) the old prince kissed Mademoiselle Bourienne’s hand
                and, drawing her to him, embraced her affectionately. <chara>Princess Mary</chara> flushed and ran
                out of the room. A few minutes later Mademoiselle Bourienne came into Princess
                <chara>Mary</chara>’s room smiling and making cheerful remarks in her agreeable voice. Princess
                <chara>Mary</chara> hastily wiped away her tears, went resolutely up to Mademoiselle Bourienne, and
                evidently unconscious of what she was doing began shouting in angry haste at the
                Frenchwoman, her voice breaking: <q>It’s horrible, vile, inhuman, to take advantage
                    of the weakness...</q> She did not finish. <q>Leave my room,</q> she exclaimed,
                and burst into sobs.</p>

            <p>Next day the prince did not say a word to his daughter, but she noticed that at
                dinner he gave orders that Mademoiselle Bourienne should be served first. After
                dinner, when the footman handed coffee and from habit began with the princess, the
                prince suddenly grew furious, threw his stick at Philip, and instantly gave
                instructions to have him conscripted for the army.</p>

            <p><q>He doesn’t obey... I said it twice... and he doesn’t obey! She is the first person
                    in this house; she’s my best friend,</q> cried the prince. <q>And if you allow
                    yourself,</q> he screamed in a fury, addressing <chara>Princess Mary</chara> for the first
                time, <q>to forget yourself again before her as you dared to do yesterday, I will
                    show you who is master in this house. Go! Don’t let me set eyes on you; beg her
                    pardon!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> asked Mademoiselle Bourienne’s pardon, and also her father’s pardon for
                herself and for Philip the footman, who had begged for her intervention.</p>

            <p>At such moments something like a pride of sacrifice gathered in her soul. And
                suddenly that father whom she had judged would look for his spectacles in her
                presence, fumbling near them and not seeing them, or would forget something that had
                just occurred, or take a false step with his failing legs and turn to see if anyone
                had noticed his feebleness, or, worst of all, at dinner when there were no visitors
                to excite him would suddenly fall asleep, letting his napkin drop and his shaking
                head sink over his plate. <q>He is old and feeble, and I dare to condemn him!</q>
                she thought at such moments, with a feeling of revulsion against herself.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER III </title>
            <p>In 1811 there was living in Moscow a French doctor—Métivier—who had rapidly become
                the fashion. He was enormously tall, handsome, amiable as Frenchmen are, and was, as
                all Moscow said, an extraordinarily clever doctor. He was received in the best
                houses not merely as a doctor, but as an equal.</p>

            <p><chara>Prince Nicholas</chara> had always ridiculed medicine, but latterly on Mademoiselle
                Bourienne’s advice had allowed this doctor to visit him and had grown accustomed to
                him. Métivier came to see the prince about twice a week.</p>

            <p>On December 6—St. Nicholas’ Day and the prince’s name day—all Moscow came to the
                prince’s front door but he gave orders to admit no one and to invite to dinner only
                a small number, a list of whom he gave to <chara>Princess Mary</chara>.</p>

            <p>Métivier, who came in the morning with his felicitations, considered it proper in his
                quality of doctor de forcer la consigne, * as he told <chara>Princess Mary</chara>, and went in to
                see the prince. It happened that on that morning of his name day the prince was in
                one of his worst moods. He had been going about the house all the morning finding
                fault with everyone and pretending not to understand what was said to him and not to
                be understood himself. <chara>Princess Mary</chara> well knew this mood of quiet absorbed
                querulousness, which generally culminated in a burst of rage, and she went about all
                that morning as though facing a cocked and loaded gun and awaited the inevitable
                explosion. Until the doctor’s arrival the morning had passed off safely. After
                admitting the doctor, <chara>Princess Mary</chara> sat down with a book in the drawing room near
                the door through which she could hear all that passed in the study.</p>

            <p>* To force the guard.</p>

            <p>At first she heard only Métivier’s voice, then her father’s, then both voices began
                speaking at the same time, the door was flung open, and on the threshold appeared
                the handsome figure of the terrified Métivier with his shock of black hair, and the
                prince in his dressing gown and fez, his face distorted with fury and the pupils of
                his eyes rolled downwards.</p>

            <p><q>You don’t understand?</q> shouted the prince, <q>but I do! French spy, slave of
                    Buonaparte, spy, get out of my house! Be off, I tell you...</q> and he slammed
                the door.</p>

            <p>Métivier, shrugging his shoulders, went up to Mademoiselle Bourienne who at the sound
                of shouting had run in from an adjoining room.</p>

            <p><q>The prince is not very well: bile and rush of blood to the head. Keep calm, I will
                    call again tomorrow,</q> said Métivier; and putting his fingers to his lips he
                hastened away.</p>

            <p>Through the study door came the sound of slippered feet and the cry: <q>Spies,
                    traitors, traitors everywhere! Not a moment’s peace in my own house!</q></p>

            <p>After Métivier’s departure the old prince called his daughter in, and the whole
                weight of his wrath fell on her. She was to blame that a spy had been admitted. Had
                he not told her, yes, told her to make a list, and not to admit anyone who was not
                on that list? Then why was that scoundrel admitted? She was the cause of it all.
                With her, he said, he could not have a moment’s peace and could not die quietly.</p>

            <p><q>No, ma’am! We must part, we must part! Understand that, understand it! I cannot
                    endure any more,</q> he said, and left the room. Then, as if afraid she might
                find some means of consolation, he returned and trying to appear calm added: <q>And
                    don’t imagine I have said this in a moment of anger. I am calm. I have thought
                    it over, and it will be carried out—we must part; so find some place for
                    yourself....</q> But he could not restrain himself and with the virulence of
                which only one who loves is capable, evidently suffering himself, he shook his fists
                at her and screamed:</p>

            <p><q>If only some fool would marry her!</q> Then he slammed the door, sent for
                Mademoiselle Bourienne, and subsided into his study.</p>

            <p>At two o’clock the six chosen guests assembled for dinner.</p>

            <p>These guests—the famous Count Rostopchín, Prince Lopukhín with his nephew, General
                Chatróv an old war comrade of the prince’s, and of the younger generation <chara>Pierre</chara> and
                Borís Drubetskóy—awaited the prince in the drawing room.</p>

            <p>Borís, who had come to Moscow on leave a few days before, had been anxious to be
                presented to <chara>Prince Nicholas Bolkónski</chara>, and had contrived to ingratiate himself so
                well that the old prince in his case made an exception to the rule of not receiving
                bachelors in his house.</p>

            <p>The prince’s house did not belong to what is known as fashionable society, but his
                little circle—though not much talked about in town—was one it was more flattering to
                be received in than any other. Borís had realized this the week before when the
                commander in chief in his presence invited Rostopchín to dinner on St. Nicholas’
                Day, and Rostopchín had replied that he could not come:</p>

            <p>
                <q>On that day I always go to pay my devotions to the relics of Prince Nicholas
                    Bolkónski.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Oh, yes, yes!</q> replied the commander in chief. <q>How is he?...</q></p>

            <p>The small group that assembled before dinner in the lofty old-fashioned drawing room
                with its old furniture resembled the solemn gathering of a court of justice. All
                were silent or talked in low tones. <chara>Prince Nicholas</chara> came in serious and taciturn.
                <chara>Princess Mary</chara> seemed even quieter and more diffident than usual. The guests were
                reluctant to address her, feeling that she was in no mood for their conversation.
                Count Rostopchín alone kept the conversation going, now relating the latest town
                news, and now the latest political gossip.</p>

            <p>Lopukhín and the old general occasionally took part in the conversation. Prince
                Bolkónski listened as a presiding judge receives a report, only now and then,
                silently or by a brief word, showing that he took heed of what was being reported to
                him. The tone of the conversation was such as indicated that no one approved of what
                was being done in the political world. Incidents were related evidently confirming
                the opinion that everything was going from bad to worse, but whether telling a story
                or giving an opinion the speaker always stopped, or was stopped, at the point beyond
                which his criticism might touch the sovereign himself.</p>

            <p>At dinner the talk turned on the latest political news: Napoleon’s seizure of the
                Duke of Oldenburg’s territory, and the Russian Note, hostile to Napoleon, which had
                been sent to all the European courts.</p>

            <p><q>Bonaparte treats Europe as a pirate does a captured vessel,</q> said Count
                Rostopchín, repeating a phrase he had uttered several times before. <q>One only
                    wonders at the long-suffering or blindness of the crowned heads. Now the Pope’s
                    turn has come and Bonaparte doesn’t scruple to depose the head of the Catholic
                    Church—yet all keep silent! Our sovereign alone has protested against the
                    seizure of the Duke of Oldenburg’s territory, and even...</q> Count Rostopchín
                paused, feeling that he had reached the limit beyond which censure was
                impossible.</p>

            <p><q>Other territories have been offered in exchange for the Duchy of Oldenburg,</q>
                said Prince Bolkónski. <q>He shifts the Dukes about as I might move my serfs from
                    Bald Hills to Boguchárovo or my Ryazán estates.</q></p>

            <p><q>The Duke of Oldenburg bears his misfortunes with admirable strength of character
                    and resignation,</q> remarked Borís, joining in respectfully.</p>

            <p>He said this because on his journey from Petersburg he had had the honor of being
                presented to the Duke. Prince Bolkónski glanced at the young man as if about to say
                something in reply, but changed his mind, evidently considering him too young.</p>

            <p><q>I have read our protests about the Oldenburg affair and was surprised how badly
                    the Note was worded,</q> remarked Count Rostopchín in the casual tone of a man
                dealing with a subject quite familiar to him.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> looked at Rostopchín with naïve astonishment, not understanding why he should
                be disturbed by the bad composition of the Note.</p>

            <p><q>Does it matter, Count, how the Note is worded,</q> he asked, <q>so long as its
                    substance is forcible?</q></p>

            <p><q>My dear fellow, with our five hundred thousand troops it should be easy to have a
                    good style,</q> returned Count Rostopchín.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> now understood the count’s dissatisfaction with the wording of the Note.</p>

            <p><q>One would have thought quill drivers enough had sprung up,</q> remarked the old
                prince. <q>There in Petersburg they are always writing—not notes only but even new
                    laws. My <chara>Andrew</chara> there has written a whole volume of laws for Russia. Nowadays
                    they are always writing!</q> and he laughed unnaturally.</p>

            <p>There was a momentary pause in the conversation; the old general cleared his throat
                to draw attention.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Did you hear of the last event at the review in Petersburg? The figure cut by the
                    new French ambassador.</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>Eh? Yes, I heard something: he said something awkward in His Majesty’s
                    presence.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>His Majesty drew attention to the Grenadier division and to the march past,</q>
                continued the general, <q>and it seems the ambassador took no notice and allowed
                    himself to reply that: <q2>We in France pay no attention to such trifles!</q2>
                    The Emperor did not condescend to reply. At the next review, they say, the
                    Emperor did not once deign to address him.</q></p>

            <p>All were silent. On this fact relating to the Emperor personally, it was impossible
                to pass any judgment.</p>

            <p><q>Impudent fellows!</q> said the prince. <q>You know Métivier? I turned him out of
                    my house this morning. He was here; they admitted him in spite of my request
                    that they should let no one in,</q> he went on, glancing angrily at his
                daughter.</p>

            <p>And he narrated his whole conversation with the French doctor and the reasons that
                convinced him that Métivier was a spy. Though these reasons were very insufficient
                and obscure, no one made any rejoinder.</p>

            <p>After the roast, champagne was served. The guests rose to congratulate the old
                prince. <chara>Princess Mary</chara>, too, went round to him.</p>

            <p>He gave her a cold, angry look and offered her his wrinkled, clean-shaven cheek to
                kiss. The whole expression of his face told her that he had not forgotten the
                morning’s talk, that his decision remained in force, and only the presence of
                visitors hindered his speaking of it to her now.</p>

            <p>When they went into the drawing room where coffee was served, the old men sat
                together.</p>

            <p><chara>Prince Nicholas</chara> grew more animated and expressed his views on the impending war.</p>

            <p>He said that our wars with Bonaparte would be disastrous so long as we sought
                alliances with the Germans and thrust ourselves into European affairs, into which we
                had been drawn by the Peace of Tilsit. <q>We ought not to fight either for or
                    against Austria. Our political interests are all in the East, and in regard to
                    Bonaparte the only thing is to have an armed frontier and a firm policy, and he
                    will never dare to cross the Russian frontier, as was the case in 1807!</q></p>

            <p><q>How can we fight the French, Prince?</q> said Count Rostopchín. <q>Can we arm
                    ourselves against our teachers and divinities? Look at our youths, look at our
                    ladies! The French are our Gods: Paris is our Kingdom of Heaven.</q></p>

            <p>He began speaking louder, evidently to be heard by everyone.</p>

            <p>
                <q>French dresses, French ideas, French feelings! There now, you turned Métivier out
                    by the scruff of his neck because he is a Frenchman and a scoundrel, but our
                    ladies crawl after him on their knees. I went to a party last night, and there
                    out of five ladies three were Roman Catholics and had the Pope’s indulgence for
                    doing woolwork on Sundays. And they themselves sit there nearly naked, like the
                    signboards at our Public Baths if I may say so. Ah, when one looks at our young
                    people, Prince, one would like to take <chara>Peter the Great</chara>’s old cudgel out of the
                    museum and belabor them in the Russian way till all the nonsense jumps out of
                    them.</q>
            </p>

            <p>All were silent. The old prince looked at Rostopchín with a smile and wagged his head
                approvingly.</p>

            <p><q>Well, good-by, your excellency, keep well!</q> said Rostopchín, getting up with
                characteristic briskness and holding out his hand to the prince.</p>

            <p><q>Good-by, my dear fellow.... His words are music, I never tire of hearing him!</q>
                said the old prince, keeping hold of the hand and offering his cheek to be
                kissed.</p>

            <p>Following Rostopchín’s example the others also rose.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER IV </title>
            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> as she sat listening to the old men’s talk and faultfinding, understood
                nothing of what she heard; she only wondered whether the guests had all observed her
                father’s hostile attitude toward her. She did not even notice the special attentions
                and amiabilities shown her during dinner by Borís Drubetskóy, who was visiting them
                for the third time already.</p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> turned with absent-minded questioning look to <chara>Pierre</chara>, who hat in hand
                and with a smile on his face was the last of the guests to approach her after the
                old prince had gone out and they were left alone in the drawing room.</p>

            <p><q>May I stay a little longer?</q> he said, letting his stout body sink into an
                armchair beside her.</p>

            <p><q>Oh yes,</q> she answered. <q>You noticed nothing?</q> her look asked.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> was in an agreeable after-dinner mood. He looked straight before him and
                smiled quietly.</p>

            <p><q>Have you known that young man long, Princess?</q> he asked.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Who?</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>Drubetskóy.</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>No, not long....</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>Do you like him?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Yes, he is an agreeable young man.... Why do you ask me that?</q> said Princess
                <chara>Mary</chara>, still thinking of that morning’s conversation with her father.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Because I have noticed that when a young man comes on leave from Petersburg to
                    Moscow it is usually with the object of marrying an heiress.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>You have observed that?</q> said <chara>Princess Mary</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Yes,</q> returned <chara>Pierre</chara> with a smile, <q>and this young man now manages matters
                    so that where there is a wealthy heiress there he is too. I can read him like a
                    book. At present he is hesitating whom to lay siege to—you or Mademoiselle Julie
                    Karágina. He is very attentive to her.</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>He visits them?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Yes, very often. And do you know the new way of courting?</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara> with an
                amused smile, evidently in that cheerful mood of good humored raillery for which he
                so often reproached himself in his diary.</p>

            <p><q>No,</q> replied <chara>Princess Mary</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>To please Moscow girls nowadays one has to be melancholy. He is very melancholy
                    with Mademoiselle Karágina,</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Really?</q> asked <chara>Princess Mary</chara>, looking into <chara>Pierre</chara>’s kindly face and still
                thinking of her own sorrow. <q>It would be a relief,</q> thought she, <q>if I
                    ventured to confide what I am feeling to someone. I should like to tell
                    everything to <chara>Pierre</chara>. He is kind and generous. It would be a relief. He would
                    give me advice.</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>Would you marry him?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Oh, my God, Count, there are moments when I would marry anybody!</q> she cried
                suddenly to her own surprise and with tears in her voice. <q>Ah, how bitter it is to
                    love someone near to you and to feel that...</q> she went on in a trembling
                voice, <q>that you can do nothing for him but grieve him, and to know that you
                    cannot alter this. Then there is only one thing left—to go away, but where could
                    I go?</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>What is wrong? What is it, Princess?</q>
            </p>

            <p>But without finishing what she was saying, <chara>Princess Mary</chara> burst into tears.</p>

            <p>
                <q>I don’t know what is the matter with me today. Don’t take any notice—forget what
                    I have said!</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara>’s gaiety vanished completely. He anxiously questioned the princess, asked her
                to speak out fully and confide her grief to him; but she only repeated that she
                begged him to forget what she had said, that she did not remember what she had said,
                and that she had no trouble except the one he knew of—that <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>’s marriage
                threatened to cause a rupture between father and son.</p>

            <p><q>Have you any news of the Rostóvs?</q> she asked, to change the subject. <q>I was
                    told they are coming soon. I am also expecting <chara>Andrew</chara> any day. I should like
                    them to meet here.</q></p>

            <p><q>And how does he now regard the matter?</q> asked <chara>Pierre</chara>, referring to the old
                prince.</p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> shook her head.</p>

            <p><q>What is to be done? In a few months the year will be up. The thing is impossible.
                    I only wish I could spare my brother the first moments. I wish they would come
                    sooner. I hope to be friends with her. You have known them a long time,</q> said
                <chara>Princess Mary</chara>. <q>Tell me honestly the whole truth: what sort of girl is she, and
                    what do you think of her?—The real truth, because you know <chara>Andrew</chara> is risking so
                    much doing this against his father’s will that I should like to know....</q></p>

            <p>An undefined instinct told <chara>Pierre</chara> that these explanations, and repeated requests to
                be told the whole truth, expressed ill-will on the princess’ part toward her future
                sister-in-law and a wish that he should disapprove of <chara>Andrew</chara>’s choice; but in reply
                he said what he felt rather than what he thought.</p>

            <p><q>I don’t know how to answer your question,</q> he said, blushing without knowing
                why. <q>I really don’t know what sort of girl she is; I can’t analyze her at all.
                    She is enchanting, but what makes her so I don’t know. That is all one can say
                    about her.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> sighed, and the expression on her face said: <q>Yes, that’s what I
                    expected and feared.</q></p>

            <p><q>Is she clever?</q> she asked.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> considered.</p>

            <p><q>I think not,</q> he said, <q>and yet—yes. She does not deign to be clever.... Oh
                    no, she is simply enchanting, and that is all.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> again shook her head disapprovingly.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Ah, I so long to like her! Tell her so if you see her before I do.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>I hear they are expected very soon,</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> told <chara>Pierre</chara> of her plan to become intimate with her future
                sister-in-law as soon as the Rostóvs arrived and to try to accustom the old prince
                to her.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER V </title>
            <p>Borís had not succeeded in making a wealthy match in Petersburg, so with the same
                object in view he came to Moscow. There he wavered between the two richest
                heiresses, Julie and <chara>Princess Mary. Though Princess Mary</chara> despite her plainness
                seemed to him more attractive than Julie, he, without knowing why, felt awkward
                about paying court to her. When they had last met on the old prince’s name day, she
                had answered at random all his attempts to talk sentimentally, evidently not
                listening to what he was saying.</p>

            <p>Julie on the contrary accepted his attentions readily, though in a manner peculiar to
                herself.</p>

            <p>She was twenty-seven. After the death of her brothers she had become very wealthy.
                She was by now decidedly plain, but thought herself not merely as good-looking as
                before but even far more attractive. She was confirmed in this delusion by the fact
                that she had become a very wealthy heiress and also by the fact that the older she
                grew the less dangerous she became to men, and the more freely they could associate
                with her and avail themselves of her suppers, soirees, and the animated company that
                assembled at her house, without incurring any obligation. A man who would have been
                afraid ten years before of going every day to the house when there was a girl of
                seventeen there, for fear of compromising her and committing himself, would now go
                boldly every day and treat her not as a marriageable girl but as a sexless
                acquaintance.</p>

            <p>That winter the Karágins’ house was the most agreeable and hospitable in Moscow. In
                addition to the formal evening and dinner parties, a large company, chiefly of men,
                gathered there every day, supping at midnight and staying till three in the morning.
                Julie never missed a ball, a promenade, or a play. Her dresses were always of the
                latest fashion. But in spite of that she seemed to be disillusioned about everything
                and told everyone that she did not believe either in friendship or in love, or any
                of the joys of life, and expected peace only <q>yonder.</q> She adopted the tone of
                one who has suffered a great disappointment, like a girl who has either lost the man
                she loved or been cruelly deceived by him. Though nothing of the kind had happened
                to her she was regarded in that light, and had even herself come to believe that she
                had suffered much in life. This melancholy, which did not prevent her amusing
                herself, did not hinder the young people who came to her house from passing the time
                pleasantly. Every visitor who came to the house paid his tribute to the melancholy
                mood of the hostess, and then amused himself with society gossip, dancing,
                intellectual games, and bouts rimés, which were in vogue at the Karágins’. Only a
                few of these young men, among them Borís, entered more deeply into Julie’s
                melancholy, and with these she had prolonged conversations in private on the vanity
                of all worldly things, and to them she showed her albums filled with mournful
                sketches, maxims, and verses.</p>

            <p>To Borís, Julie was particularly gracious: she regretted his early disillusionment
                with life, offered him such consolation of friendship as she who had herself
                suffered so much could render, and showed him her album. Borís sketched two trees in
                the album and wrote: <q>Rustic trees, your dark branches shed gloom and melancholy
                    upon me.</q></p>

            <p>On another page he drew a tomb, and wrote:</p>

            <p>La mort est secourable et la mort est tranquille. Ah! contre les douleurs il n’y a
                pas d’autre asile. *</p>

            <p>* Death gives relief and death is peaceful. Ah! from suffering there is no other
                refuge.</p>

            <p>Julie said this was charming</p>

            <p><q>There is something so enchanting in the smile of melancholy,</q> she said to
                Borís, repeating word for word a passage she had copied from a book. <q>It is a ray
                    of light in the darkness, a shade between sadness and despair, showing the
                    possibility of consolation.</q></p>

            <p>In reply Borís wrote these lines:</p>

            <p>Aliment de poison d’une âme trop sensible, Toi, sans qui le bonheur me serait
                impossible, Tendre mélancholie, ah, viens me consoler, Viens calmer les tourments de
                ma sombre retraite, Et mêle une douceur secrète A ces pleurs que je sens couler.
                *</p>

            <p>*Poisonous nourishment of a too sensitive soul, Thou, without whom happiness would
                for me be impossible, Tender melancholy, ah, come to console me, Come to calm the
                torments of my gloomy retreat, And mingle a secret sweetness With these tears that I
                feel to be flowing.</p>

            <p>For Borís, Julie played most doleful nocturnes on her harp. Borís read Poor Liza
                aloud to her, and more than once interrupted the reading because of the emotions
                that choked him. Meeting at large gatherings Julie and Borís looked on one another
                as the only souls who understood one another in a world of indifferent people.</p>

            <p>Anna Mikháylovna, who often visited the Karágins, while playing cards with the mother
                made careful inquiries as to Julie’s dowry (she was to have two estates in Pénza and
                the Nizhegórod forests). Anna Mikháylovna regarded the refined sadness that united
                her son to the wealthy Julie with emotion, and resignation to the Divine will.</p>

            <p><q>You are always charming and melancholy, my dear Julie,</q> she said to the
                daughter. <q>Borís says his soul finds repose at your house. He has suffered so many
                    disappointments and is so sensitive,</q> said she to the mother. <q>Ah, my dear,
                    I can’t tell you how fond I have grown of Julie latterly,</q> she said to her
                son. <q>But who could help loving her? She is an angelic being! Ah, Borís,
                    Borís!</q>—she paused. <q>And how I pity her mother,</q> she went on; <q>today
                    she showed me her accounts and letters from Pénza (they have enormous estates
                    there), and she, poor thing, has no one to help her, and they do cheat her
                    so!</q></p>

            <p>Borís smiled almost imperceptibly while listening to his mother. He laughed blandly
                at her naïve diplomacy but listened to what she had to say, and sometimes questioned
                her carefully about the Pénza and Nizhegórod estates.</p>

            <p>Julie had long been expecting a proposal from her melancholy adorer and was ready to
                accept it; but some secret feeling of repulsion for her, for her passionate desire
                to get married, for her artificiality, and a feeling of horror at renouncing the
                possibility of real love still restrained Borís. His leave was expiring. He spent
                every day and whole days at the Karágins’, and every day on thinking the matter over
                told himself that he would propose tomorrow. But in Julie’s presence, looking at her
                red face and chin (nearly always powdered), her moist eyes, and her expression of
                continual readiness to pass at once from melancholy to an unnatural rapture of
                married bliss, Borís could not utter the decisive words, though in imagination he
                had long regarded himself as the possessor of those Pénza and Nizhegórod estates and
                had apportioned the use of the income from them. Julie saw Borís’ indecision, and
                sometimes the thought occurred to her that she was repulsive to him, but her
                feminine self-deception immediately supplied her with consolation, and she told
                herself that he was only shy from love. Her melancholy, however, began to turn to
                irritability, and not long before Borís’ departure she formed a definite plan of
                action. Just as Borís’ leave of absence was expiring, <chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara> made his
                appearance in Moscow, and of course in the Karágins’ drawing room, and Julie,
                suddenly abandoning her melancholy, became cheerful and very attentive to
                <chara>Kurágin</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>My dear,</q> said Anna Mikháylovna to her son, <q>I know from a reliable source
                    that Prince Vasíli has sent his son to Moscow to get him married to Julie. I am
                    so fond of Julie that I should be sorry for her. What do you think of it, my
                    dear?</q></p>

            <p>The idea of being made a fool of and of having thrown away that whole month of
                arduous melancholy service to Julie, and of seeing all the revenue from the Pénza
                estates which he had already mentally apportioned and put to proper use fall into
                the hands of another, and especially into the hands of that idiot <chara>Anatole</chara>, pained
                Borís. He drove to the Karágins’ with the firm intention of proposing. Julie met him
                in a gay, careless manner, spoke casually of how she had enjoyed yesterday’s ball,
                and asked when he was leaving. Though Borís had come intentionally to speak of his
                love and therefore meant to be tender, he began speaking irritably of feminine
                inconstancy, of how easily women can turn from sadness to joy, and how their moods
                depend solely on who happens to be paying court to them. Julie was offended and
                replied that it was true that a woman needs variety, and the same thing over and
                over again would weary anyone.</p>

            <p><q>Then I should advise you...</q> Borís began, wishing to sting her; but at that
                instant the galling thought occurred to him that he might have to leave Moscow
                without having accomplished his aim, and have vainly wasted his efforts—which was a
                thing he never allowed to happen.</p>

            <p>He checked himself in the middle of the sentence, lowered his eyes to avoid seeing
                her unpleasantly irritated and irresolute face, and said:</p>

            <p>
                <q>I did not come here at all to quarrel with you. On the contrary...</q>
            </p>

            <p>He glanced at her to make sure that he might go on. Her irritability had suddenly
                quite vanished, and her anxious, imploring eyes were fixed on him with greedy
                expectation. <q>I can always arrange so as not to see her often,</q> thought Borís.
                    <q>The affair has been begun and must be finished!</q> He blushed hotly, raised
                his eyes to hers, and said:</p>

            <p>
                <q>You know my feelings for you!</q>
            </p>

            <p>There was no need to say more: Julie’s face shone with triumph and self-satisfaction;
                but she forced Borís to say all that is said on such occasions—that he loved her and
                had never loved any other woman more than her. She knew that for the Pénza estates
                and Nizhegórod forests she could demand this, and she received what she
                demanded.</p>

            <p>The affianced couple, no longer alluding to trees that shed gloom and melancholy upon
                them, planned the arrangements of a splendid house in Petersburg, paid calls, and
                prepared everything for a brilliant wedding.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER VI </title>
            <p>At the end of January old <chara>Count Rostóv</chara> went to Moscow with <chara>Natásha</chara> and <chara>Sónya</chara>. The
                countess was still unwell and unable to travel but it was impossible to wait for her
                recovery. <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> was expected in Moscow any day, the trousseau had to be
                ordered and the estate near Moscow had to be sold, besides which the opportunity of
                presenting his future daughter-in-law to old Prince Bolkónski while he was in Moscow
                could not be missed. The Rostóvs’ Moscow house had not been heated that winter and,
                as they had come only for a short time and the countess was not with them, the count
                decided to stay with <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> Akhrosímova, who had long been pressing her
                hospitality on them.</p>

            <p>Late one evening the Rostóvs’ four sleighs drove into <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s courtyard in
                the old Konyúsheny street. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> lived alone. She had already married off
                her daughter, and her sons were all in the service.</p>

            <p>She held herself as erect, told everyone her opinion as candidly, loudly, and bluntly
                as ever, and her whole bearing seemed a reproach to others for any weakness,
                passion, or temptation—the possibility of which she did not admit. From early in the
                morning, wearing a dressing jacket, she attended to her household affairs, and then
                she drove out: on holy days to church and after the service to jails and prisons on
                affairs of which she never spoke to anyone. On ordinary days, after dressing, she
                received petitioners of various classes, of whom there were always some. Then she
                had dinner, a substantial and appetizing meal at which there were always three or
                four guests; after dinner she played a game of boston, and at night she had the
                newspapers or a new book read to her while she knitted. She rarely made an exception
                and went out to pay visits, and then only to the most important persons in the
                town.</p>

            <p>She had not yet gone to bed when the Rostóvs arrived and the pulley of the hall door
                squeaked from the cold as it let in the Rostóvs and their servants. <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                Dmítrievna, with her spectacles hanging down on her nose and her head flung back,
                stood in the hall doorway looking with a stern, grim face at the new arrivals. One
                might have thought she was angry with the travelers and would immediately turn them
                out, had she not at the same time been giving careful instructions to the servants
                for the accommodation of the visitors and their belongings.</p>

            <p><q>The count’s things? Bring them here,</q> she said, pointing to the portmanteaus
                and not greeting anyone. <q>The young ladies’? There to the left. Now what are you
                    dawdling for?</q> she cried to the maids. <q>Get the samovar ready!... You’ve
                    grown plumper and prettier,</q> she remarked, drawing <chara>Natásha</chara> (whose cheeks were
                glowing from the cold) to her by the hood. <q>Foo! You are cold! Now take off your
                    things, quick!</q> she shouted to the count who was going to kiss her hand.
                    <q>You’re half frozen, I’m sure! Bring some rum for tea!... Bonjour, <chara>Sónya</chara>
                    dear!</q> she added, turning to <chara>Sónya</chara> and indicating by this French greeting her
                slightly contemptuous though affectionate attitude toward her.</p>

            <p>When they came in to tea, having taken off their outdoor things and tidied themselves
                up after their journey, <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> kissed them all in due order.</p>

            <p><q>I’m heartily glad you have come and are staying with me. It was high time,</q> she
                said, giving <chara>Natásha</chara> a significant look. <q>The old man is here and his son’s
                    expected any day. You’ll have to make his acquaintance. But we’ll speak of that
                    later on,</q> she added, glancing at <chara>Sónya</chara> with a look that showed she did not
                want to speak of it in her presence. <q>Now listen,</q> she said to the count.
                    <q>What do you want tomorrow? Whom will you send for? Shinshín?</q> she crooked
                one of her fingers. <q>The sniveling Anna Mikháylovna? That’s two. She’s here with
                    her son. The son is getting married! Then Bezúkhov, eh? He is here too, with his
                    wife. He ran away from her and she came galloping after him. He dined with me on
                    Wednesday. As for them</q>—and she pointed to the girls—<q>tomorrow I’ll take
                    them first to the Iberian shrine of the Mother of God, and then we’ll drive to
                    the Super-Rogue’s. I suppose you’ll have everything new. Don’t judge by me:
                    sleeves nowadays are this size! The other day young Princess Irína Vasílevna
                    came to see me; she was an awful sight—looked as if she had put two barrels on
                    her arms. You know not a day passes now without some new fashion.... And what
                    have you to do yourself?</q> she asked the count sternly.</p>

            <p>
                <q>One thing has come on top of another: her rags to buy, and now a purchaser has
                    turned up for the Moscow estate and for the house. If you will be so kind, I’ll
                    fix a time and go down to the estate just for a day, and leave my lassies with
                    you.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>All right. All right. They’ll be safe with me, as safe as in Chancery! I’ll take
                    them where they must go, scold them a bit, and pet them a bit,</q> said <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                Dmítrievna, touching her goddaughter and favorite, <chara>Natásha</chara>, on the cheek with her
                large hand.</p>

            <p>Next morning <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> took the young ladies to the Iberian shrine of the
                Mother of God and to Madame Suppert-Roguet, who was so afraid of <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>
                that she always let her have costumes at a loss merely to get rid of her. <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                Dmítrievna ordered almost the whole trousseau. When they got home she turned
                everybody out of the room except <chara>Natásha</chara>, and then called her pet to her
                armchair.</p>

            <p><q>Well, now we’ll talk. I congratulate you on your betrothed. You’ve hooked a fine
                    fellow! I am glad for your sake and I’ve known him since he was so high.</q> She
                held her hand a couple of feet from the ground. <chara>Natásha</chara> blushed happily. <q>I like
                    him and all his family. Now listen! You know that old <chara>Prince Nicholas</chara> much
                    dislikes his son’s marrying. The old fellow’s crotchety! Of course <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>
                    is not a child and can shift without him, but it’s not nice to enter a family
                    against a father’s will. One wants to do it peacefully and lovingly. You’re a
                    clever girl and you’ll know how to manage. Be kind, and use your wits. Then all
                    will be well.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> remained silent, from shyness <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> supposed, but really because
                she disliked anyone interfering in what touched her love of <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, which
                seemed to her so apart from all human affairs that no one could understand it. She
                loved and knew <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, he loved her only, and was to come one of these days
                and take her. She wanted nothing more.</p>

            <p>
                <q>You see I have known him a long time and am also fond of <chara>Mary</chara>, your future
                    sister-in-law. <q2>Husbands</q2> sisters bring up blisters,’ but this one
                    wouldn’t hurt a fly. She has asked me to bring you two together. Tomorrow you’ll
                    go with your father to see her. Be very nice and affectionate to her: you’re
                    younger than she. When he comes, he’ll find you already know his sister and
                    father and are liked by them. Am I right or not? Won’t that be best?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Yes, it will,</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> answered reluctantly.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER VII </title>
            <p>Next day, by <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s advice, <chara>Count Rostóv</chara> took <chara>Natásha</chara> to call on Prince
                Nicholas Bolkónski. The count did not set out cheerfully on this visit, at heart he
                felt afraid. He well remembered the last interview he had had with the old prince at
                the time of the enrollment, when in reply to an invitation to dinner he had had to
                listen to an angry reprimand for not having provided his full quota of men. <chara>Natásha</chara>,
                on the other hand, having put on her best gown, was in the highest spirits. <q>They
                    can’t help liking me,</q> she thought. <q>Everybody always has liked me, and I
                    am so willing to do anything they wish, so ready to be fond of him—for being his
                    father—and of her—for being his sister—that there is no reason for them not to
                    like me....</q></p>

            <p>They drove up to the gloomy old house on the Vozdvízhenka and entered the
                vestibule.</p>

            <p><q>Well, the Lord have mercy on us!</q> said the count, half in jest, half in
                earnest; but <chara>Natásha</chara> noticed that her father was flurried on entering the anteroom
                and inquired timidly and softly whether the prince and princess were at home.</p>

            <p>When they had been announced a perturbation was noticeable among the servants. The
                footman who had gone to announce them was stopped by another in the large hall and
                they whispered to one another. Then a maidservant ran into the hall and hurriedly
                said something, mentioning the princess. At last an old, cross looking footman came
                and announced to the Rostóvs that the prince was not receiving, but that the
                princess begged them to walk up. The first person who came to meet the visitors was
                Mademoiselle Bourienne. She greeted the father and daughter with special politeness
                and showed them to the princess’ room. The princess, looking excited and nervous,
                her face flushed in patches, ran in to meet the visitors, treading heavily, and
                vainly trying to appear cordial and at ease. From the first glance <chara>Princess Mary</chara> did
                not like <chara>Natásha</chara>. She thought her too fashionably dressed, frivolously gay and vain.
                She did not at all realize that before having seen her future sister-in-law she was
                prejudiced against her by involuntary envy of her beauty, youth, and happiness, as
                well as by jealousy of her brother’s love for her. Apart from this insuperable
                antipathy to her, <chara>Princess Mary</chara> was agitated just then because on the Rostóvs’ being
                announced, the old prince had shouted that he did not wish to see them, that
                <chara>Princess Mary</chara> might do so if she chose, but they were not to be admitted to him. She
                had decided to receive them, but feared lest the prince might at any moment indulge
                in some freak, as he seemed much upset by the Rostóvs’ visit.</p>

            <p><q>There, my dear princess, I’ve brought you my songstress,</q> said the count,
                bowing and looking round uneasily as if afraid the old prince might appear. <q>I am
                    so glad you should get to know one another... very sorry the prince is still
                    ailing,</q> and after a few more commonplace remarks he rose. <q>If you’ll allow
                    me to leave my <chara>Natásha</chara> in your hands for a quarter of an hour, Princess, I’ll
                    drive round to see Anna Semënovna, it’s quite near in the Dogs’ Square, and then
                    I’ll come back for her.</q></p>

            <p>The count had devised this diplomatic ruse (as he afterwards told his daughter) to
                give the future sisters-in-law an opportunity to talk to one another freely, but
                another motive was to avoid the danger of encountering the old prince, of whom he
                was afraid. He did not mention this to his daughter, but <chara>Natásha</chara> noticed her
                father’s nervousness and anxiety and felt mortified by it. She blushed for him, grew
                still angrier at having blushed, and looked at the princess with a bold and defiant
                expression which said that she was not afraid of anybody. The princess told the
                count that she would be delighted, and only begged him to stay longer at Anna
                Semënovna’s, and he departed.</p>

            <p>Despite the uneasy glances thrown at her by <chara>Princess Mary</chara>—who wished to have a
                tête-à-tête with <chara>Natásha</chara>—Mademoiselle Bourienne remained in the room and
                persistently talked about Moscow amusements and theaters. <chara>Natásha</chara> felt offended by
                the hesitation she had noticed in the anteroom, by her father’s nervousness, and by
                the unnatural manner of the princess who—she thought—was making a favor of receiving
                her, and so everything displeased her. She did not like <chara>Princess Mary</chara>, whom she
                thought very plain, affected, and dry. <chara>Natásha</chara> suddenly shrank into herself and
                involuntarily assumed an offhand air which alienated <chara>Princess Mary</chara> still more. After
                five minutes of irksome, constrained conversation, they heard the sound of slippered
                feet rapidly approaching. <chara>Princess Mary</chara> looked frightened.</p>

            <p>The door opened and the old prince, in a dressing gown and a white nightcap, came
                in.</p>

            <p><q>Ah, madam!</q> he began. <q>Madam, Countess... <chara>Countess Rostóva</chara>, if I am not
                    mistaken... I beg you to excuse me, to excuse me... I did not know, madam. God
                    is my witness, I did not know you had honored us with a visit, and I came in
                    such a costume only to see my daughter. I beg you to excuse me... God is my
                    witness, I didn’t know—</q> he repeated, stressing the word <q>God</q> so
                unnaturally and so unpleasantly that <chara>Princess Mary</chara> stood with downcast eyes not
                daring to look either at her father or at <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p>Nor did the latter, having risen and curtsied, know what to do. Mademoiselle
                Bourienne alone smiled agreeably.</p>

            <p><q>I beg you to excuse me, excuse me! God is my witness, I did not know,</q> muttered
                the old man, and after looking <chara>Natásha</chara> over from head to foot he went out.</p>

            <p>Mademoiselle Bourienne was the first to recover herself after this apparition and
                began speaking about the prince’s indisposition. <chara>Natásha</chara> and <chara>Princess Mary</chara> looked at
                one another in silence, and the longer they did so without saying what they wanted
                to say, the greater grew their antipathy to one another.</p>

            <p>When the count returned, <chara>Natásha</chara> was impolitely pleased and hastened to get away: at
                that moment she hated the stiff, elderly princess, who could place her in such an
                embarrassing position and had spent half an hour with her without once mentioning
                <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>. <q>I couldn’t begin talking about him in the presence of that
                    Frenchwoman,</q> thought <chara>Natásha</chara>. The same thought was meanwhile tormenting
                <chara>Princess Mary</chara>. She knew what she ought to have said to <chara>Natásha</chara>, but she had been
                unable to say it because Mademoiselle Bourienne was in the way, and because, without
                knowing why, she felt it very difficult to speak of the marriage. When the count was
                already leaving the room, <chara>Princess Mary</chara> went up hurriedly to <chara>Natásha</chara>, took her by
                the hand, and said with a deep sigh:</p>

            <p>
                <q>Wait, I must...</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> glanced at her ironically without knowing why.</p>

            <p><q>Dear <chara>Natalie</chara>,</q> said <chara>Princess Mary</chara>, <q>I want you to know that I am glad my
                    brother has found happiness....</q></p>

            <p>She paused, feeling that she was not telling the truth. <chara>Natásha</chara> noticed this and
                guessed its reason.</p>

            <p><q>I think, Princess, it is not convenient to speak of that now,</q> she said with
                external dignity and coldness, though she felt the tears choking her.</p>

            <p><q>What have I said and what have I done?</q> thought she, as soon as she was out of
                the room.</p>

            <p>They waited a long time for <chara>Natásha</chara> to come to dinner that day. She sat in her room
                crying like a child, blowing her nose and sobbing. <chara>Sónya</chara> stood beside her, kissing
                her hair.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natásha</chara>, what is it about?</q> she asked. <q>What do they matter to you? It will
                    all pass, <chara>Natásha</chara>.</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>But if you only knew how offensive it was... as if I...</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Don’t talk about it, <chara>Natásha</chara>. It wasn’t your fault so why should you mind? Kiss
                    me,</q> said <chara>Sónya</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> raised her head and, kissing her friend on the lips, pressed her wet face
                against her.</p>

            <p><q>I can’t tell you, I don’t know. No one’s to blame,</q> said <chara>Natásha</chara>—<q>It’s my
                    fault. But it all hurts terribly. Oh, why doesn’t he come?...</q></p>

            <p>She came in to dinner with red eyes. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>, who knew how the prince had
                received the Rostóvs, pretended not to notice how upset <chara>Natásha</chara> was and jested
                resolutely and loudly at table with the count and the other guests.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER VIII </title>
            <p>That evening the Rostóvs went to the Opera, for which <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> had taken a
                box.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> did not want to go, but could not refuse <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s kind offer which
                was intended expressly for her. When she came ready dressed into the ballroom to
                await her father, and looking in the large mirror there saw that she was pretty,
                very pretty, she felt even more sad, but it was a sweet, tender sadness.</p>

            <p><q>O God, if he were here now I would not behave as I did then, but differently. I
                    would not be silly and afraid of things, I would simply embrace him, cling to
                    him, and make him look at me with those searching inquiring eyes with which he
                    has so often looked at me, and then I would make him laugh as he used to laugh.
                    And his eyes—how I see those eyes!</q> thought <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>And what do his
                    father and sister matter to me? I love him alone, him, him, with that face and
                    those eyes, with his smile, manly and yet childlike.... No, I had better not
                    think of him; not think of him but forget him, quite forget him for the present.
                    I can’t bear this waiting and I shall cry in a minute!</q> and she turned away
                from the glass, making an effort not to cry. <q>And how can <chara>Sónya</chara> love Nicholas so
                    calmly and quietly and wait so long and so patiently?</q> thought she, looking
                at <chara>Sónya</chara>, who also came in quite ready, with a fan in her hand. <q>No, she’s
                    altogether different. I can’t!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> at that moment felt so softened and tender that it was not enough for her to
                love and know she was beloved, she wanted now, at once, to embrace the man she
                loved, to speak and hear from him words of love such as filled her heart. While she
                sat in the carriage beside her father, pensively watching the lights of the street
                lamps flickering on the frozen window, she felt still sadder and more in love, and
                forgot where she was going and with whom. Having fallen into the line of carriages,
                the Rostóvs’ carriage drove up to the theater, its wheels squeaking over the snow.
                <chara>Natásha</chara> and <chara>Sónya</chara>, holding up their dresses, jumped out quickly. The count got out
                helped by the footmen, and, passing among men and women who were entering and the
                program sellers, they all three went along the corridor to the first row of boxes.
                Through the closed doors the music was already audible.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natásha</chara>, your hair!...</q> whispered <chara>Sónya</chara>.</p>

            <p>An attendant deferentially and quickly slipped before the ladies and opened the door
                of their box. The music sounded louder and through the door rows of brightly lit
                boxes in which ladies sat with bare arms and shoulders, and noisy stalls brilliant
                with uniforms, glittered before their eyes. A lady entering the next box shot a
                glance of feminine envy at <chara>Natásha</chara>. The curtain had not yet risen and the overture
                was being played. <chara>Natásha</chara>, smoothing her gown, went in with <chara>Sónya</chara> and sat down,
                scanning the brilliant tiers of boxes opposite. A sensation she had not experienced
                for a long time—that of hundreds of eyes looking at her bare arms and neck—suddenly
                affected her both agreeably and disagreeably and called up a whole crowd of
                memories, desires and emotions associated with that feeling.</p>

            <p>The two remarkably pretty girls, <chara>Natásha</chara> and <chara>Sónya</chara>, with <chara>Count Rostóv</chara> who had not
                been seen in Moscow for a long time, attracted general attention. Moreover,
                everybody knew vaguely of <chara>Natásha</chara>’s engagement to <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, and knew that the
                Rostóvs had lived in the country ever since, and all looked with curiosity at a
                fiancée who was making one of the best matches in Russia.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara>’s looks, as everyone told her, had improved in the country, and that evening
                thanks to her agitation she was particularly pretty. She struck those who saw her by
                her fullness of life and beauty, combined with her indifference to everything about
                her. Her black eyes looked at the crowd without seeking anyone, and her delicate
                arm, bare to above the elbow, lay on the velvet edge of the box, while, evidently
                unconsciously, she opened and closed her hand in time to the music, crumpling her
                program. <q>Look, there’s Alénina,</q> said <chara>Sónya</chara>, <q>with her mother, isn’t
                it?</q></p>

            <p><q>Dear me, Michael Kirílovich has grown still stouter!</q> remarked the count.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Look at our Anna Mikháylovna—what a headdress she has on!</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>The Karágins, Julie—and Borís with them. One can see at once that they’re
                    engaged....</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>Drubetskóy has proposed?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Oh yes, I heard it today,</q> said Shinshín, coming into the Rostóvs’ box.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> looked in the direction in which her father’s eyes were turned and saw Julie
                sitting beside her mother with a happy look on her face and a string of pearls round
                her thick red neck—which <chara>Natásha</chara> knew was covered with powder. Behind them, wearing
                a smile and leaning over with an ear to Julie’s mouth, was Borís’ handsome smoothly
                brushed head. He looked at the Rostóvs from under his brows and said something,
                smiling, to his betrothed.</p>

            <p><q>They are talking about us, about me and him!</q> thought <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>And he no
                    doubt is calming her jealousy of me. They needn’t trouble themselves! If only
                    they knew how little I am concerned about any of them.</q></p>

            <p>Behind them sat Anna Mikháylovna wearing a green headdress and with a happy look of
                resignation to the will of God on her face. Their box was pervaded by that
                atmosphere of an affianced couple which <chara>Natásha</chara> knew so well and liked so much. She
                turned away and suddenly remembered all that had been so humiliating in her
                morning’s visit.</p>

            <p><q>What right has he not to wish to receive me into his family? Oh, better not think
                    of it—not till he comes back!</q> she told herself, and began looking at the
                faces, some strange and some familiar, in the stalls. In the front, in the very
                center, leaning back against the orchestra rail, stood <chara>Dólokhov</chara> in a Persian dress,
                his curly hair brushed up into a huge shock. He stood in full view of the audience,
                well aware that he was attracting everyone’s attention, yet as much at ease as
                though he were in his own room. Around him thronged Moscow’s most brilliant young
                men, whom he evidently dominated.</p>

            <p>The count, laughing, nudged the blushing <chara>Sónya</chara> and pointed to her former adorer.</p>

            <p><q>Do you recognize him?</q> said he. <q>And where has he sprung from?</q> he asked,
                turning to Shinshín. <q>Didn’t he vanish somewhere?</q></p>

            <p><q>He did,</q> replied Shinshín. <q>He was in the Caucasus and ran away from there.
                    They say he has been acting as minister to some ruling prince in Persia, where
                    he killed the Shah’s brother. Now all the Moscow ladies are mad about him! It’s
                        <q2><chara>Dólokhov the Persian</chara></q2> that does it! We never hear a word but
                    <chara>Dólokhov</chara> is mentioned. They swear by him, they offer him to you as they would a
                    dish of choice sterlet. <chara>Dólokhov</chara> and <chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara> have turned all our ladies’
                    heads.</q></p>

            <p>A tall, beautiful woman with a mass of plaited hair and much exposed plump white
                shoulders and neck, round which she wore a double string of large pearls, entered
                the adjoining box rustling her heavy silk dress and took a long time settling into
                her place.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> involuntarily gazed at that neck, those shoulders, and pearls and coiffure,
                and admired the beauty of the shoulders and the pearls. While <chara>Natásha</chara> was fixing her
                gaze on her for the second time the lady looked round and, meeting the count’s eyes,
                nodded to him and smiled. She was the <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara>, <chara>Pierre</chara>’s wife, and the
                count, who knew everyone in society, leaned over and spoke to her.</p>

            <p><q>Have you been here long, Countess?</q> he inquired. <q>I’ll call, I’ll call to
                    kiss your hand. I’m here on business and have brought my girls with me. They say
                    Semënova acts marvelously. Count <chara>Pierre</chara> never used to forget us. Is he
                here?</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes, he meant to look in,</q> answered <chara>Hélène</chara>, and glanced attentively at
                <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Count Rostóv</chara> resumed his seat.</p>

            <p><q>Handsome, isn’t she?</q> he whispered to <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Wonderful!</q> answered <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>She’s a woman one could easily fall in love
                    with.</q></p>

            <p>Just then the last chords of the overture were heard and the conductor tapped with
                his stick. Some latecomers took their seats in the stalls, and the curtain rose.</p>

            <p>As soon as it rose everyone in the boxes and stalls became silent, and all the men,
                old and young, in uniform and evening dress, and all the women with gems on their
                bare flesh, turned their whole attention with eager curiosity to the stage. <chara>Natásha</chara>
                too began to look at it.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER IX </title>
            <p>The floor of the stage consisted of smooth boards, at the sides was some painted
                cardboard representing trees, and at the back was a cloth stretched over boards. In
                the center of the stage sat some girls in red bodices and white skirts. One very fat
                girl in a white silk dress sat apart on a low bench, to the back of which a piece of
                green cardboard was glued. They all sang something. When they had finished their
                song the girl in white went up to the prompter’s box and a man with tight silk
                trousers over his stout legs, and holding a plume and a dagger, went up to her and
                began singing, waving his arms about.</p>

            <p>First the man in the tight trousers sang alone, then she sang, then they both paused
                while the orchestra played and the man fingered the hand of the girl in white,
                obviously awaiting the beat to start singing with her. They sang together and
                everyone in the theater began clapping and shouting, while the man and woman on the
                stage—who represented lovers—began smiling, spreading out their arms, and
                bowing.</p>

            <p>After her life in the country, and in her present serious mood, all this seemed
                grotesque and amazing to <chara>Natásha</chara>. She could not follow the opera nor even listen to
                the music; she saw only the painted cardboard and the queerly dressed men and women
                who moved, spoke, and sang so strangely in that brilliant light. She knew what it
                was all meant to represent, but it was so pretentiously false and unnatural that she
                first felt ashamed for the actors and then amused at them. She looked at the faces
                of the audience, seeking in them the same sense of ridicule and perplexity she
                herself experienced, but they all seemed attentive to what was happening on the
                stage, and expressed delight which to <chara>Natásha</chara> seemed feigned. <q>I suppose it has to
                    be like this!</q> she thought. She kept looking round in turn at the rows of
                pomaded heads in the stalls and then at the seminude women in the boxes, especially
                at <chara>Hélène</chara> in the next box, who—apparently quite unclothed—sat with a quiet tranquil
                smile, not taking her eyes off the stage. And feeling the bright light that flooded
                the whole place and the warm air heated by the crowd, <chara>Natásha</chara> little by little began
                to pass into a state of intoxication she had not experienced for a long while. She
                did not realize who and where she was, nor what was going on before her. As she
                looked and thought, the strangest fancies unexpectedly and disconnectedly passed
                through her mind: the idea occurred to her of jumping onto the edge of the box and
                singing the aria the actress was singing, then she wished to touch with her fan an
                old gentleman sitting not far from her, then to lean over to <chara>Hélène</chara> and tickle
                her.</p>

            <p>At a moment when all was quiet before the commencement of a song, a door leading to
                the stalls on the side nearest the Rostóvs’ box creaked, and the steps of a belated
                arrival were heard. <q>There’s <chara>Kurágin</chara>!</q> whispered Shinshín. <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara>
                turned smiling to the newcomer, and <chara>Natásha</chara>, following the direction of that look,
                saw an exceptionally handsome adjutant approaching their box with a self-assured yet
                courteous bearing. This was <chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara> whom she had seen and noticed long ago
                at the ball in Petersburg. He was now in an adjutant’s uniform with one epaulet and
                a shoulder knot. He moved with a restrained swagger which would have been ridiculous
                had he not been so good-looking and had his handsome face not worn such an
                expression of good-humored complacency and gaiety. Though the performance was
                proceeding, he walked deliberately down the carpeted gangway, his sword and spurs
                slightly jingling and his handsome perfumed head held high. Having looked at <chara>Natásha</chara>
                he approached his sister, laid his well gloved hand on the edge of her box, nodded
                to her, and leaning forward asked a question, with a motion toward <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Mais charmante!</q> said he, evidently referring to <chara>Natásha</chara>, who did not exactly
                hear his words but understood them from the movement of his lips. Then he took his
                place in the first row of the stalls and sat down beside <chara>Dólokhov</chara>, nudging with his
                elbow in a friendly and offhand way that <chara>Dólokhov</chara> whom others treated so fawningly.
                He winked at him gaily, smiled, and rested his foot against the orchestra
                screen.</p>

            <p><q>How like the brother is to the sister,</q> remarked the count. <q>And how handsome
                    they both are!</q></p>

            <p>Shinshín, lowering his voice, began to tell the count of some intrigue of <chara>Kurágin</chara>’s
                in Moscow, and <chara>Natásha</chara> tried to overhear it just because he had said she was
                    <q>charmante.</q></p>

            <p>The first act was over. In the stalls everyone began moving about, going out and
                coming in.</p>

            <p>Borís came to the Rostóvs’ box, received their congratulations very simply, and
                raising his eyebrows with an absent-minded smile conveyed to <chara>Natásha</chara> and <chara>Sónya</chara> his
                fiancée’s invitation to her wedding, and went away. <chara>Natásha</chara> with a gay, coquettish
                smile talked to him, and congratulated on his approaching wedding that same Borís
                with whom she had formerly been in love. In the state of intoxication she was in,
                everything seemed simple and natural.</p>

            <p>The scantily clad <chara>Hélène</chara> smiled at everyone in the same way, and <chara>Natásha</chara> gave Borís a
                similar smile.</p>

            <p><chara>Hélène</chara>’s box was filled and surrounded from the stalls by the most distinguished and
                intellectual men, who seemed to vie with one another in their wish to let everyone
                see that they knew her.</p>

            <p>During the whole of that entr’acte <chara>Kurágin</chara> stood with <chara>Dólokhov</chara> in front of the
                orchestra partition, looking at the Rostóvs’ box. <chara>Natásha</chara> knew he was talking about
                her and this afforded her pleasure. She even turned so that he should see her
                profile in what she thought was its most becoming aspect. Before the beginning of
                the second act <chara>Pierre</chara> appeared in the stalls. The Rostóvs had not seen him since
                their arrival. His face looked sad, and he had grown still stouter since <chara>Natásha</chara>
                last saw him. He passed up to the front rows, not noticing anyone. <chara>Anatole</chara> went up
                to him and began speaking to him, looking at and indicating the Rostóvs’ box. On
                seeing <chara>Natásha</chara> <chara>Pierre</chara> grew animated and, hastily passing between the rows, came
                toward their box. When he got there he leaned on his elbows and, smiling, talked to
                her for a long time. While conversing with <chara>Pierre</chara>, <chara>Natásha</chara> heard a man’s voice in
                <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara>’s box and something told her it was <chara>Kurágin</chara>. She turned and their
                eyes met. Almost smiling, he gazed straight into her eyes with such an enraptured
                caressing look that it seemed strange to be so near him, to look at him like that,
                to be so sure he admired her, and not to be acquainted with him.</p>

            <p>In the second act there was scenery representing tombstones, there was a round hole
                in the canvas to represent the moon, shades were raised over the footlights, and
                from horns and contrabass came deep notes while many people appeared from right and
                left wearing black cloaks and holding things like daggers in their hands. They began
                waving their arms. Then some other people ran in and began dragging away the maiden
                who had been in white and was now in light blue. They did not drag her away at once,
                but sang with her for a long time and then at last dragged her off, and behind the
                scenes something metallic was struck three times and everyone knelt down and sang a
                prayer. All these things were repeatedly interrupted by the enthusiastic shouts of
                the audience.</p>

            <p>During this act every time <chara>Natásha</chara> looked toward the stalls she saw <chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara>
                with an arm thrown across the back of his chair, staring at her. She was pleased to
                see that he was captivated by her and it did not occur to her that there was
                anything wrong in it.</p>

            <p>When the second act was over <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara> rose, turned to the Rostóvs’ box—her
                whole bosom completely exposed—beckoned the old count with a gloved finger, and
                paying no attention to those who had entered her box began talking to him with an
                amiable smile.</p>

            <p><q>Do make me acquainted with your charming daughters,</q> said she. <q>The whole
                    town is singing their praises and I don’t even know them!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> rose and curtsied to the splendid countess. She was so pleased by praise from
                this brilliant beauty that she blushed with pleasure.</p>

            <p><q>I want to become a Moscovite too, now,</q> said <chara>Hélène</chara>. <q>How is it you’re not
                    ashamed to bury such pearls in the country?</q></p>

            <p><chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara> quite deserved her reputation of being a fascinating woman. She
                could say what she did not think—especially what was flattering—quite simply and
                naturally.</p>

            <p><q>Dear count, you must let me look after your daughters! Though I am not staying
                    here long this time—nor are you—I will try to amuse them. I have already heard
                    much of you in Petersburg and wanted to get to know you,</q> said she to <chara>Natásha</chara>
                with her stereotyped and lovely smile. <q>I had heard about you from my page,
                    Drubetskóy. Have you heard he is getting married? And also from my husband’s
                    friend Bolkónski, <chara>Prince Andrew Bolkónski</chara>,</q> she went on with special
                emphasis, implying that she knew of his relation to <chara>Natásha</chara>. To get better
                acquainted she asked that one of the young ladies should come into her box for the
                rest of the performance, and <chara>Natásha</chara> moved over to it.</p>

            <p>The scene of the third act represented a palace in which many candles were burning
                and pictures of knights with short beards hung on the walls. In the middle stood
                what were probably a king and a queen. The king waved his right arm and, evidently
                nervous, sang something badly and sat down on a crimson throne. The maiden who had
                been first in white and then in light blue, now wore only a smock, and stood beside
                the throne with her hair down. She sang something mournfully, addressing the queen,
                but the king waved his arm severely, and men and women with bare legs came in from
                both sides and began dancing all together. Then the violins played very shrilly and
                merrily and one of the women with thick bare legs and thin arms, separating from the
                others, went behind the wings, adjusted her bodice, returned to the middle of the
                stage, and began jumping and striking one foot rapidly against the other. In the
                stalls everyone clapped and shouted <q>bravo!</q> Then one of the men went into a
                corner of the stage. The cymbals and horns in the orchestra struck up more loudly,
                and this man with bare legs jumped very high and waved his feet about very rapidly.
                (He was Duport, who received sixty thousand rubles a year for this art.) Everybody
                in the stalls, boxes, and galleries began clapping and shouting with all their
                might, and the man stopped and began smiling and bowing to all sides. Then other men
                and women danced with bare legs. Then the king again shouted to the sound of music,
                and they all began singing. But suddenly a storm came on, chromatic scales and
                diminished sevenths were heard in the orchestra, everyone ran off, again dragging
                one of their number away, and the curtain dropped. Once more there was a terrible
                noise and clatter among the audience, and with rapturous faces everyone began
                shouting: <q>Duport! Duport! Duport!</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> no longer thought this strange. She
                looked about with pleasure, smiling joyfully.</p>

            <p><q>Isn’t Duport delightful?</q> <chara>Hélène</chara> asked her.</p>

            <p><q>Oh, yes,</q> replied <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER X </title>
            <p>During the entr’acte a whiff of cold air came into <chara>Hélène</chara>’s box, the door opened, and
                <chara>Anatole</chara> entered, stooping and trying not to brush against anyone.</p>

            <p><q>Let me introduce my brother to you,</q> said <chara>Hélène</chara>, her eyes shifting uneasily
                from <chara>Natásha</chara> to <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> turned her pretty little head toward the elegant young officer and smiled at
                him over her bare shoulder. <chara>Anatole</chara>, who was as handsome at close quarters as at a
                distance, sat down beside her and told her he had long wished to have this
                happiness—ever since the Narýshkins’ ball in fact, at which he had had the
                well-remembered pleasure of seeing her. <chara>Kurágin</chara> was much more sensible and simple
                with women than among men. He talked boldly and naturally, and <chara>Natásha</chara> was strangely
                and agreeably struck by the fact that there was nothing formidable in this man about
                whom there was so much talk, but that on the contrary his smile was most naïve,
                cheerful, and good-natured.</p>

            <p><chara>Kurágin</chara> asked her opinion of the performance and told her how at a previous
                performance Semënova had fallen down on the stage.</p>

            <p><q>And do you know, Countess,</q> he said, suddenly addressing her as an old,
                familiar acquaintance, <q>we are getting up a costume tournament; you ought to take
                    part in it! It will be great fun. We shall all meet at the Karágins’! Please
                    come! No! Really, eh?</q> said he.</p>

            <p>While saying this he never removed his smiling eyes from her face, her neck, and her
                bare arms. <chara>Natásha</chara> knew for certain that he was enraptured by her. This pleased her,
                yet his presence made her feel constrained and oppressed. When she was not looking
                at him she felt that he was looking at her shoulders, and she involuntarily caught
                his eye so that he should look into hers rather than this. But looking into his eyes
                she was frightened, realizing that there was not that barrier of modesty she had
                always felt between herself and other men. She did not know how it was that within
                five minutes she had come to feel herself terribly near to this man. When she turned
                away she feared he might seize her from behind by her bare arm and kiss her on the
                neck. They spoke of most ordinary things, yet she felt that they were closer to one
                another than she had ever been to any man. <chara>Natásha</chara> kept turning to <chara>Hélène</chara> and to her
                father, as if asking what it all meant, but <chara>Hélène</chara> was engaged in conversation with
                a general and did not answer her look, and her father’s eyes said nothing but what
                they always said: <q>Having a good time? Well, I’m glad of it!</q></p>

            <p>During one of these moments of awkward silence when <chara>Anatole</chara>’s prominent eyes were
                gazing calmly and fixedly at her, <chara>Natásha</chara>, to break the silence, asked him how he
                liked Moscow. She asked the question and blushed. She felt all the time that by
                talking to him she was doing something improper. <chara>Anatole</chara> smiled as though to
                encourage her.</p>

            <p><q>At first I did not like it much, because what makes a town pleasant ce sont les
                    jolies femmes, * isn’t that so? But now I like it very much indeed,</q> he said,
                looking at her significantly. <q>You’ll come to the costume tournament, Countess? Do
                    come!</q> and putting out his hand to her bouquet and dropping his voice, he
                added, <q>You will be the prettiest there. Do come, dear countess, and give me this
                    flower as a pledge!</q></p>

            <p>* Are the pretty women.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> did not understand what he was saying any more than he did himself, but she
                felt that his incomprehensible words had an improper intention. She did not know
                what to say and turned away as if she had not heard his remark. But as soon as she
                had turned away she felt that he was there, behind, so close behind her.</p>

            <p><q>How is he now? Confused? Angry? Ought I to put it right?</q> she asked herself,
                and she could not refrain from turning round. She looked straight into his eyes, and
                his nearness, self-assurance, and the good-natured tenderness of his smile
                vanquished her. She smiled just as he was doing, gazing straight into his eyes. And
                again she felt with horror that no barrier lay between him and her.</p>

            <p>The curtain rose again. <chara>Anatole</chara> left the box, serene and gay. <chara>Natásha</chara> went back to
                her father in the other box, now quite submissive to the world she found herself in.
                All that was going on before her now seemed quite natural, but on the other hand all
                her previous thoughts of her betrothed, of <chara>Princess Mary</chara>, or of life in the country
                did not once recur to her mind and were as if belonging to a remote past.</p>

            <p>In the fourth act there was some sort of devil who sang waving his arm about, till
                the boards were withdrawn from under him and he disappeared down below. That was the
                only part of the fourth act that <chara>Natásha</chara> saw. She felt agitated and tormented, and
                the cause of this was <chara>Kurágin</chara> whom she could not help watching. As they were leaving
                the theater <chara>Anatole</chara> came up to them, called their carriage, and helped them in. As
                he was putting <chara>Natásha</chara> in he pressed her arm above the elbow. Agitated and flushed
                she turned round. He was looking at her with glittering eyes, smiling tenderly.</p>

            <p>Only after she had reached home was <chara>Natásha</chara> able clearly to think over what had
                happened to her, and suddenly remembering <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> she was horrified, and at
                tea to which all had sat down after the opera, she gave a loud exclamation, flushed,
                and ran out of the room.</p>

            <p><q>O God! I am lost!</q> she said to herself. <q>How could I let him?</q> She sat for
                a long time hiding her flushed face in her hands trying to realize what had happened
                to her, but was unable either to understand what had happened or what she felt.
                Everything seemed dark, obscure, and terrible. There in that enormous, illuminated
                theater where the bare-legged Duport, in a tinsel-decorated jacket, jumped about to
                the music on wet boards, and young girls and old men, and the nearly naked <chara>Hélène</chara>
                with her proud, calm smile, rapturously cried <q>bravo!</q>—there in the presence of
                that <chara>Hélène</chara> it had all seemed clear and simple; but now, alone by herself, it was
                incomprehensible. <q>What is it? What was that terror I felt of him? What is this
                    gnawing of conscience I am feeling now?</q> she thought.</p>

            <p>Only to the old countess at night in bed could <chara>Natásha</chara> have told all she was feeling.
                She knew that <chara>Sónya</chara> with her severe and simple views would either not understand it
                at all or would be horrified at such a confession. So <chara>Natásha</chara> tried to solve what
                was torturing her by herself.</p>

            <p><q>Am I spoiled for <chara>Andrew</chara>’s love or not?</q> she asked herself, and with soothing
                irony replied: <q>What a fool I am to ask that! What did happen to me? Nothing! I
                    have done nothing, I didn’t lead him on at all. Nobody will know and I shall
                    never see him again,</q> she told herself. <q>So it is plain that nothing has
                    happened and there is nothing to repent of, and <chara>Andrew</chara> can love me still. But
                    why <q2>still?</q2> O God, why isn’t he here?</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> quieted herself for a
                moment, but again some instinct told her that though all this was true, and though
                nothing had happened, yet the former purity of her love for <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> had
                perished. And again in imagination she went over her whole conversation with
                <chara>Kurágin</chara>, and again saw the face, gestures, and tender smile of that bold handsome
                man when he pressed her arm.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XI </title>
            <p><chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara> was staying in Moscow because his father had sent him away from
                Petersburg, where he had been spending twenty thousand rubles a year in cash,
                besides running up debts for as much more, which his creditors demanded from his
                father.</p>

            <p>His father announced to him that he would now pay half his debts for the last time,
                but only on condition that he went to Moscow as adjutant to the commander in chief—a
                post his father had procured for him—and would at last try to make a good match
                there. He indicated to him <chara>Princess Mary</chara> and Julie Karágina.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> consented and went to Moscow, where he put up at <chara>Pierre’s house. Pierre</chara>
                received him unwillingly at first, but got used to him after a while, sometimes even
                accompanied him on his carousals, and gave him money under the guise of loans.</p>

            <p>As Shinshín had remarked, from the time of his arrival <chara>Anatole</chara> had turned the heads
                of the Moscow ladies, especially by the fact that he slighted them and plainly
                preferred the gypsy girls and French actresses—with the chief of whom, Mademoiselle
                George, he was said to be on intimate relations. He had never missed a carousal at
                Danílov’s or other Moscow revelers’, drank whole nights through, outvying everyone
                else, and was at all the balls and parties of the best society. There was talk of
                his intrigues with some of the ladies, and he flirted with a few of them at the
                balls. But he did not run after the unmarried girls, especially the rich heiresses
                who were most of them plain. There was a special reason for this, as he had got
                married two years before—a fact known only to his most intimate friends. At that
                time while with his regiment in Poland, a Polish landowner of small means had forced
                him to marry his daughter. <chara>Anatole</chara> had very soon abandoned his wife and, for a
                payment which he agreed to send to his father-in-law, had arranged to be free to
                pass himself off as a bachelor.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> was always content with his position, with himself, and with others. He was
                instinctively and thoroughly convinced that it was impossible for him to live
                otherwise than as he did and that he had never in his life done anything base. He
                was incapable of considering how his actions might affect others or what the
                consequences of this or that action of his might be. He was convinced that, as a
                duck is so made that it must live in water, so God had made him such that he must
                spend thirty thousand rubles a year and always occupy a prominent position in
                society. He believed this so firmly that others, looking at him, were persuaded of
                it too and did not refuse him either a leading place in society or money, which he
                borrowed from anyone and everyone and evidently would not repay.</p>

            <p>He was not a gambler, at any rate he did not care about winning. He was not vain. He
                did not mind what people thought of him. Still less could he be accused of ambition.
                More than once he had vexed his father by spoiling his own career, and he laughed at
                distinctions of all kinds. He was not mean, and did not refuse anyone who asked of
                him. All he cared about was gaiety and women, and as according to his ideas there
                was nothing dishonorable in these tastes, and he was incapable of considering what
                the gratification of his tastes entailed for others, he honestly considered himself
                irreproachable, sincerely despised rogues and bad people, and with a tranquil
                conscience carried his head high.</p>

            <p>Rakes, those male Magdalenes, have a secret feeling of innocence similar to that
                which female Magdalenes have, based on the same hope of forgiveness. <q>All will be
                    forgiven her, for she loved much; and all will be forgiven him, for he enjoyed
                    much.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara>, who had reappeared that year in Moscow after his exile and his Persian
                adventures, and was leading a life of luxury, gambling, and dissipation, associated
                with his old Petersburg comrade <chara>Kurágin</chara> and made use of him for his own ends.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> was sincerely fond of <chara>Dólokhov for his cleverness and audacity. Dólokhov</chara>, who
                needed <chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara>’s name, position, and connections as a bait to draw rich
                young men into his gambling set, made use of him and amused himself at his expense
                without letting the other feel it. Apart from the advantage he derived from <chara>Anatole</chara>,
                the very process of dominating another’s will was in itself a pleasure, a habit, and
                a necessity to <chara>Dólokhov</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> had made a strong impression on <chara>Kurágin</chara>. At supper after the opera he
                described to <chara>Dólokhov</chara> with the air of a connoisseur the attractions of her arms,
                shoulders, feet, and hair and expressed his intention of making love to her. <chara>Anatole</chara>
                had no notion and was incapable of considering what might come of such love-making,
                as he never had any notion of the outcome of any of his actions.</p>

            <p><q>She’s first-rate, my dear fellow, but not for us,</q> replied <chara>Dólokhov</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>I will tell my sister to ask her to dinner,</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>. <q>Eh?</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>You’d better wait till she’s married....</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>You know, I adore little girls, they lose their heads at once,</q> pursued
                <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>You have been caught once already by a <q2>little girl,</q2></q> said <chara>Dólokhov</chara> who
                knew of <chara>Kurágin</chara>’s marriage. <q>Take care!</q></p>

            <p><q>Well, that can’t happen twice! Eh?</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, with a good-humored
                laugh.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XII </title>
            <p>The day after the opera the Rostóvs went nowhere and nobody came to see them. <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                Dmítrievna talked to the count about something which they concealed from <chara>Natásha</chara>.
                <chara>Natásha</chara> guessed they were talking about the old prince and planning something, and
                this disquieted and offended her. She was expecting <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> any moment and
                twice that day sent a manservant to the Vozdvízhenka to ascertain whether he had
                come. He had not arrived. She suffered more now than during her first days in
                Moscow. To her impatience and pining for him were now added the unpleasant
                recollection of her interview with <chara>Princess Mary</chara> and the old prince, and a fear and
                anxiety of which she did not understand the cause. She continually fancied that
                either he would never come or that something would happen to her before he came. She
                could no longer think of him by herself calmly and continuously as she had done
                before. As soon as she began to think of him, the recollection of the old prince, of
                <chara>Princess Mary</chara>, of the theater, and of <chara>Kurágin</chara> mingled with her thoughts. The
                question again presented itself whether she was not guilty, whether she had not
                already broken faith with <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, and again she found herself recalling to
                the minutest detail every word, every gesture, and every shade in the play of
                expression on the face of the man who had been able to arouse in her such an
                incomprehensible and terrifying feeling. To the family <chara>Natásha</chara> seemed livelier than
                usual, but she was far less tranquil and happy than before.</p>

            <p>On Sunday morning <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> invited her visitors to Mass at her parish
                church—the Church of the Assumption built over the graves of victims of the
                plague.</p>

            <p><q>I don’t like those fashionable churches,</q> she said, evidently priding herself
                on her independence of thought. <q>God is the same everywhere. We have an excellent
                    priest, he conducts the service decently and with dignity, and the deacon is the
                    same. What holiness is there in giving concerts in the choir? I don’t like it,
                    it’s just self-indulgence!</q></p>

            <p><chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> liked Sundays and knew how to keep them. Her whole house was
                scrubbed and cleaned on Saturdays; neither she nor the servants worked, and they all
                wore holiday dress and went to church. At her table there were extra dishes at
                dinner, and the servants had vodka and roast goose or suckling pig. But in nothing
                in the house was the holiday so noticeable as in <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s broad, stern
                face, which on that day wore an invariable look of solemn festivity.</p>

            <p>After Mass, when they had finished their coffee in the dining room where the loose
                covers had been removed from the furniture, a servant announced that the carriage
                was ready, and <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> rose with a stern air. She wore her holiday shawl,
                in which she paid calls, and announced that she was going to see <chara>Prince Nicholas</chara>
                Bolkónski to have an explanation with him about <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p>After she had gone, a dressmaker from Madame Suppert-Roguet waited on the Rostóvs,
                and <chara>Natásha</chara>, very glad of this diversion, having shut herself into a room adjoining
                the drawing room, occupied herself trying on the new dresses. Just as she had put on
                a bodice without sleeves and only tacked together, and was turning her head to see
                in the glass how the back fitted, she heard in the drawing room the animated sounds
                of her father’s voice and another’s—a woman’s—that made her flush. It was <chara>Hélène</chara>.
                <chara>Natásha</chara> had not time to take off the bodice before the door opened and Countess
                Bezúkhova, dressed in a purple velvet gown with a high collar, came into the room
                beaming with good-humored amiable smiles.</p>

            <p><q>Oh, my enchantress!</q> she cried to the blushing <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>Charming! No, this
                    is really beyond anything, my dear count,</q> said she to <chara>Count Rostóv</chara> who had
                followed her in. <q>How can you live in Moscow and go nowhere? No, I won’t let you
                    off! Mademoiselle George will recite at my house tonight and there’ll be some
                    people, and if you don’t bring your lovely girls—who are prettier than
                    Mademoiselle George—I won’t know you! My husband is away in Tver or I would send
                    him to fetch you. You must come. You positively must! Between eight and
                    nine.</q></p>

            <p>She nodded to the dressmaker, whom she knew and who had curtsied respectfully to her,
                and seated herself in an armchair beside the looking glass, draping the folds of her
                velvet dress picturesquely. She did not cease chattering good-naturedly and gaily,
                continually praising <chara>Natásha’s beauty. She looked at Natásha</chara>’s dresses and praised
                them, as well as a new dress of her own made of <q>metallic gauze,</q> which she had
                received from Paris, and advised <chara>Natásha</chara> to have one like it.</p>

            <p><q>But anything suits you, my charmer!</q> she remarked.</p>

            <p>A smile of pleasure never left <chara>Natásha</chara>’s face. She felt happy and as if she were
                blossoming under the praise of this dear <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara> who had formerly seemed
                to her so unapproachable and important and was now so kind to her. <chara>Natásha</chara>
                brightened up and felt almost in love with this woman, who was so beautiful and so
                kind. <chara>Hélène</chara> for her part was sincerely delighted with <chara>Natásha</chara> and wished to give
                her a good time. <chara>Anatole</chara> had asked her to bring him and <chara>Natásha</chara> together, and she
                was calling on the Rostóvs for that purpose. The idea of throwing her brother and
                <chara>Natásha</chara> together amused her.</p>

            <p>Though at one time, in Petersburg, she had been annoyed with <chara>Natásha</chara> for drawing
                Borís away, she did not think of that now, and in her own way heartily wished
                <chara>Natásha</chara> well. As she was leaving the Rostóvs she called her protégée aside.</p>

            <p>
                <q>My brother dined with me yesterday—we nearly died of laughter—he ate nothing and
                    kept sighing for you, my charmer! He is madly, quite madly, in love with you, my
                    dear.</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> blushed scarlet when she heard this.</p>

            <p><q>How she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!</q> said <chara>Hélène</chara>. <q>You must
                    certainly come. If you love somebody, my charmer, that is not a reason to shut
                    yourself up. Even if you are engaged, I am sure your fiancé would wish you to go
                    into society rather than be bored to death.</q></p>

            <p><q>So she knows I am engaged, and she and her husband <chara>Pierre—that good Pierre</chara>—have
                    talked and laughed about this. So it’s all right.</q> And again, under <chara>Hélène</chara>’s
                influence, what had seemed terrible now seemed simple and natural. <q>And she is
                    such a grande dame, so kind, and evidently likes me so much. And why not enjoy
                    myself?</q> thought <chara>Natásha</chara>, gazing at <chara>Hélène</chara> with wide-open, wondering
                eyes.</p>

            <p><chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> came back to dinner taciturn and serious, having evidently suffered
                a defeat at the old prince’s. She was still too agitated by the encounter to be able
                to talk of the affair calmly. In answer to the count’s inquiries she replied that
                things were all right and that she would tell about it next day. On hearing of
                <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara>’s visit and the invitation for that evening, <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>
                remarked:</p>

            <p><q>I don’t care to have anything to do with Bezúkhova and don’t advise you to;
                    however, if you’ve promised—go. It will divert your thoughts,</q> she added,
                addressing <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XIII </title>
            <p><chara>Count Rostóv</chara> took the girls to <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara>’s. There were a good many people
                there, but nearly all strangers to <chara>Natásha</chara>. <chara>Count Rostóv</chara> was displeased to see that
                the company consisted almost entirely of men and women known for the freedom of
                their conduct. Mademoiselle George was standing in a corner of the drawing room
                surrounded by young men. There were several Frenchmen present, among them Métivier
                who from the time <chara>Hélène</chara> reached Moscow had been an intimate in her house. The count
                decided not to sit down to cards or let his girls out of his sight and to get away
                as soon as Mademoiselle George’s performance was over.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> was at the door, evidently on the lookout for the Rostóvs. Immediately after
                greeting the count he went up to <chara>Natásha</chara> and followed her. As soon as she saw him
                she was seized by the same feeling she had had at the opera—gratified vanity at his
                admiration of her and fear at the absence of a moral barrier between them.</p>

            <p><chara>Hélène</chara> welcomed <chara>Natásha</chara> delightedly and was loud in admiration of her beauty and her
                dress. Soon after their arrival Mademoiselle George went out of the room to change
                her costume. In the drawing room people began arranging the chairs and taking their
                seats. <chara>Anatole</chara> moved a chair for <chara>Natásha</chara> and was about to sit down beside her, but
                the count, who never lost sight of her, took the seat himself. <chara>Anatole</chara> sat down
                behind her.</p>

            <p>Mademoiselle George, with her bare, fat, dimpled arms, and a red shawl draped over
                one shoulder, came into the space left vacant for her, and assumed an unnatural
                pose. Enthusiastic whispering was audible.</p>

            <p>Mademoiselle George looked sternly and gloomily at the audience and began reciting
                some French verses describing her guilty love for her son. In some places she raised
                her voice, in others she whispered, lifting her head triumphantly; sometimes she
                paused and uttered hoarse sounds, rolling her eyes.</p>

            <p><q>Adorable! divine! delicious!</q> was heard from every side.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> looked at the fat actress, but neither saw nor heard nor understood anything
                of what went on before her. She only felt herself again completely borne away into
                this strange senseless world—so remote from her old world—a world in which it was
                impossible to know what was good or bad, reasonable or senseless. Behind her sat
                <chara>Anatole</chara>, and conscious of his proximity she experienced a frightened sense of
                expectancy.</p>

            <p>After the first monologue the whole company rose and surrounded Mademoiselle George,
                expressing their enthusiasm.</p>

            <p><q>How beautiful she is!</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> remarked to her father who had also risen and
                was moving through the crowd toward the actress.</p>

            <p><q>I don’t think so when I look at you!</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, following <chara>Natásha</chara>. He said
                this at a moment when she alone could hear him. <q>You are enchanting... from the
                    moment I saw you I have never ceased...</q></p>

            <p><q>Come, come, <chara>Natásha</chara>!</q> said the count, as he turned back for his daughter.
                    <q>How beautiful she is!</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> without saying anything stepped up to her
                father and looked at him with surprised inquiring eyes.</p>

            <p>After giving several recitations, Mademoiselle George left, and <chara>Countess Bezúkhova</chara>
                asked her visitors into the ballroom.</p>

            <p>The count wished to go home, but <chara>Hélène</chara> entreated him not to spoil her improvised
                ball, and the Rostóvs stayed on. <chara>Anatole</chara> asked <chara>Natásha</chara> for a valse and as they
                danced he pressed her waist and hand and told her she was bewitching and that he
                loved her. During the écossaise, which she also danced with him, <chara>Anatole</chara> said
                nothing when they happened to be by themselves, but merely gazed at her. <chara>Natásha</chara>
                lifted her frightened eyes to him, but there was such confident tenderness in his
                affectionate look and smile that she could not, whilst looking at him, say what she
                had to say. She lowered her eyes.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t say such things to me. I am betrothed and love another,</q> she said
                rapidly.... She glanced at him.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> was not upset or pained by what she had said.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t speak to me of that! What can I do?</q> said he. <q>I tell you I am madly,
                    madly, in love with you! Is it my fault that you are enchanting?... It’s our
                    turn to begin.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara>, animated and excited, looked about her with wide-open frightened eyes and
                seemed merrier than usual. She understood hardly anything that went on that evening.
                They danced the écossaise and the Grossvater. Her father asked her to come home, but
                she begged to remain. Wherever she went and whomever she was speaking to, she felt
                his eyes upon her. Later on she recalled how she had asked her father to let her go
                to the dressing room to rearrange her dress, that <chara>Hélène</chara> had followed her and spoken
                laughingly of her brother’s love, and that she again met <chara>Anatole</chara> in the little
                sitting room. <chara>Hélène</chara> had disappeared leaving them alone, and <chara>Anatole</chara> had taken her
                hand and said in a tender voice:</p>

            <p><q>I cannot come to visit you but is it possible that I shall never see you? I love
                    you madly. Can I never...?</q> and, blocking her path, he brought his face close
                to hers.</p>

            <p>His large, glittering, masculine eyes were so close to hers that she saw nothing but
                them.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natalie</chara>?</q> he whispered inquiringly while she felt her hands being painfully
                pressed. <q><chara>Natalie</chara>?</q></p>

            <p><q>I don’t understand. I have nothing to say,</q> her eyes replied.</p>

            <p>Burning lips were pressed to hers, and at the same instant she felt herself released,
                and <chara>Hélène</chara>’s footsteps and the rustle of her dress were heard in the room. <chara>Natásha</chara>
                looked round at her, and then, red and trembling, threw a frightened look of inquiry
                at <chara>Anatole</chara> and moved toward the door.</p>

            <p><q>One word, just one, for God’s sake!</q> cried <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p>She paused. She so wanted a word from him that would explain to her what had happened
                and to which she could find no answer.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natalie</chara>, just a word, only one!</q> he kept repeating, evidently not knowing what
                to say and he repeated it till <chara>Hélène</chara> came up to them.</p>

            <p><chara>Hélène</chara> returned with <chara>Natásha</chara> to the drawing room. The Rostóvs went away without
                staying for supper.</p>

            <p>After reaching home <chara>Natásha</chara> did not sleep all night. She was tormented by the
                insoluble question whether she loved <chara>Anatole</chara> or <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>. She loved Prince
                <chara>Andrew</chara>—she remembered distinctly how deeply she loved him. But she also loved
                <chara>Anatole</chara>, of that there was no doubt. <q>Else how could all this have happened?</q>
                thought she. <q>If, after that, I could return his smile when saying good-by, if I
                    was able to let it come to that, it means that I loved him from the first. It
                    means that he is kind, noble, and splendid, and I could not help loving him.
                    What am I to do if I love him and the other one too?</q> she asked herself,
                unable to find an answer to these terrible questions.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XIV </title>
            <p>Morning came with its cares and bustle. Everyone got up and began to move about and
                talk, dressmakers came again. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> appeared, and they were called to
                breakfast. <chara>Natásha</chara> kept looking uneasily at everybody with wide-open eyes, as if
                wishing to intercept every glance directed toward her, and tried to appear the same
                as usual.</p>

            <p>After breakfast, which was her best time, <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> sat down in her armchair
                and called <chara>Natásha</chara> and the count to her.</p>

            <p><q>Well, friends, I have now thought the whole matter over and this is my advice,</q>
                she began. <q>Yesterday, as you know, I went to see Prince Bolkónski. Well, I had a
                    talk with him.... He took it into his head to begin shouting, but I am not one
                    to be shouted down. I said what I had to say!</q></p>

            <p><q>Well, and he?</q> asked the count.</p>

            <p><q>He? He’s crazy... he did not want to listen. But what’s the use of talking? As it
                    is we have worn the poor girl out,</q> said <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>. <q>My advice to
                    you is finish your business and go back home to Otrádnoe... and wait
                there.</q></p>

            <p><q>Oh, no!</q> exclaimed <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Yes, go back,</q> said <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>, <q>and wait there. If your betrothed
                    comes here now—there will be no avoiding a quarrel; but alone with the old man
                    he will talk things over and then come on to you.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Count Rostóv</chara> approved of this suggestion, appreciating its reasonableness. If the old
                man came round it would be all the better to visit him in Moscow or at Bald Hills
                later on; and if not, the wedding, against his wishes, could only be arranged at
                Otrádnoe.</p>

            <p><q>That is perfectly true. And I am sorry I went to see him and took her,</q> said
                the old count.</p>

            <p><q>No, why be sorry? Being here, you had to pay your respects. But if he won’t—that’s
                    his affair,</q> said <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>, looking for something in her reticule.
                    <q>Besides, the trousseau is ready, so there is nothing to wait for; and what is
                    not ready I’ll send after you. Though I don’t like letting you go, it is the
                    best way. So go, with God’s blessing!</q></p>

            <p>Having found what she was looking for in the reticule she handed it to <chara>Natásha</chara>. It
                was a letter from <chara>Princess Mary</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q>She has written to you. How she torments herself, poor thing! She’s afraid you
                    might think that she does not like you.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>But she doesn’t like me,</q> said <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t talk nonsense!</q> cried <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>I shan’t believe anyone, I know she doesn’t like me,</q> replied <chara>Natásha</chara> boldly as
                she took the letter, and her face expressed a cold and angry resolution that caused
                <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> to look at her more intently and to frown.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t answer like that, my good girl!</q> she said. <q>What I say is true! Write
                    an answer!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> did not reply and went to her own room to read <chara>Princess Mary</chara>’s letter.</p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> wrote that she was in despair at the misunderstanding that had occurred
                between them. Whatever her father’s feelings might be, she begged <chara>Natásha</chara> to believe
                that she could not help loving her as the one chosen by her brother, for whose
                happiness she was ready to sacrifice everything.</p>

            <p><q>Do not think, however,</q> she wrote, <q>that my father is ill-disposed toward
                    you. He is an invalid and an old man who must be forgiven; but he is good and
                    magnanimous and will love her who makes his son happy.</q> <chara>Princess Mary</chara> went on
                to ask <chara>Natásha</chara> to fix a time when she could see her again.</p>

            <p>After reading the letter <chara>Natásha</chara> sat down at the writing table to answer it. <q>Dear
                    Princess,</q> she wrote in French quickly and mechanically, and then paused.
                What more could she write after all that had happened the evening before? <q>Yes,
                    yes! All that has happened, and now all is changed,</q> she thought as she sat
                with the letter she had begun before her. <q>Must I break off with him? Must I
                    really? That’s awful...</q> and to escape from these dreadful thoughts she went
                to <chara>Sónya</chara> and began sorting patterns with her.</p>

            <p>After dinner <chara>Natásha</chara> went to her room and again took up <chara>Princess Mary</chara>’s letter.
                    <q>Can it be that it is all over?</q> she thought. <q>Can it be that all this
                    has happened so quickly and has destroyed all that went before?</q> She recalled
                her love for <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> in all its former strength, and at the same time felt
                that she loved <chara>Kurágin</chara>. She vividly pictured herself as <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>’s wife, and
                the scenes of happiness with him she had so often repeated in her imagination, and
                at the same time, aglow with excitement, recalled every detail of yesterday’s
                interview with <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Why could that not be as well?</q> she sometimes asked herself in complete
                bewilderment. <q>Only so could I be completely happy; but now I have to choose, and
                    I can’t be happy without either of them. Only,</q> she thought, <q>to tell
                    <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> what has happened or to hide it from him are both equally
                    impossible. But with that one nothing is spoiled. But am I really to abandon
                    forever the joy of <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>’s love, in which I have lived so long?</q></p>

            <p><q>Please, Miss!</q> whispered a maid entering the room with a mysterious air. <q>A
                    man told me to give you this—</q> and she handed <chara>Natásha</chara> a letter.</p>

            <p><q>Only, for Christ’s sake...</q> the girl went on, as <chara>Natásha</chara>, without thinking,
                mechanically broke the seal and read a love letter from <chara>Anatole</chara>, of which, without
                taking in a word, she understood only that it was a letter from him—from the man she
                loved. Yes, she loved him, or else how could that have happened which had happened?
                And how could she have a love letter from him in her hand?</p>

            <p>With trembling hands <chara>Natásha</chara> held that passionate love letter which <chara>Dólokhov</chara> had
                composed for <chara>Anatole</chara>, and as she read it she found in it an echo of all that she
                herself imagined she was feeling.</p>

            <p><q>Since yesterday evening my fate has been sealed; to be loved by you or to die.
                    There is no other way for me,</q> the letter began. Then he went on to say that
                he knew her parents would not give her to him—for this there were secret reasons he
                could reveal only to her—but that if she loved him she need only say the word yes,
                and no human power could hinder their bliss. Love would conquer all. He would steal
                her away and carry her off to the ends of the earth.</p>

            <p><q>Yes, yes! I love him!</q> thought <chara>Natásha</chara>, reading the letter for the twentieth
                time and finding some peculiarly deep meaning in each word of it.</p>

            <p>That evening <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> was going to the Akhárovs’ and proposed to take the
                girls with her. <chara>Natásha</chara>, pleading a headache, remained at home.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XV </title>
            <p>On returning late in the evening <chara>Sónya</chara> went to <chara>Natásha</chara>’s room, and to her surprise
                found her still dressed and asleep on the sofa. Open on the table, beside her lay
                <chara>Anatole</chara>’s letter. <chara>Sónya</chara> picked it up and read it.</p>

            <p>As she read she glanced at the sleeping <chara>Natásha</chara>, trying to find in her face an
                explanation of what she was reading, but did not find it. Her face was calm, gentle,
                and happy. Clutching her breast to keep herself from choking, <chara>Sónya</chara>, pale and
                trembling with fear and agitation, sat down in an armchair and burst into tears.</p>

            <p><q>How was it I noticed nothing? How could it go so far? Can she have left off loving
                    <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>? And how could she let <chara>Kurágin</chara> go to such lengths? He is a
                    deceiver and a villain, that’s plain! What will Nicholas, dear noble Nicholas,
                    do when he hears of it? So this is the meaning of her excited, resolute,
                    unnatural look the day before yesterday, yesterday, and today,</q> thought
                <chara>Sónya</chara>. <q>But it can’t be that she loves him! She probably opened the letter without
                    knowing who it was from. Probably she is offended by it. She could not do such a
                    thing!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Sónya</chara> wiped away her tears and went up to <chara>Natásha</chara>, again scanning her face.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natásha</chara>!</q> she said, just audibly.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> awoke and saw <chara>Sónya</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Ah, you’re back?</q>
            </p>

            <p>And with the decision and tenderness that often come at the moment of awakening, she
                embraced her friend, but noticing <chara>Sónya</chara>’s look of embarrassment, her own face
                expressed confusion and suspicion.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Sónya</chara>, you’ve read that letter?</q> she demanded.</p>

            <p><q>Yes,</q> answered <chara>Sónya</chara> softly.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> smiled rapturously.</p>

            <p><q>No, <chara>Sónya</chara>, I can’t any longer!</q> she said. <q>I can’t hide it from you any
                    longer. You know, we love one another! <chara>Sónya</chara>, darling, he writes...
                <chara>Sónya</chara>...</q></p>

            <p><chara>Sónya</chara> stared open-eyed at <chara>Natásha</chara>, unable to believe her ears.</p>

            <p><q>And Bolkónski?</q> she asked.</p>

            <p><q>Ah, <chara>Sónya</chara>, if you only knew how happy I am!</q> cried <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>You don’t know
                    what love is....</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>But, <chara>Natásha</chara>, can that be all over?</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> looked at <chara>Sónya</chara> with wide-open eyes as if she could not grasp the
                question.</p>

            <p><q>Well, then, are you refusing <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>?</q> said <chara>Sónya</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Oh, you don’t understand anything! Don’t talk nonsense, just listen!</q> said
                <chara>Natásha</chara>, with momentary vexation.</p>

            <p><q>But I can’t believe it,</q> insisted <chara>Sónya</chara>. <q>I don’t understand. How is it you
                    have loved a man for a whole year and suddenly... Why, you have only seen him
                    three times! <chara>Natásha</chara>, I don’t believe you, you’re joking! In three days to
                    forget everything and so...</q></p>

            <p><q>Three days?</q> said <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>It seems to me I’ve loved him a hundred years. It
                    seems to me that I have never loved anyone before. You can’t understand it....
                    <chara>Sónya</chara>, wait a bit, sit here,</q> and <chara>Natásha</chara> embraced and kissed her.</p>

            <p><q>I had heard that it happens like this, and you must have heard it too, but it’s
                    only now that I feel such love. It’s not the same as before. As soon as I saw
                    him I felt he was my master and I his slave, and that I could not help loving
                    him. Yes, his slave! Whatever he orders I shall do. You don’t understand that.
                    What can I do? What can I do, <chara>Sónya</chara>?</q> cried <chara>Natásha</chara> with a happy yet
                frightened expression.</p>

            <p><q>But think what you are doing,</q> cried <chara>Sónya</chara>. <q>I can’t leave it like this. This
                    secret correspondence... How could you let him go so far?</q> she went on, with
                a horror and disgust she could hardly conceal.</p>

            <p><q>I told you that I have no will,</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> replied. <q>Why can’t you understand?
                    I love him!</q></p>

            <p><q>Then I won’t let it come to that... I shall tell!</q> cried <chara>Sónya</chara>, bursting into
                tears.</p>

            <p><q>What do you mean? For God’s sake... If you tell, you are my enemy!</q> declared
                <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>You want me to be miserable, you want us to be separated....</q></p>

            <p>When she saw <chara>Natásha</chara>’s fright, <chara>Sónya</chara> shed tears of shame and pity for her friend.</p>

            <p><q>But what has happened between you?</q> she asked. <q>What has he said to you? Why
                    doesn’t he come to the house?</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> did not answer her questions.</p>

            <p><q>For God’s sake, <chara>Sónya</chara>, don’t tell anyone, don’t torture me,</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> entreated.
                    <q>Remember no one ought to interfere in such matters! I have confided in
                    you....</q></p>

            <p><q>But why this secrecy? Why doesn’t he come to the house?</q> asked <chara>Sónya</chara>. <q>Why
                    doesn’t he openly ask for your hand? You know <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> gave you complete
                    freedom—if it is really so; but I don’t believe it! <chara>Natásha</chara>, have you considered
                    what these secret reasons can be?</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> looked at <chara>Sónya</chara> with astonishment. Evidently this question presented itself
                to her mind for the first time and she did not know how to answer it.</p>

            <p>
                <q>I don’t know what the reasons are. But there must be reasons!</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Sónya</chara> sighed and shook her head incredulously.</p>

            <p><q>If there were reasons...</q> she began.</p>

            <p>But <chara>Natásha</chara>, guessing her doubts, interrupted her in alarm.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Sónya</chara>, one can’t doubt him! One can’t, one can’t! Don’t you understand?</q> she
                cried.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Does he love you?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Does he love me?</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> repeated with a smile of pity at her friend’s lack of
                comprehension. <q>Why, you have read his letter and you have seen him.</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>But if he is dishonorable?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>He! dishonorable? If you only knew!</q> exclaimed <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>If he is an honorable man he should either declare his intentions or cease seeing
                    you; and if you won’t do this, I will. I will write to him, and I will tell
                    Papa!</q> said <chara>Sónya</chara> resolutely.</p>

            <p><q>But I can’t live without him!</q> cried <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q><chara>Natásha</chara>, I don’t understand you. And what are you saying! Think of your father
                    and of Nicholas.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>I don’t want anyone, I don’t love anyone but him. How dare you say he is
                    dishonorable? Don’t you know that I love him?</q> screamed <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>Go away,
                    <chara>Sónya</chara>! I don’t want to quarrel with you, but go, for God’s sake go! You see how
                    I am suffering!</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> cried angrily, in a voice of despair and repressed
                irritation. <chara>Sónya</chara> burst into sobs and ran from the room.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> went to the table and without a moment’s reflection wrote that answer to
                <chara>Princess Mary</chara> which she had been unable to write all the morning. In this letter she
                said briefly that all their misunderstandings were at an end; that availing herself
                of the magnanimity of <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> who when he went abroad had given her her
                freedom, she begged <chara>Princess Mary</chara> to forget everything and forgive her if she had
                been to blame toward her, but that she could not be his wife. At that moment this
                all seemed quite easy, simple, and clear to <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p>On Friday the Rostóvs were to return to the country, but on Wednesday the count went
                with the prospective purchaser to his estate near Moscow.</p>

            <p>On the day the count left, <chara>Sónya</chara> and <chara>Natásha</chara> were invited to a big dinner party at
                the Karágins’, and <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> took them there. At that party <chara>Natásha</chara> again met
                <chara>Anatole</chara>, and <chara>Sónya</chara> noticed that she spoke to him, trying not to be overheard, and
                that all through dinner she was more agitated than ever. When they got home <chara>Natásha</chara>
                was the first to begin the explanation <chara>Sónya</chara> expected.</p>

            <p><q>There, <chara>Sónya</chara>, you were talking all sorts of nonsense about him,</q> <chara>Natásha</chara> began
                in a mild voice such as children use when they wish to be praised. <q>We have had an
                    explanation today.</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>Well, what happened? What did he say? <chara>Natásha</chara>, how glad I am you’re not angry
                    with me! Tell me everything—the whole truth. What did he say?</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> became thoughtful.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Oh, <chara>Sónya</chara>, if you knew him as I do! He said... He asked me what I had promised
                    Bolkónski. He was glad I was free to refuse him.</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Sónya</chara> sighed sorrowfully.</p>

            <p><q>But you haven’t refused Bolkónski?</q> said she.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Perhaps I have. Perhaps all is over between me and Bolkónski. Why do you think so
                    badly of me?</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>I don’t think anything, only I don’t understand this...</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>Wait a bit, <chara>Sónya</chara>, you’ll understand everything. You’ll see what a man he is! Now
                    don’t think badly of me or of him. I don’t think badly of anyone: I love and
                    pity everybody. But what am I to do?</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Sónya</chara> did not succumb to the tender tone <chara>Natásha</chara> used toward her. The more emotional
                and ingratiating the expression of <chara>Natásha</chara>’s face became, the more serious and stern
                grew <chara>Sónya</chara>’s.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natásha</chara>,</q> said she, <q>you asked me not to speak to you, and I haven’t spoken,
                    but now you yourself have begun. I don’t trust him, <chara>Natásha</chara>. Why this
                    secrecy?</q></p>

            <p><q>Again, again!</q> interrupted <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q><chara>Natásha</chara>, I am afraid for you!</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>Afraid of what?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>I am afraid you’re going to your ruin,</q> said <chara>Sónya</chara> resolutely, and was herself
                horrified at what she had said.</p>

            <p>Anger again showed in <chara>Natásha</chara>’s face.</p>

            <p>
                <q>And I’ll go to my ruin, I will, as soon as possible! It’s not your business! It
                    won’t be you, but I, who’ll suffer. Leave me alone, leave me alone! I hate
                    you!</q>
            </p>

            <p><q><chara>Natásha</chara>!</q> moaned <chara>Sónya</chara>, aghast.</p>

            <p><q>I hate you, I hate you! You’re my enemy forever!</q> And <chara>Natásha</chara> ran out of the
                room.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> did not speak to <chara>Sónya</chara> again and avoided her. With the same expression of
                agitated surprise and guilt she went about the house, taking up now one occupation,
                now another, and at once abandoning them.</p>

            <p>Hard as it was for <chara>Sónya</chara>, she watched her friend and did not let her out of her
                sight.</p>

            <p>The day before the count was to return, <chara>Sónya</chara> noticed that <chara>Natásha</chara> sat by the drawing
                room window all the morning as if expecting something and that she made a sign to an
                officer who drove past, whom <chara>Sónya</chara> took to be <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Sónya</chara> began watching her friend still more attentively and noticed that at dinner and
                all that evening <chara>Natásha</chara> was in a strange and unnatural state. She answered
                questions at random, began sentences she did not finish, and laughed at
                everything.</p>

            <p>After tea <chara>Sónya</chara> noticed a housemaid at <chara>Natásha</chara>’s door timidly waiting to let her
                pass. She let the girl go in, and then listening at the door learned that another
                letter had been delivered.</p>

            <p>Then suddenly it became clear to <chara>Sónya</chara> that <chara>Natásha</chara> had some dreadful plan for that
                evening. <chara>Sónya</chara> knocked at her door. <chara>Natásha</chara> did not let her in.</p>

            <p><q>She will run away with him!</q> thought <chara>Sónya</chara>. <q>She is capable of anything.
                    There was something particularly pathetic and resolute in her face today. She
                    cried as she said good-by to Uncle,</q> <chara>Sónya</chara> remembered. <q>Yes, that’s it, she
                    means to elope with him, but what am I to do?</q> thought she, recalling all the
                signs that clearly indicated that <chara>Natásha</chara> had some terrible intention. <q>The count
                    is away. What am I to do? Write to <chara>Kurágin</chara> demanding an explanation? But what is
                    there to oblige him to reply? Write to <chara>Pierre</chara>, as <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> asked me to in
                    case of some misfortune?... But perhaps she really has already refused
                    Bolkónski—she sent a letter to <chara>Princess Mary</chara> yesterday. And Uncle is
                    away....</q> To tell <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> who had such faith in <chara>Natásha</chara> seemed to
                <chara>Sónya terrible. <q>Well, anyway,</q> thought Sónya</chara> as she stood in the dark passage,
                    <q>now or never I must prove that I remember the family’s goodness to me and
                    that I love Nicholas. Yes! If I don’t sleep for three nights I’ll not leave this
                    passage and will hold her back by force and will and not let the family be
                    disgraced,</q> thought she.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XVI </title>
            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> had lately moved to <chara>Dólokhov</chara>’s. The plan for <chara>Natalie Rostóva</chara>’s abduction had
                been arranged and the preparations made by <chara>Dólokhov</chara> a few days before, and on the
                day that <chara>Sónya</chara>, after listening at <chara>Natásha</chara>’s door, resolved to safeguard her, it was
                to have been put into execution. <chara>Natásha</chara> had promised to come out to <chara>Kurágin</chara> at the
                back porch at ten that evening. <chara>Kurágin</chara> was to put her into a troyka he would have
                ready and to drive her forty miles to the village of Kámenka, where an unfrocked
                priest was in readiness to perform a marriage ceremony over them. At Kámenka a relay
                of horses was to wait which would take them to the Warsaw highroad, and from there
                they would hasten abroad with post horses.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> had a passport, an order for post horses, ten thousand rubles he had taken
                from his sister and another ten thousand borrowed with <chara>Dólokhov</chara>’s help.</p>

            <p>Two witnesses for the mock marriage—Khvóstikov, a retired petty official whom
                <chara>Dólokhov</chara> made use of in his gambling transactions, and Makárin, a retired hussar, a
                kindly, weak fellow who had an unbounded affection for <chara>Kurágin</chara>—were sitting at tea
                in <chara>Dólokhov</chara>’s front room.</p>

            <p>In his large study, the walls of which were hung to the ceiling with Persian rugs,
                bearskins, and weapons, sat <chara>Dólokhov</chara> in a traveling cloak and high boots, at an open
                desk on which lay an abacus and some bundles of paper money. <chara>Anatole</chara>, with uniform
                unbuttoned, walked to and fro from the room where the witnesses were sitting,
                through the study to the room behind, where his French valet and others were packing
                the last of his things. <chara>Dólokhov</chara> was counting the money and noting something
                down.</p>

            <p><q>Well,</q> he said, <q>Khvóstikov must have two thousand.</q></p>

            <p><q>Give it to him, then,</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Makárka</q> (their name for Makárin) <q>will go through fire and water for you for
                    nothing. So here are our accounts all settled,</q> said <chara>Dólokhov</chara>, showing him
                the memorandum. <q>Is that right?</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes, of course,</q> returned <chara>Anatole</chara>, evidently not listening to <chara>Dólokhov</chara> and
                looking straight before him with a smile that did not leave his face.</p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara> banged down the lid of his desk and turned to <chara>Anatole</chara> with an ironic
                smile:</p>

            <p>
                <q>Do you know? You’d really better drop it all. There’s still time!</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Fool,</q> retorted <chara>Anatole</chara>. <q>Don’t talk nonsense! If you only knew... it’s the
                    devil knows what!</q></p>

            <p><q>No, really, give it up!</q> said <chara>Dólokhov</chara>. <q>I am speaking seriously. It’s no
                    joke, this plot you’ve hatched.</q></p>

            <p><q>What, teasing again? Go to the devil! Eh?</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, making a grimace.
                    <q>Really it’s no time for your stupid jokes,</q> and he left the room.</p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara> smiled contemptuously and condescendingly when <chara>Anatole</chara> had gone out.</p>

            <p><q>You wait a bit,</q> he called after him. <q>I’m not joking, I’m talking sense.
                    Come here, come here!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> returned and looked at <chara>Dólokhov</chara>, trying to give him his attention and
                evidently submitting to him involuntarily.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Now listen to me. I’m telling you this for the last time. Why should I joke about
                    it? Did I hinder you? Who arranged everything for you? Who found the priest and
                    got the passport? Who raised the money? I did it all.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Well, thank you for it. Do you think I am not grateful?</q> And <chara>Anatole</chara> sighed and
                embraced <chara>Dólokhov</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q>I helped you, but all the same I must tell you the truth; it is a dangerous
                    business, and if you think about it—a stupid business. Well, you’ll carry her
                    off—all right! Will they let it stop at that? It will come out that you’re
                    already married. Why, they’ll have you in the criminal court....</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Oh, nonsense, nonsense!</q> <chara>Anatole</chara> ejaculated and again made a grimace. <q>Didn’t
                    I explain to you? What?</q> And <chara>Anatole</chara>, with the partiality dull-witted people
                have for any conclusion they have reached by their own reasoning, repeated the
                argument he had already put to <chara>Dólokhov</chara> a hundred times. <q>Didn’t I explain to you
                    that I have come to this conclusion: if this marriage is invalid,</q> he went
                on, crooking one finger, <q>then I have nothing to answer for; but if it is valid,
                    no matter! Abroad no one will know anything about it. Isn’t that so? And don’t
                    talk to me, don’t, don’t.</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>Seriously, you’d better drop it! You’ll only get yourself into a mess!</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Go to the devil!</q> cried <chara>Anatole</chara> and, clutching his hair, left the room, but
                returned at once and dropped into an armchair in front of <chara>Dólokhov</chara> with his feet
                turned under him. <q>It’s the very devil! What? Feel how it beats!</q> He took
                <chara>Dólokhov</chara>’s hand and put it on his heart. <q>What a foot, my dear fellow! What a
                    glance! A goddess!</q> he added in French. <q>What?</q></p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara> with a cold smile and a gleam in his handsome insolent eyes looked at
                him—evidently wishing to get some more amusement out of him.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Well and when the money’s gone, what then?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>What then? Eh?</q> repeated <chara>Anatole</chara>, sincerely perplexed by a thought of the
                future. <q>What then?... Then, I don’t know.... But why talk nonsense!</q> He
                glanced at his watch. <q>It’s time!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> went into the back room.</p>

            <p><q>Now then! Nearly ready? You’re dawdling!</q> he shouted to the servants.</p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara> put away the money, called a footman whom he ordered to bring something for
                them to eat and drink before the journey, and went into the room where Khvóstikov
                and Makárin were sitting.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> lay on the sofa in the study leaning on his elbow and smiling pensively,
                while his handsome lips muttered tenderly to himself.</p>

            <p><q>Come and eat something. Have a drink!</q> <chara>Dólokhov</chara> shouted to him from the other
                room.</p>

            <p><q>I don’t want to,</q> answered <chara>Anatole</chara> continuing to smile.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Come! <chara>Balagá</chara> is here.</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> rose and went into the dining room. <chara>Balagá</chara> was a famous troyka driver who had
                known <chara>Dólokhov</chara> and <chara>Anatole</chara> some six years and had given them good service with his
                troykas. More than once when <chara>Anatole</chara>’s regiment was stationed at Tver he had taken
                him from Tver in the evening, brought him to Moscow by daybreak, and driven him back
                again the next night. More than once he had enabled <chara>Dólokhov</chara> to escape when pursued.
                More than once he had driven them through the town with gypsies and <q>ladykins</q>
                as he called the cocottes. More than once in their service he had run over
                pedestrians and upset vehicles in the streets of Moscow and had always been
                protected from the consequences by <q>my gentlemen</q> as he called them. He had
                ruined more than one horse in their service. More than once they had beaten him, and
                more than once they had made him drunk on champagne and Madeira, which he loved; and
                he knew more than one thing about each of them which would long ago have sent an
                ordinary man to Siberia. They often called <chara>Balagá</chara> into their orgies and made him
                drink and dance at the gypsies’, and more than one thousand rubles of their money
                had passed through his hands. In their service he risked his skin and his life
                twenty times a year, and in their service had lost more horses than the money he had
                from them would buy. But he liked them; liked that mad driving at twelve miles an
                hour, liked upsetting a driver or running down a pedestrian, and flying at full
                gallop through the Moscow streets. He liked to hear those wild, tipsy shouts behind
                him: <q>Get on! Get on!</q> when it was impossible to go any faster. He liked giving
                a painful lash on the neck to some peasant who, more dead than alive, was already
                hurrying out of his way. <q>Real gentlemen!</q> he considered them.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> and <chara>Dólokhov</chara> liked <chara>Balagá</chara> too for his masterly driving and because he liked
                the things they liked. With others <chara>Balagá</chara> bargained, charging twenty-five rubles for
                a two hours’ drive, and rarely drove himself, generally letting his young men do so.
                But with <q>his gentlemen</q> he always drove himself and never demanded anything
                for his work. Only a couple of times a year—when he knew from their valets that they
                had money in hand—he would turn up of a morning quite sober and with a deep bow
                would ask them to help him. The gentlemen always made him sit down.</p>

            <p><q>Do help me out, Theodore Iványch, sir,</q> or <q>your excellency,</q> he would
                say. <q>I am quite out of horses. Let me have what you can to go to the
                fair.</q></p>

            <p>And <chara>Anatole</chara> and <chara>Dólokhov</chara>, when they had money, would give him a thousand or a couple
                of thousand rubles.</p>

            <p><chara>Balagá</chara> was a fair-haired, short, and snub-nosed peasant of about twenty-seven;
                red-faced, with a particularly red thick neck, glittering little eyes, and a small
                beard. He wore a fine, dark-blue, silk-lined cloth coat over a sheepskin.</p>

            <p>On entering the room now he crossed himself, turning toward the front corner of the
                room, and went up to <chara>Dólokhov</chara>, holding out a small, black hand.</p>

            <p><q>Theodore Iványch!</q> he said, bowing.</p>

            <p>
                <q>How d’you do, friend? Well, here he is!</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Good day, your excellency!</q> he said, again holding out his hand to <chara>Anatole</chara> who
                had just come in.</p>

            <p><q>I say, <chara>Balagá</chara>,</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, putting his hands on the man’s shoulders, <q>do
                    you care for me or not? Eh? Now, do me a service.... What horses have you come
                    with? Eh?</q></p>

            <p><q>As your messenger ordered, your special beasts,</q> replied <chara>Balagá</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Well, listen, <chara>Balagá</chara>! Drive all three to death but get me there in three hours.
                    Eh?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>When they are dead, what shall I drive?</q> said <chara>Balagá</chara> with a wink.</p>

            <p><q>Mind, I’ll smash your face in! Don’t make jokes!</q> cried <chara>Anatole</chara>, suddenly
                rolling his eyes.</p>

            <p><q>Why joke?</q> said the driver, laughing. <q>As if I’d grudge my gentlemen
                    anything! As fast as ever the horses can gallop, so fast we’ll go!</q></p>

            <p><q>Ah!</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>. <q>Well, sit down.</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes, sit down!</q> said <chara>Dólokhov</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q>I’ll stand, Theodore Iványch.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Sit down; nonsense! Have a drink!</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, and filled a large glass of
                Madeira for him.</p>

            <p>The driver’s eyes sparkled at the sight of the wine. After refusing it for manners’
                sake, he drank it and wiped his mouth with a red silk handkerchief he took out of
                his cap.</p>

            <p>
                <q>And when are we to start, your excellency?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Well...</q> <chara>Anatole</chara> looked at his watch. <q>We’ll start at once. Mind, <chara>Balagá</chara>!
                    You’ll get there in time? Eh?</q></p>

            <p><q>That depends on our luck in starting, else why shouldn’t we be there in time?</q>
                replied <chara>Balagá</chara>. <q>Didn’t we get you to Tver in seven hours? I think you remember
                    that, your excellency?</q></p>

            <p><q>Do you know, one Christmas I drove from Tver,</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, smilingly at the
                recollection and turning to Makárin who gazed rapturously at him with wide-open
                eyes. <q>Will you believe it, Makárka, it took one’s breath away, the rate we flew.
                    We came across a train of loaded sleighs and drove right over two of them.
                    Eh?</q></p>

            <p><q>Those were horses!</q> <chara>Balagá</chara> continued the tale. <q>That time I’d harnessed two
                    young side horses with the bay in the shafts,</q> he went on, turning to
                <chara>Dólokhov</chara>. <q>Will you believe it, Theodore Iványch, those animals flew forty miles?
                    I couldn’t hold them in, my hands grew numb in the sharp frost so that I threw
                    down the reins—<q2>Catch hold yourself, your excellency!</q2> says I, and I just
                    tumbled on the bottom of the sleigh and sprawled there. It wasn’t a case of
                    urging them on, there was no holding them in till we reached the place. The
                    devils took us there in three hours! Only the near one died of it.</q></p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XVII </title>
            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> went out of the room and returned a few minutes later wearing a fur coat girt
                with a silver belt, and a sable cap jauntily set on one side and very becoming to
                his handsome face. Having looked in a mirror, and standing before <chara>Dólokhov</chara> in the
                same pose he had assumed before it, he lifted a glass of wine.</p>

            <p><q>Well, good-by, Theodore. Thank you for everything and farewell!</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>.
                    <q>Well, comrades and friends...</q> he considered for a moment <q>... of my
                    youth, farewell!</q> he said, turning to Makárin and the others.</p>

            <p>Though they were all going with him, <chara>Anatole</chara> evidently wished to make something
                touching and solemn out of this address to his comrades. He spoke slowly in a loud
                voice and throwing out his chest slightly swayed one leg.</p>

            <p><q>All take glasses; you too, <chara>Balagá</chara>. Well, comrades and friends of my youth, we’ve
                    had our fling and lived and reveled. Eh? And now, when shall we meet again? I am
                    going abroad. We have had a good time—now farewell, lads! To our health!
                    Hurrah!...</q> he cried, and emptying his glass flung it on the floor.</p>

            <p><q>To your health!</q> said <chara>Balagá</chara> who also emptied his glass, and wiped his mouth
                with his handkerchief.</p>

            <p>Makárin embraced <chara>Anatole</chara> with tears in his eyes.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Ah, Prince, how sorry I am to part from you!</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Let’s go. Let’s go!</q> cried <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Balagá</chara> was about to leave the room.</p>

            <p><q>No, stop!</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>. <q>Shut the door; we have first to sit down. That’s
                    the way.</q></p>

            <p>They shut the door and all sat down.</p>

            <p><q>Now, quick march, lads!</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, rising.</p>

            <p>Joseph, his valet, handed him his sabretache and saber, and they all went out into
                the vestibule.</p>

            <p><q>And where’s the fur cloak?</q> asked <chara>Dólokhov</chara>. <q>Hey, Ignátka! Go to Matrëna
                    Matrévna and ask her for the sable cloak. I have heard what elopements are
                    like,</q> continued <chara>Dólokhov</chara> with a wink. <q>Why, she’ll rush out more dead than
                    alive just in the things she is wearing; if you delay at all there’ll be tears
                    and <q2>Papa</q2> and <q2>Mamma,</q2> and she’s frozen in a minute and must go
                    back—but you wrap the fur cloak round her first thing and carry her to the
                    sleigh.</q></p>

            <p>The valet brought a woman’s fox-lined cloak.</p>

            <p><q>Fool, I told you the sable one! Hey, Matrëna, the sable!</q> he shouted so that
                his voice rang far through the rooms.</p>

            <p>A handsome, slim, and pale-faced gypsy girl with glittering black eyes and curly
                blue-black hair, wearing a red shawl, ran out with a sable mantle on her arm.</p>

            <p><q>Here, I don’t grudge it—take it!</q> she said, evidently afraid of her master and
                yet regretful of her cloak.</p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara>, without answering, took the cloak, threw it over Matrëna, and wrapped her
                up in it.</p>

            <p><q>That’s the way,</q> said <chara>Dólokhov</chara>, <q>and then so!</q> and he turned the collar up
                round her head, leaving only a little of the face uncovered. <q>And then so, do you
                    see?</q> and he pushed <chara>Anatole</chara>’s head forward to meet the gap left by the
                collar, through which Matrëna’s brilliant smile was seen.</p>

            <p><q>Well, good-by, Matrëna,</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, kissing her. <q>Ah, my revels here are
                    over. Remember me to Stëshka. There, good-by! Good-by, Matrëna, wish me
                    luck!</q></p>

            <p><q>Well, Prince, may God give you great luck!</q> said Matrëna in her gypsy
                accent.</p>

            <p>Two troykas were standing before the porch and two young drivers were holding the
                horses. <chara>Balagá</chara> took his seat in the front one and holding his elbows high arranged
                the reins deliberately. <chara>Anatole</chara> and <chara>Dólokhov</chara> got in with him. Makárin, Khvóstikov,
                and a valet seated themselves in the other sleigh.</p>

            <p><q>Well, are you ready?</q> asked <chara>Balagá</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Go!</q> he cried, twisting the reins round his hands, and the troyka tore down the
                Nikítski Boulevard.</p>

            <p><q>Tproo! Get out of the way! Hi!... Tproo!...</q> The shouting of <chara>Balagá</chara> and of the
                sturdy young fellow seated on the box was all that could be heard. On the Arbát
                Square the troyka caught against a carriage; something cracked, shouts were heard,
                and the troyka flew along the Arbát Street.</p>

            <p>After taking a turn along the Podnovínski Boulevard, <chara>Balagá</chara> began to rein in, and
                turning back drew up at the crossing of the old Konyúsheny Street.</p>

            <p>The young fellow on the box jumped down to hold the horses and <chara>Anatole</chara> and <chara>Dólokhov</chara>
                went along the pavement. When they reached the gate <chara>Dólokhov</chara> whistled. The whistle
                was answered, and a maidservant ran out.</p>

            <p><q>Come into the courtyard or you’ll be seen; she’ll come out directly,</q> said
                she.</p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara> stayed by the gate. <chara>Anatole</chara> followed the maid into the courtyard, turned the
                corner, and ran up into the porch.</p>

            <p>He was met by Gabriel, <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s gigantic footman.</p>

            <p><q>Come to the mistress, please,</q> said the footman in his deep bass, intercepting
                any retreat.</p>

            <p><q>To what Mistress? Who are you?</q> asked <chara>Anatole</chara> in a breathless whisper.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Kindly step in, my orders are to bring you in.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q><chara>Kurágin</chara>! Come back!</q> shouted <chara>Dólokhov</chara>. <q>Betrayed! Back!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Dólokhov</chara>, after <chara>Anatole</chara> entered, had remained at the wicket gate and was struggling
                with the yard porter who was trying to lock it. With a last desperate effort
                <chara>Dólokhov</chara> pushed the porter aside, and when <chara>Anatole</chara> ran back seized him by the arm,
                pulled him through the wicket, and ran back with him to the troyka.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XVIII </title>
            <p><chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>, having found <chara>Sónya</chara> weeping in the corridor, made her confess
                everything, and intercepting the note to <chara>Natásha she read it and went into Natásha</chara>’s
                room with it in her hand.</p>

            <p><q>You shameless good-for-nothing!</q> said she. <q>I won’t hear a word.</q></p>

            <p>Pushing back <chara>Natásha</chara> who looked at her with astonished but tearless eyes, she locked
                her in; and having given orders to the yard porter to admit the persons who would be
                coming that evening, but not to let them out again, and having told the footman to
                bring them up to her, she seated herself in the drawing room to await the
                abductors.</p>

            <p>When Gabriel came to inform her that the men who had come had run away again, she
                rose frowning, and clasping her hands behind her paced through the rooms a long time
                considering what she should do. Toward midnight she went to <chara>Natásha</chara>’s room fingering
                the key in her pocket. <chara>Sónya</chara> was sitting sobbing in the corridor. <q><chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                    Dmítrievna, for God’s sake let me in to her!</q> she pleaded, but <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                Dmítrievna unlocked the door and went in without giving her an answer....
                    <q>Disgusting, abominable... In my house... horrid girl, hussy! I’m only sorry
                    for her father!</q> thought she, trying to restrain her wrath. <q>Hard as it may
                    be, I’ll tell them all to hold their tongues and will hide it from the
                    count.</q> She entered the room with resolute steps. <chara>Natásha</chara> lying on the sofa,
                her head hidden in her hands, and she did not stir. She was in just the same
                position in which <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> had left her.</p>

            <p><q>A nice girl! Very nice!</q> said <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>. <q>Arranging meetings with
                    lovers in my house! It’s no use pretending: you listen when I speak to you!</q>
                And <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> touched her arm. <q>Listen when I speak! You’ve disgraced
                    yourself like the lowest of hussies. I’d treat you differently, but I’m sorry
                    for your father, so I will conceal it.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> did not change her position, but her whole body heaved with noiseless,
                convulsive sobs which choked her. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> glanced round at <chara>Sónya</chara> and seated
                herself on the sofa beside <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>It’s lucky for him that he escaped me; but I’ll find him!</q> she said in her
                rough voice. <q>Do you hear what I am saying or not?</q> she added.</p>

            <p>She put her large hand under <chara>Natásha</chara>’s face and turned it toward her. Both <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                Dmítrievna and <chara>Sónya</chara> were amazed when they saw how <chara>Natásha</chara> looked. Her eyes were dry
                and glistening, her lips compressed, her cheeks sunken.</p>

            <p><q>Let me be!... What is it to me?... I shall die!</q> she muttered, wrenching
                herself from <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s hands with a vicious effort and sinking down again
                into her former position.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natalie</chara>!</q> said <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>. <q>I wish for your good. Lie still, stay like
                    that then, I won’t touch you. But listen. I won’t tell you how guilty you are.
                    You know that yourself. But when your father comes back tomorrow what am I to
                    tell him? Eh?</q></p>

            <p>Again <chara>Natásha</chara>’s body shook with sobs.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Suppose he finds out, and your brother, and your betrothed?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>I have no betrothed: I have refused him!</q> cried <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>That’s all the same,</q> continued <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>. <q>If they hear of this, will
                    they let it pass? He, your father, I know him... if he challenges him to a duel
                    will that be all right? Eh?</q></p>

            <p><q>Oh, let me be! Why have you interfered at all? Why? Why? Who asked you to?</q>
                shouted <chara>Natásha</chara>, raising herself on the sofa and looking malignantly at <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                Dmítrievna.</p>

            <p><q>But what did you want?</q> cried <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>, growing angry again. <q>Were
                    you kept under lock and key? Who hindered his coming to the house? Why carry you
                    off as if you were some gypsy singing girl?... Well, if he had carried you
                    off... do you think they wouldn’t have found him? Your father, or brother, or
                    your betrothed? And he’s a scoundrel, a wretch—that’s a fact!</q></p>

            <p><q>He is better than any of you!</q> exclaimed <chara>Natásha</chara> getting up. <q>If you hadn’t
                    interfered... Oh, my God! What is it all? What is it? <chara>Sónya</chara>, why?... Go
                    away!</q></p>

            <p>And she burst into sobs with the despairing vehemence with which people bewail
                disasters they feel they have themselves occasioned. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> was to speak
                again but <chara>Natásha</chara> cried out:</p>

            <p><q>Go away! Go away! You all hate and despise me!</q> and she threw herself back on
                the sofa.</p>

            <p><chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> went on admonishing her for some time, enjoining on her that it must
                all be kept from her father and assuring her that nobody would know anything about
                it if only <chara>Natásha</chara> herself would undertake to forget it all and not let anyone see
                that something had happened. <chara>Natásha</chara> did not reply, nor did she sob any longer, but
                she grew cold and had a shivering fit. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> put a pillow under her head,
                covered her with two quilts, and herself brought her some lime-flower water, but
                <chara>Natásha</chara> did not respond to her.</p>

            <p><q>Well, let her sleep,</q> said <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> as she went out of the room
                supposing <chara>Natásha</chara> to be asleep.</p>

            <p>But <chara>Natásha</chara> was not asleep; with pale face and fixed wide-open eyes she looked
                straight before her. All that night she did not sleep or weep and did not speak to
                <chara>Sónya</chara> who got up and went to her several times.</p>

            <p>Next day <chara>Count Rostóv</chara> returned from his estate near Moscow in time for lunch as he
                had promised. He was in very good spirits; the affair with the purchaser was going
                on satisfactorily, and there was nothing to keep him any longer in Moscow, away from
                the countess whom he missed. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> met him and told him that <chara>Natásha</chara> had
                been very unwell the day before and that they had sent for the doctor, but that she
                was better now. <chara>Natásha</chara> had not left her room that morning. With compressed and
                parched lips and dry fixed eyes, she sat at the window, uneasily watching the people
                who drove past and hurriedly glancing round at anyone who entered the room. She was
                evidently expecting news of him and that he would come or would write to her.</p>

            <p>When the count came to see her she turned anxiously round at the sound of a man’s
                footstep, and then her face resumed its cold and malevolent expression. She did not
                even get up to greet him. <q>What is the matter with you, my angel? Are you ill?</q>
                asked the count.</p>

            <p>After a moment’s silence <chara>Natásha</chara> answered: <q>Yes, ill.</q></p>

            <p>In reply to the count’s anxious inquiries as to why she was so dejected and whether
                anything had happened to her betrothed, she assured him that nothing had happened
                and asked him not to worry. <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> confirmed <chara>Natásha</chara>’s assurances that
                nothing had happened. From the pretense of illness, from his daughter’s distress,
                and by the embarrassed faces of <chara>Sónya</chara> and <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>, the count saw clearly
                that something had gone wrong during his absence, but it was so terrible for him to
                think that anything disgraceful had happened to his beloved daughter, and he so
                prized his own cheerful tranquillity, that he avoided inquiries and tried to assure
                himself that nothing particularly had happened; and he was only dissatisfied that
                her indisposition delayed their return to the country.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XIX </title>
            <p>From the day his wife arrived in Moscow <chara>Pierre</chara> had been intending to go away
                somewhere, so as not to be near her. Soon after the Rostóvs came to Moscow the
                effect <chara>Natásha</chara> had on him made him hasten to carry out his intention. He went to
                Tver to see Joseph Alexéevich’s widow, who had long since promised to hand over to
                him some papers of her deceased husband’s.</p>

            <p>When he returned to Moscow <chara>Pierre</chara> was handed a letter from <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> asking
                him to come and see her on a matter of great importance relating to <chara>Andrew</chara> Bolkónski
                and his betrothed. <chara>Pierre</chara> had been avoiding <chara>Natásha</chara> because it seemed to him that
                his feeling for her was stronger than a married man’s should be for his friend’s
                fiancée. Yet some fate constantly threw them together.</p>

            <p><q>What can have happened? And what can they want with me?</q> thought he as he
                dressed to go to <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s. <q>If only <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> would hurry up and
                    come and marry her!</q> thought he on his way to the house.</p>

            <p>On the Tverskóy Boulevard a familiar voice called to him.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Pierre! Been back long?</q> someone shouted. Pierre</chara> raised his head. In a sleigh
                drawn by two gray trotting-horses that were bespattering the dashboard with snow,
                <chara>Anatole and his constant companion Makárin dashed past. Anatole</chara> was sitting upright
                in the classic pose of military dandies, the lower part of his face hidden by his
                beaver collar and his head slightly bent. His face was fresh and rosy, his
                white-plumed hat, tilted to one side, disclosed his curled and pomaded hair
                besprinkled with powdery snow.</p>

            <p><q>Yes, indeed, that’s a true sage,</q> thought <chara>Pierre</chara>. <q>He sees nothing beyond the
                    pleasure of the moment, nothing troubles him and so he is always cheerful,
                    satisfied, and serene. What wouldn’t I give to be like him!</q> he thought
                enviously.</p>

            <p>In <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s anteroom the footman who helped him off with his fur coat said
                that the mistress asked him to come to her bedroom.</p>

            <p>When he opened the ballroom door <chara>Pierre</chara> saw <chara>Natásha</chara> sitting at the window, with a
                thin, pale, and spiteful face. She glanced round at him, frowned, and left the room
                with an expression of cold dignity.</p>

            <p><q>What has happened?</q> asked <chara>Pierre</chara>, entering <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s room.</p>

            <p><q>Fine doings!</q> answered Dmítrievna. <q>For fifty-eight years have I lived in
                    this world and never known anything so disgraceful!</q></p>

            <p>And having put him on his honor not to repeat anything she told him, <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>
                informed him that <chara>Natásha</chara> had refused <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> without her parents’ knowledge
                and that the cause of this was <chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara> into whose society <chara>Pierre</chara>’s wife had
                thrown her and with whom <chara>Natásha</chara> had tried to elope during her father’s absence, in
                order to be married secretly.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> raised his shoulders and listened open-mouthed to what was told him, scarcely
                able to believe his own ears. That <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>’s deeply loved affianced wife—the
                same <chara>Natásha</chara> Rostóva who used to be so charming—should give up Bolkónski for that
                fool <chara>Anatole</chara> who was already secretly married (as <chara>Pierre</chara> knew), and should be so in
                love with him as to agree to run away with him, was something <chara>Pierre</chara> could not
                conceive and could not imagine.</p>

            <p>He could not reconcile the charming impression he had of <chara>Natásha</chara>, whom he had known
                from a child, with this new conception of her baseness, folly, and cruelty. He
                thought of his wife. <q>They are all alike!</q> he said to himself, reflecting that
                he was not the only man unfortunate enough to be tied to a bad woman. But still he
                pitied <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> to the point of tears and sympathized with his wounded pride,
                and the more he pitied his friend the more did he think with contempt and even with
                disgust of that <chara>Natásha</chara> who had just passed him in the ballroom with such a look of
                cold dignity. He did not know that <chara>Natásha</chara>’s soul was overflowing with despair,
                shame, and humiliation, and that it was not her fault that her face happened to
                assume an expression of calm dignity and severity.</p>

            <p><q>But how get married?</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>, in answer to <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>. <q>He could
                    not marry—he is married!</q></p>

            <p><q>Things get worse from hour to hour!</q> ejaculated <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>. <q>A nice
                    youth! What a scoundrel! And she’s expecting him—expecting him since yesterday.
                    She must be told! Then at least she won’t go on expecting him.</q></p>

            <p>After hearing the details of <chara>Anatole</chara>’s marriage from <chara>Pierre</chara>, and giving vent to her
                anger against <chara>Anatole</chara> in words of abuse, <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> told <chara>Pierre</chara> why she had
                sent for him. She was afraid that the count or Bolkónski, who might arrive at any
                moment, if they knew of this affair (which she hoped to hide from them) might
                challenge <chara>Anatole</chara> to a duel, and she therefore asked <chara>Pierre</chara> to tell his
                brother-in-law in her name to leave Moscow and not dare to let her set eyes on him
                again. <chara>Pierre</chara>—only now realizing the danger to the old count, Nicholas, and Prince
                <chara>Andrew</chara>—promised to do as she wished. Having briefly and exactly explained her wishes
                to him, she let him go to the drawing room.</p>

            <p><q>Mind, the count knows nothing. Behave as if you know nothing either,</q> she said.
                    <q>And I will go and tell her it is no use expecting him! And stay to dinner if
                    you care to!</q> she called after <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> met the old count, who seemed nervous and upset. That morning <chara>Natásha</chara> had told
                him that she had rejected Bolkónski.</p>

            <p><q>Troubles, troubles, my dear fellow!</q> he said to <chara>Pierre</chara>. <q>What troubles one
                    has with these girls without their mother! I do so regret having come here.... I
                    will be frank with you. Have you heard she has broken off her engagement without
                    consulting anybody? It’s true this engagement never was much to my liking. Of
                    course he is an excellent man, but still, with his father’s disapproval they
                    wouldn’t have been happy, and <chara>Natásha</chara> won’t lack suitors. Still, it has been
                    going on so long, and to take such a step without father’s or mother’s consent!
                    And now she’s ill, and God knows what! It’s hard, Count, hard to manage
                    daughters in their mother’s absence....</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> saw that the count was much upset and tried to change the subject, but the
                count returned to his troubles.</p>

            <p><chara>Sónya</chara> entered the room with an agitated face.</p>

            <p>
                <q><chara>Natásha</chara> is not quite well; she’s in her room and would like to see you. <chara><c4>Márya</chara>
                    Dmítrievna is with her and she too asks you to come.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Yes, you are a great friend of Bolkónski’s, no doubt she wants to send him a
                    message,</q> said the count. <q>Oh dear! Oh dear! How happy it all was!</q></p>

            <p>And clutching the spare gray locks on his temples the count left the room.</p>

            <p>When <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> told <chara>Natásha that <chara>Anatole</chara> was married, Natásha</chara> did not wish to
                believe it and insisted on having it confirmed by <chara>Pierre himself. <chara>Sónya</chara> told Pierre</chara>
                this as she led him along the corridor to <chara>Natásha</chara>’s room.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara>, pale and stern, was sitting beside <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>, and her eyes,
                glittering feverishly, met <chara>Pierre</chara> with a questioning look the moment he entered. She
                did not smile or nod, but only gazed fixedly at him, and her look asked only one
                thing: was he a friend, or like the others an enemy in regard to <chara>Anatole</chara>? As for
                <chara>Pierre</chara>, he evidently did not exist for her.</p>

            <p><q>He knows all about it,</q> said <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> pointing to <chara>Pierre</chara> and addressing
                <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>Let him tell you whether I have told the truth.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> looked from one to the other as a hunted and wounded animal looks at the
                approaching dogs and sportsmen.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natálya Ilyníchna</chara>,</q> <chara>Pierre</chara> began, dropping his eyes with a feeling of pity for
                her and loathing for the thing he had to do, <q>whether it is true or not should
                    make no difference to you, because...</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>Then it is not true that he’s married!</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>Yes, it is true.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Has he been married long?</q> she asked. <q>On your honor?...</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> gave his word of honor.</p>

            <p><q>Is he still here?</q> she asked, quickly.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Yes, I have just seen him.</q>
            </p>

            <p>She was evidently unable to speak and made a sign with her hands that they should
                leave her alone.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XX </title>
            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> did not stay for dinner, but left the room and went away at once. He drove
                through the town seeking <chara>Anatole Kurágin</chara>, at the thought of whom now the blood
                rushed to his heart and he felt a difficulty in breathing. He was not at the ice
                hills, nor at the gypsies’, nor at Komoneno’s. <chara>Pierre</chara> drove to the Club. In the Club
                all was going on as usual. The members who were assembling for dinner were sitting
                about in groups; they greeted <chara>Pierre</chara> and spoke of the town news. The footman having
                greeted him, knowing his habits and his acquaintances, told him there was a place
                left for him in the small dining room and that Prince Michael Zakhárych was in the
                library, but Paul Timoféevich had not yet arrived. One of <chara>Pierre</chara>’s acquaintances,
                while they were talking about the weather, asked if he had heard of <chara>Kurágin</chara>’s
                abduction of Rostóva which was talked of in the town, and was it true? <chara>Pierre</chara>
                laughed and said it was nonsense for he had just come from the Rostóvs’. He asked
                everyone about <chara>Anatole</chara>. One man told him he had not come yet, and another that he
                was coming to dinner. <chara>Pierre</chara> felt it strange to see this calm, indifferent crowd of
                people unaware of what was going on in his soul. He paced through the ballroom,
                waited till everyone had come, and as <chara>Anatole</chara> had not turned up did not stay for
                dinner but drove home.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara>, for whom <chara>Pierre</chara> was looking, dined that day with <chara>Dólokhov</chara>, consulting him as
                to how to remedy this unfortunate affair. It seemed to him essential to see <chara>Natásha</chara>.
                In the evening he drove to his sister’s to discuss with her how to arrange a
                meeting. When <chara>Pierre</chara> returned home after vainly hunting all over Moscow, his valet
                informed him that Prince <chara>Anatole</chara> was with the countess. The countess’ drawing room
                was full of guests.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> without greeting his wife whom he had not seen since his return—at that moment
                she was more repulsive to him than ever—entered the drawing room and seeing <chara>Anatole</chara>
                went up to him.</p>

            <p><q>Ah, <chara>Pierre</chara>,</q> said the countess going up to her husband. <q>You don’t know what
                    a plight our <chara>Anatole</chara>...</q></p>

            <p>She stopped, seeing in the forward thrust of her husband’s head, in his glowing eyes
                and his resolute gait, the terrible indications of that rage and strength which she
                knew and had herself experienced after his duel with <chara>Dólokhov</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Where you are, there is vice and evil!</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara> to his wife. <q><chara>Anatole</chara>,
                    come with me! I must speak to you,</q> he added in French.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> glanced round at his sister and rose submissively, ready to follow <chara>Pierre</chara>.
                <chara>Pierre</chara>, taking him by the arm, pulled him toward himself and was leading him from
                the room.</p>

            <p><q>If you allow yourself in my drawing room...</q> whispered <chara>Hélène</chara>, but <chara>Pierre</chara> did
                not reply and went out of the room.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> followed him with his usual jaunty step but his face betrayed anxiety.</p>

            <p>Having entered his study <chara>Pierre</chara> closed the door and addressed <chara>Anatole</chara> without looking
                at him.</p>

            <p>
                <q>You promised <chara>Countess Rostóva</chara> to marry her and were about to elope with her, is
                    that so?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Mon cher,</q> answered <chara>Anatole</chara> (their whole conversation was in French), <q>I
                    don’t consider myself bound to answer questions put to me in that tone.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara>’s face, already pale, became distorted by fury. He seized <chara>Anatole</chara> by the
                collar of his uniform with his big hand and shook him from side to side till
                <chara>Anatole</chara>’s face showed a sufficient degree of terror.</p>

            <p><q>When I tell you that I must talk to you!...</q> repeated <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Come now, this is stupid. What?</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, fingering a button of his collar
                that had been wrenched loose with a bit of the cloth.</p>

            <p><q>You’re a scoundrel and a blackguard, and I don’t know what deprives me from the
                    pleasure of smashing your head with this!</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>, expressing himself so
                artificially because he was talking French.</p>

            <p>He took a heavy paperweight and lifted it threateningly, but at once put it back in
                its place.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Did you promise to marry her?</q>
            </p>

            <p>
                <q>I... I didn’t think of it. I never promised, because...</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> interrupted him.</p>

            <p><q>Have you any letters of hers? Any letters?</q> he said, moving toward <chara>Anatole</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> glanced at him and immediately thrust his hand into his pocket and drew out
                his pocketbook.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> took the letter <chara>Anatole</chara> handed him and, pushing aside a table that stood in
                his way, threw himself on the sofa.</p>

            <p><q>I shan’t be violent, don’t be afraid!</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara> in answer to a frightened
                gesture of <chara>Anatole</chara>’s. <q>First, the letters,</q> said he, as if repeating a lesson
                to himself. <q>Secondly,</q> he continued after a short pause, again rising and
                again pacing the room, <q>tomorrow you must get out of Moscow.</q></p>

            <p>
                <q>But how can I?...</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Thirdly,</q> <chara>Pierre</chara> continued without listening to him, <q>you must never breathe
                    a word of what has passed between you and <chara>Countess Rostóva</chara>. I know I can’t
                    prevent your doing so, but if you have a spark of conscience...</q> <chara>Pierre</chara> paced
                the room several times in silence.</p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> sat at a table frowning and biting his lips.</p>

            <p>
                <q>After all, you must understand that besides your pleasure there is such a thing
                    as other people’s happiness and peace, and that you are ruining a whole life for
                    the sake of amusing yourself! Amuse yourself with women like my wife—with them
                    you are within your rights, for they know what you want of them. They are armed
                    against you by the same experience of debauchery; but to promise a maid to marry
                    her... to deceive, to kidnap.... Don’t you understand that it is as mean as
                    beating an old man or a child?...</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> paused and looked at <chara>Anatole</chara> no longer with an angry but with a questioning
                look.</p>

            <p><q>I don’t know about that, eh?</q> said <chara>Anatole</chara>, growing more confident as <chara>Pierre</chara>
                mastered his wrath. <q>I don’t know that and don’t want to,</q> he said, not looking
                at <chara>Pierre</chara> and with a slight tremor of his lower jaw, <q>but you have used such words
                    to me—<q2>mean</q2> and so on—which as a man of honor I can’t allow anyone to
                    use.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> glanced at him with amazement, unable to understand what he wanted.</p>

            <p><q>Though it was tête-à-tête,</q> <chara>Anatole</chara> continued, <q>still I can’t...</q></p>

            <p><q>Is it satisfaction you want?</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara> ironically.</p>

            <p>
                <q>You could at least take back your words. What? If you want me to do as you wish,
                    eh?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>I take them back, I take them back!</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>, <q>and I ask you to forgive
                    me.</q> <chara>Pierre</chara> involuntarily glanced at the loose button. <q>And if you require
                    money for your journey...</q></p>

            <p><chara>Anatole</chara> smiled. The expression of that base and cringing smile, which <chara>Pierre</chara> knew so
                well in his wife, revolted him.</p>

            <p><q>Oh, vile and heartless brood!</q> he exclaimed, and left the room.</p>

            <p>Next day <chara>Anatole</chara> left for Petersburg.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XXI </title>
            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> drove to <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>’s to tell her of the fulfillment of her wish that
                <chara>Kurágin</chara> should be banished from Moscow. The whole house was in a state of alarm and
                commotion. <chara>Natásha</chara> was very ill, having, as <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> told him in secret,
                poisoned herself the night after she had been told that <chara>Anatole</chara> was married, with
                some arsenic she had stealthily procured. After swallowing a little she had been so
                frightened that she woke <chara>Sónya</chara> and told her what she had done. The necessary
                antidotes had been administered in time and she was now out of danger, though still
                so weak that it was out of the question to move her to the country, and so the
                countess had been sent for. <chara>Pierre</chara> saw the distracted count, and <chara>Sónya</chara>, who had a
                tear-stained face, but he could not see <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> dined at the club that day and heard on all sides gossip about the attempted
                abduction of Rostóva. He resolutely denied these rumors, assuring everyone that
                nothing had happened except that his brother-in-law had proposed to her and been
                refused. It seemed to <chara>Pierre</chara> that it was his duty to conceal the whole affair and
                re-establish <chara>Natásha</chara>’s reputation.</p>

            <p>He was awaiting <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>’s return with dread and went every day to the old
                prince’s for news of him.</p>

            <p>Old Prince Bolkónski heard all the rumors current in the town from Mademoiselle
                Bourienne and had read the note to <chara>Princess Mary</chara> in which <chara>Natásha</chara> had broken off her
                engagement. He seemed in better spirits than usual and awaited his son with great
                impatience.</p>

            <p>Some days after <chara>Anatole</chara>’s departure <chara>Pierre</chara> received a note from <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>,
                informing him of his arrival and asking him to come to see him.</p>

            <p>As soon as he reached Moscow, <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> had received from his father <chara>Natásha</chara>’s
                note to <chara>Princess Mary</chara> breaking off her engagement (Mademoiselle Bourienne had
                purloined it from <chara>Princess Mary</chara> and given it to the old prince), and he heard from
                him the story of <chara>Natásha</chara>’s elopement, with additions.</p>

            <p><chara>Prince Andrew</chara> had arrived in the evening and <chara>Pierre</chara> came to see him next morning.
                <chara>Pierre</chara> expected to find <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> in almost the same state as <chara>Natásha</chara> and was
                therefore surprised on entering the drawing room to hear him in the study talking in
                a loud animated voice about some intrigue going on in Petersburg. The old prince’s
                voice and another now and then interrupted him. <chara>Princess Mary</chara> came out to meet
                <chara>Pierre</chara>. She sighed, looking toward the door of the room where <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> was,
                evidently intending to express her sympathy with his sorrow, but <chara>Pierre</chara> saw by her
                face that she was glad both at what had happened and at the way her brother had
                taken the news of <chara>Natásha</chara>’s faithlessness.</p>

            <p><q>He says he expected it,</q> she remarked. <q>I know his pride will not let him
                    express his feelings, but still he has taken it better, far better, than I
                    expected. Evidently it had to be....</q></p>

            <p><q>But is it possible that all is really ended?</q> asked <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Princess Mary</chara> looked at him with astonishment. She did not understand how he could
                ask such a question. <chara>Pierre</chara> went into the study. <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, greatly changed and
                plainly in better health, but with a fresh horizontal wrinkle between his brows,
                stood in civilian dress facing his father and Prince Meshchérski, warmly disputing
                and vigorously gesticulating. The conversation was about Speránski—the news of whose
                sudden exile and alleged treachery had just reached Moscow.</p>

            <p><q>Now he is censured and accused by all who were enthusiastic about him a month
                    ago,</q> <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> was saying, <q>and by those who were unable to understand
                    his aims. To judge a man who is in disfavor and to throw on him all the blame of
                    other men’s mistakes is very easy, but I maintain that if anything good has been
                    accomplished in this reign it was done by him, by him alone.</q></p>

            <p>He paused at the sight of <chara>Pierre</chara>. His face quivered and immediately assumed a
                vindictive expression.</p>

            <p><q>Posterity will do him justice,</q> he concluded, and at once turned to <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Well, how are you? Still getting stouter?</q> he said with animation, but the new
                wrinkle on his forehead deepened. <q>Yes, I am well,</q> he said in answer to
                <chara>Pierre</chara>’s question, and smiled.</p>

            <p>To <chara>Pierre</chara> that smile said plainly: <q>I am well, but my health is now of no use to
                    anyone.</q></p>

            <p>After a few words to <chara>Pierre</chara> about the awful roads from the Polish frontier, about
                people he had met in Switzerland who knew <chara>Pierre</chara>, and about M. Dessalles, whom he
                had brought from abroad to be his son’s tutor, <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> again joined warmly in
                the conversation about Speránski which was still going on between the two old
                men.</p>

            <p><q>If there were treason, or proofs of secret relations with Napoleon, they would
                    have been made public,</q> he said with warmth and haste. <q>I do not, and never
                    did, like Speránski personally, but I like justice!</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> now recognized in his friend a need with which he was only too familiar, to
                get excited and to have arguments about extraneous matters in order to stifle
                thoughts that were too oppressive and too intimate. When Prince Meshchérski had
                left, <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> took <chara>Pierre</chara>’s arm and asked him into the room that had been
                assigned him. A bed had been made up there, and some open portmanteaus and trunks
                stood about. <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> went to one and took out a small casket, from which he
                drew a packet wrapped in paper. He did it all silently and very quickly. He stood up
                and coughed. His face was gloomy and his lips compressed.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Forgive me for troubling you....</q>
            </p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> saw that <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> was going to speak of <chara>Natásha</chara>, and his broad face
                expressed pity and sympathy. This expression irritated <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, and in a
                determined, ringing, and unpleasant tone he continued:</p>

            <p>
                <q>I have received a refusal from <chara>Countess Rostóva</chara> and have heard reports of your
                    brother-in-law having sought her hand, or something of that kind. Is that
                    true?</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>Both true and untrue,</q> <chara>Pierre</chara> began; but <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> interrupted him.</p>

            <p><q>Here are her letters and her portrait,</q> said he.</p>

            <p>He took the packet from the table and handed it to <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p>
                <q>Give this to the countess... if you see her.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>She is very ill,</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Then she is here still?</q> said <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>. <q>And Prince <chara>Kurágin</chara>?</q> he
                added quickly.</p>

            <p>
                <q>He left long ago. She has been at death’s door.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>I much regret her illness,</q> said <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>; and he smiled like his father,
                coldly, maliciously, and unpleasantly.</p>

            <p><q>So Monsieur <chara>Kurágin</chara> has not honored <chara>Countess Rostóva</chara> with his hand?</q> said
                <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, and he snorted several times.</p>

            <p><q>He could not marry, for he was married already,</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Prince Andrew</chara> laughed disagreeably, again reminding one of his father.</p>

            <p><q>And where is your brother-in-law now, if I may ask?</q> he said.</p>

            <p><q>He has gone to Peters... But I don’t know,</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>Well, it doesn’t matter,</q> said <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>. <q>Tell <chara>Countess Rostóva</chara> that she
                    was and is perfectly free and that I wish her all that is good.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> took the packet. <chara>Prince Andrew</chara>, as if trying to remember whether he had
                something more to say, or waiting to see if <chara>Pierre</chara> would say anything, looked
                fixedly at him.</p>

            <p><q>I say, do you remember our discussion in Petersburg?</q> asked <chara>Pierre</chara>,
                    <q>about...</q></p>

            <p><q>Yes,</q> returned <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> hastily. <q>I said that a fallen woman should be
                    forgiven, but I didn’t say I could forgive her. I can’t.</q></p>

            <p><q>But can this be compared...?</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara>Prince Andrew</chara> interrupted him and cried sharply: <q>Yes, ask her hand again, be
                    magnanimous, and so on?... Yes, that would be very noble, but I am unable to
                    follow in that gentleman’s footsteps. If you wish to be my friend never speak to
                    me of that... of all that! Well, good-by. So you’ll give her the packet?</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> left the room and went to the old prince and <chara>Princess Mary</chara>.</p>

            <p>The old man seemed livelier than usual. <chara>Princess Mary</chara> was the same as always, but
                beneath her sympathy for her brother, <chara>Pierre</chara> noticed her satisfaction that the
                engagement had been broken off. Looking at them <chara>Pierre</chara> realized what contempt and
                animosity they all felt for the Rostóvs, and that it was impossible in their
                presence even to mention the name of her who could give up <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> for anyone
                else.</p>

            <p>At dinner the talk turned on the war, the approach of which was becoming evident.
                <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> talked incessantly, arguing now with his father, now with the Swiss
                tutor Dessalles, and showing an unnatural animation, the cause of which <chara>Pierre</chara> so
                well understood.</p>

        </ch>
        <ch>
            <title>CHAPTER XXII </title>
            <p>That same evening <chara>Pierre</chara> went to the Rostóvs’ to fulfill the commission entrusted to
                him. <chara>Natásha</chara> was in bed, the count at the club, and <chara>Pierre</chara>, after giving the letters
                to <chara>Sónya</chara>, went to <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> who was interested to know how <chara>Prince Andrew</chara> had
                taken the news. Ten minutes later <chara>Sónya</chara> came to <chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara>.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Natásha</chara> insists on seeing <chara>Count Peter Kirílovich</chara>,</q> said she.</p>

            <p>
                <q>But how? Are we to take him up to her? The room there has not been tidied up.</q>
            </p>

            <p><q>No, she has dressed and gone into the drawing room,</q> said <chara>Sónya</chara>.</p>

            <p><chara><c4>Márya Dmítrievna</chara> only shrugged her shoulders.</p>

            <p><q>When will her mother come? She has worried me to death! Now mind, don’t tell her
                    everything!</q> said she to <chara>Pierre</chara>. <q>One hasn’t the heart to scold her, she is
                    so much to be pitied, so much to be pitied.</q></p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> was standing in the middle of the drawing room, emaciated, with a pale set
                face, but not at all shamefaced as <chara>Pierre</chara> expected to find her. When he appeared at
                the door she grew flurried, evidently undecided whether to go to meet him or to wait
                till he came up.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> hastened to her. He thought she would give him her hand as usual; but she,
                stepping up to him, stopped, breathing heavily, her arms hanging lifelessly just in
                the pose she used to stand in when she went to the middle of the ballroom to sing,
                but with quite a different expression of face.</p>

            <p><q><chara>Peter Kirílovich</chara>,</q> she began rapidly, <q>Prince Bolkónski was your friend—is
                    your friend,</q> she corrected herself. (It seemed to her that everything that
                had once been must now be different.) <q>He told me once to apply to you...</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> sniffed as he looked at her, but did not speak. Till then he had reproached
                her in his heart and tried to despise her, but he now felt so sorry for her that
                there was no room in his soul for reproach.</p>

            <p><q>He is here now: tell him... to for... forgive me!</q> She stopped and breathed
                still more quickly, but did not shed tears.</p>

            <p><q>Yes... I will tell him,</q> answered <chara>Pierre</chara>; <q>but...</q></p>

            <p>He did not know what to say.</p>

            <p><chara>Natásha</chara> was evidently dismayed at the thought of what he might think she had
                meant.</p>

            <p><q>No, I know all is over,</q> she said hurriedly. <q>No, that can never be. I’m only
                    tormented by the wrong I have done him. Tell him only that I beg him to forgive,
                    forgive, forgive me for everything....</q></p>

            <p>She trembled all over and sat down on a chair.</p>

            <p>A sense of pity he had never before known overflowed <chara>Pierre</chara>’s heart.</p>

            <p><q>I will tell him, I will tell him everything once more,</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>. <q>But...
                    I should like to know one thing....</q></p>

            <p><q>Know what?</q> <chara>Natásha</chara>’s eyes asked.</p>

            <p><q>I should like to know, did you love...</q> <chara>Pierre</chara> did not know how to refer to
                <chara>Anatole</chara> and flushed at the thought of him—<q>did you love that bad man?</q></p>

            <p><q>Don’t call him bad!</q> said <chara>Natásha</chara>. <q>But I don’t know, don’t know at
                    all....</q></p>

            <p>She began to cry and a still greater sense of pity, tenderness, and love welled up in
                <chara>Pierre</chara>. He felt the tears trickle under his spectacles and hoped they would not be
                noticed.</p>

            <p><q>We won’t speak of it any more, my dear,</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>, and his gentle, cordial
                tone suddenly seemed very strange to <chara>Natásha</chara>.</p>

            <p><q>We won’t speak of it, my dear—I’ll tell him everything; but one thing I beg of
                    you, consider me your friend and if you want help, advice, or simply to open
                    your heart to someone—not now, but when your mind is clearer--think of me!</q>
                He took her hand and kissed it. <q>I shall be happy if it’s in my power...</q></p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> grew confused.</p>

            <p><q>Don’t speak to me like that. I am not worth it!</q> exclaimed <chara>Natásha</chara> and turned
                to leave the room, but <chara>Pierre</chara> held her hand.</p>

            <p>He knew he had something more to say to her. But when he said it he was amazed at his
                own words.</p>

            <p><q>Stop, stop! You have your whole life before you,</q> said he to her.</p>

            <p><q>Before me? No! All is over for me,</q> she replied with shame and
                self-abasement.</p>

            <p><q>All over?</q> he repeated. <q>If I were not myself, but the handsomest, cleverest,
                    and best man in the world, and were free, I would this moment ask on my knees
                    for your hand and your love!</q></p>

            <p>For the first time for many days <chara>Natásha</chara> wept tears of gratitude and tenderness, and
                glancing at <chara>Pierre</chara> she went out of the room.</p>

            <p><chara>Pierre</chara> too when she had gone almost ran into the anteroom, restraining tears of
                tenderness and joy that choked him, and without finding the sleeves of his fur cloak
                threw it on and got into his sleigh.</p>

            <p><q>Where to now, your excellency?</q> asked the coachman.</p>

            <p><q>Where to?</q> <chara>Pierre</chara> asked himself. <q>Where can I go now? Surely not to the Club
                    or to pay calls?</q> All men seemed so pitiful, so poor, in comparison with this
                feeling of tenderness and love he experienced: in comparison with that softened,
                grateful, last look she had given him through her tears.</p>

            <p><q>Home!</q> said <chara>Pierre</chara>, and despite twenty-two degrees of frost Fahrenheit he threw
                open the bearskin cloak from his broad chest and inhaled the air with joy.</p>

            <p>It was clear and frosty. Above the dirty, ill-lit streets, above the black roofs,
                stretched the dark starry sky. Only looking up at the sky did <chara>Pierre</chara> cease to feel
                how sordid and humiliating were all mundane things compared with the heights to
                which his soul had just been raised. At the entrance to the Arbát Square an immense
                expanse of dark starry sky presented itself to his eyes. Almost in the center of it,
                above the Prechístenka Boulevard, surrounded and sprinkled on all sides by stars but
                distinguished from them all by its nearness to the earth, its white light, and its
                long uplifted tail, shone the enormous and brilliant comet of 1812—the comet which
                was said to portend all kinds of woes and the end of the world. In <chara>Pierre</chara>, however,
                that comet with its long luminous tail aroused no feeling of fear. On the contrary
                he gazed joyfully, his eyes moist with tears, at this bright comet which, having
                traveled in its orbit with inconceivable velocity through immeasurable space, seemed
                suddenly—like an arrow piercing the earth—to remain fixed in a chosen spot,
                vigorously holding its tail erect, shining and displaying its white light amid
                countless other scintillating stars. It seemed to <chara>Pierre</chara> that this comet fully
                responded to what was passing in his own softened and uplifted soul, now blossoming
                into a new life.</p>
        </ch>

    </book>

      